<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-12-11T05:48:33+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Baiyang Zhang</title><subtitle>A place dedicated to sharing insights and reflections on mathematics, physics, and social sciences. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">罗伯特议事规则</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/%E7%BD%97%E4%BC%AF%E7%89%B9%E8%AE%AE%E4%BA%8B%E8%A7%84%E5%88%99/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="罗伯特议事规则"/><published>2023-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/%E7%BD%97%E4%BC%AF%E7%89%B9%E8%AE%AE%E4%BA%8B%E8%A7%84%E5%88%99</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/%E7%BD%97%E4%BC%AF%E7%89%B9%E8%AE%AE%E4%BA%8B%E8%A7%84%E5%88%99/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="当会议主持人的讲究">当会议主持人的讲究</h2> <p>协商会议的进行 至少需要两名会议官员，一是·（主席），负责主持会议、秉持规则，二是负责会议的书面记录。<em>这二人都该计入法定人数</em>。主持要保证<em>能看到整个会场，所有与会者都能看到他</em>。</p> <p>在指定的开会时间，主持人需要判断出席人数是否满足法定人数，如果满足，主持人当等待会场肃静，或者示意会场肃静，然后大声宣布“会议现在开始／开幕”或“现在进入会议程序”。</p> <h2 id="动议motion">动议(motion)</h2> <p>动议是指在会议中由一名参与者提出的一个<em>正式提议</em>，用以建议采取某项行动或决策。指与会者在 会议之上提出的、需要会议给予处理的正式建议。例如，在一个组织的会议上，有一名成员想提出一个新的议题，要求增加会议预算。</p> <p>成员提出动议，必须向主持人处取得<em>发言权</em>，这要求他从自己的位置上起立，向主持人申请（主持人可以点头示意）。如果数人同时起立申请发言，那么最先起立并称呼主持人的那位将取得发言权。</p> <p>对动议的处理，可分六个步骤</p> <ol> <li>一位成员提出动议。例如，成员A说：“要求增加会议预算。”</li> <li>另（至少）一位成员表示附议，即支持该动议。例如，成员 B 说：“我支持这个动议。”</li> <li>主持人宣布议题。例如，主持人说：“已经有动议提出并得到支持，现在开始讨论增加年度会议预算10%的动议。”</li> <li>与会成员就议题展开辩论。例如，成员们轮流发表意见，有的支持增加预算以改善会议质量，有的则担心预算增加可能会给组织带来财务压力。</li> <li>主持人将议题提请表决。可通过举手等方式进行。</li> <li>主持人宣布表决结果。例如，主持人宣布：“增加年度会议预算10%的动议已通过/未通过。”</li> </ol> <hr/> <p>动议主要分为三大类：主动议（Main Motions）、辅动议（Subsidiary Motions）、和再议类动议（Incidental Motions）。</p> <p><strong>主动议（Main Motions）</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong>定义</strong>：主动议是提出新议题的动议。它旨在引入一个待会议考虑的主题，并在通过后成为会议的正式决定。</li> <li><strong>例子</strong>：比如，在社区会议上，一名成员提出主动议：“我提议社区购买新的游乐设施。”这个动议旨在引入一个全新的议题，即购买游乐设施的议题。</li> </ul> <p><strong>辅动议（Subsidiary Motions）</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong>定义</strong>：辅动议用于修改、延迟或以其他方式影响主动议的处理方式。<em>辅动议通常优先于主动议进行考虑</em>。</li> <li><strong>例子</strong>：假设有人提出主动议：“我提议增加今年的社区保安预算。”接着，另一名成员提出辅动议：“我提议将这个动议提交给财务委员会进行详细评估。”这个辅动议旨在修改处理主动议的方式。</li> </ul> <p><strong>再议类动议（Incidental Motions）</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong>定义</strong>：再议类动议通常与<em>会议的程序</em>有关，它们出现在对会议流程、议程、或成员权利和特权的问题上。<em>这类动议通常在出现时立即处理</em>。</li> <li><strong>例子</strong>：在讨论一项议题时，一名成员可能会提出再议类动议：“我请求对议程进行修改，以便先讨论另一个更紧急的议题。”这个动议直接涉及到会议的议程安排，需要立即处理。</li> </ul> <p>具而言之，主动议可以进一步细分为<strong>实质主动议</strong>（Substantive Main Motion）和<strong>程序主动议</strong>（Procedural Main Motion）。<em>实质主动议是提出一个新的议题或建议，通常与组织的实质性活动或决策有关</em>。例如，在一个社区会议上，一名成员可能提出这样的实质主动议：“我提议社区为公园购置新的儿童游乐设施。”这个动议提出了一个具体的行动建议，即购买新的游乐设施，这是一个实质性的议题。而<em>程序主动议涉及会议的程序或组织运作方式的改变</em>。这类动议通常关注于会议的流程或规则。例如，在一个公司董事会会议上，成员可能提出这样的程序主动议：“我提议修改会议议程，将财务报告的讨论提前到今天的第一项议程。”这个动议关注的是会议的议程安排，是一个程序性的议题。</p> <p>实质主动议和程序主动议的区别在于，前者关注于组织的具体决策或行动，而后者则关注于会议的流程、规则或组织的运作方式。这两种主动议都是会议决策过程中不可或缺的部分。</p> <hr/> <p>辅动议（Subsidiary Motions）可以进一步细分为<strong>附属动议</strong>（Subsidiary Motions）、<strong>优先动议</strong>（Privileged Motions）和<strong>偶发动议</strong>（Incidental Motions）。这三类辅动议都用于影响或处理主动议，但它们的功能和使用场合有所不同。</p> <p><em>附属动议用于直接影响或处理在讨论中的主动议</em>。这些动议可以修改、延迟或以其他方式影响主动议。例如，在会议中，当有成员提出主动议：“我提议增加年度社区活动预算。”随后，另一名成员可能提出附属动议：“我提议将这个动议推迟到下次会议再讨论。”附属动议共计七种：搁置、修改、委托、改期、调整辩论限制、结束辩论、暂停。</p> <p><em>优先动议与会议的主题无关，但由于它们的重要性或紧迫性，优先于其他所有动议处理</em>。这类动议通常涉及会议的基本需求或成员的权利。例如，在长时间的会议中，一名成员可能感到疲劳，因此提出优先动议：“我提议现在休息15分钟。”这个动议由于涉及会议成员的即时需求，因此优先于正在讨论的主动议处理。优先动议共计五种：要求遵守议程、提出权益问题、休息、休会、指定后续会议时间。</p> <p><em>偶发动议通常与会议的程序、议程或成员权利和特权有关</em>，它们出现在对会议流程、议程的问题上。这类动议通常在提出时立即处理。例如，在一次讨论中，如果一名成员认为另一名成员的发言与议题不相关，他可能提出偶发动议：“我要求点名表决，以决定是否继续讨论这个子议题。”这个动议直接影响会议的进行方式和讨论内容。这些辅动议通过提供对主动议的处理方式、会议流程的调整和即时需求的解决，确保了会议的高效和有序进行。偶发动议主要包括程序问题、申诉、暂缓规则、反对考虑、拆分议题、逐段或逐条讨论、起立重新表决、关于表决方式的动议、关于提名的动议、请求免责、请求和咨询等。</p> <hr/> <p><em>再议类动议</em>，所谓再议，即对已经处理的动议再次进行考虑。它分作四种：恢复、取消（或修改）、收回委托、重议。</p> <h3 id="各动议之间的优先关系">各动议之间的优先关系</h3> <p>与名目相反，<em>辅动议优先于主动议</em>；这类似于重要的事情可以在解决了当前次要问题之后从容解决。三大辅动议中： \(\text{偶发动议} \geq \text{优先动议} &gt; \text{附属动议}\) 比如说，会议正在讨论交党费的问题，这是主议题。之后讨论最多能延期几天的问题，这是辅动议里的附属动议。这时有人提出来说我家里着火了，提议推迟会议，这是优先动议，需要马上解决。但是同时又有人提出，家里着火这人压根就不是党员，不应该有开会的资格，会议应该在此人缺席的情况下继续进行，这就是偶发动议，也应当立即解决。这些都解决了之后再回到一开始的附属动议。</p> <h2 id="场与次休息与休会一些术语">场与次、休息与休会，一些术语</h2> <p><strong>“场”与“次”的区别</strong></p> <p>严格说来，“次”的内涵更大，包含了“场”，一次会议可以包含五场、十场会议。所谓一场会议，指组织成员在同一个场合正式集会以处理事务，会议需要连续进行，<em>除了短暂休息，成员不可解散离场</em>。所谓一次会议，指组织成员围绕既定的会议程序、议事日程、时间表或公开宣称的目标而开展的一场、或者连续若干场会议。</p> <p><strong>休息与休会</strong></p> <p>它们的区别在于效果：<em>休息结束后的会议直接从断点继续，如同没有休息一样</em>，没有任何开幕的步骤；<em>休会结束后的会议，一般先有开幕的程序，并且要宣读上一场会议纪要，然后从断点继续</em>。</p> <p><strong>关于会议类型的一些术语</strong></p> <p>会议类型包括例行会议、临时会议、后续会议、年度会议、闭门会 议、公开会议、电子会议等。以下详细解释。</p> <p>以下是关于不同类型会议的解释和示例：</p> <ul> <li>例行会议（Regular Meeting）。按照既定的时间表定期召开的会议，通常有固定的议程。例如，一个公司每月第一周的星期三举行的董事会议，讨论公司运营和财务情况。</li> <li>临时会议（Special Meeting）。为了讨论特定事项而特别召开的会议，通常不在常规会议时间表内。例如，公司因应突发市场变化，紧急召集董事会进行特别讨论。</li> <li>后续会议（Adjourned Meeting）。为了完成之前会议上未完成的议程，而在之后的某个时间继续举行的会议。例如，上周的社区会议因时间限制未能讨论完所有议题，所以本周召开后续会议继续讨论。</li> <li>年度会议（Annual Meeting）。通常每年举行一次的正式会议，用于回顾过去一年的工作并规划未来。例如，一家公司的年度股东大会，总结去年的业绩并讨论未来的战略。</li> <li>闭门会议（Executive Session）。仅限特定成员参加的私密会议，通常用于讨论敏感或保密的议题。例如，董事会就高级管理层的任命进行闭门讨论。</li> <li>公开会议（Open Meeting）。对公众开放的会议，任何人都可以参加旁听。例如，市政府就城市规划举行的公开会议，邀请市民参与讨论和提供反馈。</li> <li>电子会议（Electronic Meeting）。通过电话、视频会议或其他电子方式远程召开的会议。例如，一家跨国公司使用视频会议软件，召集位于不同国家的团队成员进行月度会议。</li> </ul> <h2 id="主动议言简意赅无歧义">主动议：言简意赅无歧义</h2> <p>主动议一旦得到通过，便将作为<em>会议的决定</em>被记录下来。因此，主动议的措辞应该言简意赅且无歧义。不应当包含有争议性，例如歧视类用语。用语要风格明确，与其说“动议不赞成公开发售基金”，不如直接说“动议反对公开发售基金”。</p> <p>一般而言，不要在动议当中说明动议的理由。有人可能赞成动议的行动，但是并不同意所陈述的理由，说得太多反而自找麻烦。如果确实需要说明动议的背景或缘由，可采用决议的形式，在“决定项”前加上“前言”，前言以“鉴于……”开头。比如：鉴于协会所指派的专家在调查后发现河边地带的低层写字楼普遍存在严重火灾隐患。因此决定，成立一个七人委员会，其中四位是……，另外三位由主持人指派，以起草本协会关于贯彻城市防火安全条例的措施，以及对该条例的修改建议。</p> <p>有些主动议不合规则，属于无效动议，应尽量避免。主动议不可与国家法律相冲突自不必言，而同一次会议当中，不应提出本质上与此前已经被否决的主动议内容相同的主动议；无论是不是在同一次会议当中，都不可提出与此前的决议冲突的主动议（若符合重议条件，则可例外）。对于“得到暂时处理”的主动议，只要还在会议处理的时限之内，则不可提出跟它们相似或相反的主动议，以免引起会议混乱。</p> <h2 id="七种附属动议的实操范例">七种附属动议的实操范例</h2> <p><strong>搁置</strong></p> <p>指会议根本不想对主动议做出决定，因为无论它得到通行，还是被 明确否决，都将造成不良后果，当搁置的动议通过，主动议即被忽略、 丢弃，就是说，不再处理，没有结论，而且在<em>本次会议期间不可重提</em>。</p> <p>例如，一家全州规模的专业协会的基层组织会议，面对一个主动议：“决定，本分部支持州协会主席杰姆斯·桑顿先生竞选国会参议员”，但是辩论陷入了棘手的境地，一方面成员尊敬自己的主席，另一方面认为他竞选参议员并不可取。如果直接否决该决议，则可能构成对主席的诋毁，而且无论表决结果如何，都会导致内部的分裂。于是出现了搁置：</p> <p>成员A（取得发言权）：我动议搁置（该决议）。（成员B，C附议）</p> <p>主持人：有人动议有人附议，搁置关于“支持桑顿主席竞选国会参议员”的决议。主持人请A先生发言……</p> <p>如果搁置最终没有通过，主持人宣布结果（不同意搁置）之后，还得继续讨论原决议。</p> <p><strong>修改</strong></p> <p>指在动议得到处理之前，修改它的措辞，甚至在一定程度上修改其含义，修改的内容称作“<em>修正案</em>”。这是所有附属动议当中使用<em>最广泛、最频繁</em>的一种。</p> <p>有些修正案不合规则，需要注意避免，如修正案必须切题，即必须与被修改的动议紧密相关，不能引入任何新议题，只能对原议题进行修改。如果修改后的动议等于在事实上否决了原来的动议，也属违规；如果修正案改变了动议的种类，如原来的动议是“将待决问题改期到下午两点”，修正案为“搁置该问题”，那么这个修正应当无效。</p> <p>举个例子。假设在一个学校董事会的会议上，一名成员提出了一个主动议：“我提议从下个学期开始，将每周的体育课程从两节增加到三节。”在讨论这个动议时，另一名成员可能认为增加的数量过多，因此提出修改动议：“我提议修改这个动议，将体育课程的增加量修改为每周增加一节，而不是两节。”这个修改动议需要得到至少一名其他成员的支持（second）。假设有另一名成员说：“我支持这个修改动议。”一旦修改动议得到支持，它就成为讨论的焦点。成员们会讨论这个修改动议，而不是原始的主动议。在充分讨论之后，会议主持人将指导成员对修改动议进行表决。如果修改动议通过，原始的主动议就被更改为：“我提议从下个学期开始，将每周的体育课程从两节增加到三节。”变为：“我提议从下个学期开始，将每周的体育课程从两节增加到两节半。”如果修改动议未通过，会议将继续讨论原始的未修改的主动议。无论修改动议是否通过，主动议都需要继续进行讨论，并最终进行表决。</p> <p><strong>委托</strong></p> <p>指把一个待决的动议交给专业小组（委员会）讨论，以便使问题得到更充分、详尽的考虑和研究，待讨论结果出炉，再交还会议，回归议事程序。主要有三种引申形式：进入全体委员会（Committee of the Whole）、进入准全体委员会（Quasi Committee of the Whole）、和非正式讨论（Informal Consideration）。下面是这三种形式的详细说明和例子：</p> <ol> <li>进入全体委员会（Committee of the Whole）。这是一种让整个会议以一种更自由的格式讨论某个议题的方式。在这种模式下，会议的正式主持人暂时退位，一般<em>由另一位成员担任全体委员会的主席</em>，以促进讨论的自由氛围，让前主持人不再有特殊的地位，以便会议从新的角度讨论问题。例如，在一次城市议会的会议中，议员们需要深入讨论一个复杂的城市规划项目。为了使讨论更加深入和灵活，议会决定进入全体委员会，此时主持人暂时退位，由另一名议员担任全体委员会主席，以便进行更自由的讨论。实际上，具体做法可以根据组织的实际情况和需求有所调整。在某些情况下，如果会议规模较小或原主持人被认为能够有效促进自由讨论，也可能不更换主持人。</li> <li>进入准全体委员会（Quasi Committee of the Whole）。与全体委员会类似，但主要区别在于主持人不改变。这种方式允许较为自由的讨论，同时保持一定的正式程度。例如，在一家公司的年度董事会议中，董事们决定对一项重大投资进行深入讨论。他们选择进入准全体委员会，由原会议主持人继续主持，但放宽了对发言次数和时长的限制，使讨论更加灵活。</li> <li>非正式讨论（Informal Consideration）。这是一种更加非正式的讨论方式，常用于较小的会议或组织。在这种模式下，放宽了对讨论的正式议事规则的限制，例如对发言次数的限制。例如，在一个社区协会的月度会议中，成员们希望就如何改善社区安全进行深入讨论。他们决定采用非正式讨论的方式，允许成员自由地表达观点，没有严格的发言次数限制。</li> </ol> <p><strong>改期</strong></p> <p>即推迟对当前待决议题的讨论。<em>必须指定什么时间可继续讨论</em>。改期不同于搁置，搁置的意图不在推迟，而是阻挠（kill）动议。</p> <p>例如，在一个非营利组织的董事会会议上，成员们正在讨论一个主动议，比如：“我提议在下个季度为社区中心购买新的电脑设备。”在讨论过程中，可能出现需要更多时间来收集有关电脑设备的信息，或者有关键成员缺席无法立即做出决策的情况。这时，一名成员可能会提出改期动议：“我提议将这个动议改期到下次会议上再讨论，以便我们有时间获取更多的报价信息。”这个改期动议需要得到至少一名其他成员的支持。得到支持后，会议将对该改期动议进行讨论。<em>讨论集中在改期的必要性和可行性上，而不是原始动议的内容</em>。讨论结束后，会议主持人将引导成员对改期动议进行表决。如果改期动议通过，原始关于购买电脑设备的动议将被推迟到下次会议或指定的未来时间；如果改期动议未通过，会议将继续讨论原始的未改期的主动议。</p> <p>无论改期动议是否通过，主动议都将根据改期动议的结果被相应处理，要么继续讨论，要么推迟到后续会议。</p> <p><strong>调整辩论限制</strong></p> <p>包括两种 方式，一是减少发言次数或缩短每次发言的时间，但不限制什么时候结束辩论；二是要求在未来某一时刻结束辩论，或者要求在指定的一段时间之后结束辩论，以提请表决。鉴于该方法会限制讨论的充分性，对决策不利，因此需要“三分之二表决”，且不可在委员会中使用。</p> <p>例如，如果要调整<em>发言的次数</em>或<em>每次发言的时间长度</em>，那么调整辩论限制的格式为：“我动议每次发言控制在5分钟之内”，或“我动议延长李先生的发言时间3分钟”。如果<em>要限制辩论的时间长度</em>，那么调整辩论限制的格式为：“我动议对这个修正案的辩论控制在20分钟之内。” 如果要指定结束辩论并开始表决的时刻，那么调整辩论限制的格式为：“我动议9点结束辩论并开始表决。</p> <p><strong>结束辩论（Move the Previous Question 或 Call for the Question）</strong></p> <p>调整辩论限制只能指定在未来某一时刻结束辩论，结束辩论则可立即结束辩论，此外不接受除暂停以外的任何附属动议。与调整辩论限制一样，结束辩论需要“三分之二表决”，且不可在委员会中使用。</p> <p>这个动议的目的是防止会议过度拖延，尤其是在讨论开始变得重复或偏离主题时。</p> <p>假设在一个社区委员会的会议上，成员们正在讨论一个关于是否在公园安装新的安全照明的主动议。在经过一段时间的讨论后，一些成员可能开始觉得讨论已经足够充分，或者讨论开始偏离主题。这时，一名成员可能会提出结束辩论的动议：“我提议结束辩论，并对当前关于公园安全照明的动议进行表决。”结束辩论的动议同样需要得到二次动议（second），即至少一名其他成员的支持。然后，不同于大多数其他动议，结束辩论的动议不进行讨论（毕竟提出该动议的原因一开始就是因为觉得辩论失去了意义），而是立即进行表决。如果结束辩论动议获得通过（通常需要超过三分之二的成员同意，有些情况下可能需要更高比例的支持），则立即结束当前动议的讨论，并进行表决。如果结束辩论动议未通过，讨论将继续进行。</p> <p>结束辩论动议在以下情况下特别重要：</p> <ul> <li>当讨论开始变得重复无新意时。</li> <li>当讨论偏离了主题或不再产生有价值的信息时。</li> <li>当时间有限且需要迅速做出决策时。</li> </ul> <p><strong>暂停（Recess）</strong></p> <p>指中断待决议题，以便立即响应其他事务。这是多数方的一种<em>隐形权力</em>，能够不经辩论便立即中断对一个动议的讨论，它可能会侵犯少数方与个体的权利，容易被滥用。鉴于此，议事规则规定，暂停只能用于应对突然出现的紧急事务，或者为了提前处理另一件更需要先处理的事务。</p> <p>“暂停动议”作为一种辅动议，可用于休息、处理紧急事务或进行非正式讨论。这种动议通常是针对会议当天内的短暂休息或中断，而非推迟会议到另一天。</p> <p>例如，假设在一个学校董事会的长时间会议中，成员们已经连续工作了数小时，正在讨论一个关于校园设施升级的复杂议题。随着会议进行，成员们可能开始感到疲劳，需要休息或处理个人事务。这时，一名成员可能会提出暂停动议：“我提议我们暂停会议10分钟，以便大家可以休息一下。”得到二次动议（second），即至少一名其他成员的支持后，会议主持人通常会立即对该动议进行表冠决。如果暂停动议获得通过，则会议将暂时中断，成员们可以休息或处理其他事务。如果暂停动议未通过，会议将继续进行，不进行休息。</p> <h3 id="动议的重要性">动议的重要性</h3> <p>暂停动议在以下情况下特别重要：</p> <ul> <li>当成员需要休息或恢复精力，以保持会议效率和成员注意力时。</li> <li>当需要处理突发事件或紧急情况，这些情况需要会议成员立即注意时。</li> <li>当会议进行了长时间而成员需要短暂的休息或餐点时。</li> </ul> <p>这个动议有助于保持会议成员的精神饱满和高效参与，确保会议能在良好的状态下进行。</p> <h2 id="五种优先动议">五种优先动议</h2> <p><strong>要求遵守议程（Call for the Orders of the Day）</strong></p> <p>成员可以要求会议遵守既定的日程、时间表或会议程序，或者要求立即处理指定在此时此刻的普通议程或特别议程。“要求遵守议程”是作为辅动议的一种，用于确保会议按照预定的议程顺序进行。当会议偏离了原定议程，或当某些成员希望会议返回到预定议程上时，可以使用这个动议。</p> <p>设想在一个公司的董事会议上，会议原定有一个详细的议程安排，包括多个关键议题按特定顺序讨论。假设在会议进行中，讨论开始偏离预定议程，或者某些成员试图引入不在议程上的新议题，导致原定的重要议题被忽视。这时，一名成员可能会提出“要求遵守议程”动议：“我要求遵守议程，返回到今天会议安排的第三项议题”。“要求遵守议程”动议一般<em>不需要二次动议</em>（second），并且不进行讨论。会议主持人应立即对此动议进行表决。如果动议通过，则会议必须立即返回到预定的议程上讨论对应的议题。如果动议未通过，会议可以继续当前的讨论或处理其他议题。</p> <p>“要求遵守议程”动议在以下情况下特别重要：</p> <ul> <li>当会议开始偏离预定议程，而这可能导致重要议题未能得到及时或适当的讨论时。</li> <li>当会议时间有限，需要确保所有预定议题都能被讨论到时。</li> <li>当某些议题具有优先级或法律要求必须遵守特定顺序时。</li> </ul> <p>这个动议有助于确保会议的有序性和效率，确保所有计划的议题都能按顺序得到妥善处理。</p> <p><strong>提出权益问题（Raise a Point of Order）</strong></p> <p>指会议组织及其成员出现了一些特殊情况，这些情况涉及会议或成员的基本权益，或者重要，或者紧急，急需给予考虑和解决。权益问题由成员提出，主持人裁定，无须表决，除非主持人的裁定遭到申诉。这也体现了主持人的权力。”提出权益问题”用于指出会议进行过程中的程序错误或违反议事规则的情况。当会议成员认为会议的某个方面违反了会议规则或常规议事程序时，他们可以提出权益问题，以纠正这种情况。</p> <p>权益问题分作两类：</p> <ol> <li>关系到会议<em>整体的</em>基本权益，如涉及组织的安全和保密问题，或者会场环境如取暖、通风、光线出现问题，或者官员、雇员或嘉宾出现了有损会议利益的行为；</li> <li>关系到<em>个人</em>基本权益，如在某位成员未出席的情况之下通过了一份会议纪要，然而这份会议纪要对上次会议该成员出席情况记录有误，或者出现了对某位成员的不当指控等。如果这两类问题发生冲突，<em>会议的权益问题优先于个人的权益问题</em>。</li> </ol> <p>假设在一个社团的会员大会上，成员们正在讨论一项有争议的议题。在讨论过程中，如果会议主持人未能正确执行会议规则（如<em>允许某成员超时发言</em>或未遵守发言顺序），一名会议成员可能会提出权益问题：“我提出权益问题，会议规则规定每位成员的发言时间不得超过两分钟。”提出权益问题<em>不需要二次动议</em>（second），并且应该立即被会议主持人处理。主持人需要就提出的问题做出判断，确定是否确实存在程序上的错误或违规。如果主持人认为提出的权益问题成立，他们将采取措施纠正程序错误，比如重新调整发言顺序或限制发言时间。如果主持人判断权益问题不成立，可以解释为什么当前的做法是合规的。成员如果对主持人的判断不满意，可以提出<em>上诉动议（Appeal）</em>，由全体成员表决是否接受主持人的判断。</p> <p>“提出权益问题”动议在以下情况下特别重要：</p> <ul> <li>确保会议遵循既定的议事规则和程序。</li> <li>保障会议成员的权利和议事的公平性。</li> <li>促进会议的有效和有序进行。</li> </ul> <p>这个动议是一个关键的工具，用于确保会议遵守规则和程序，维护会议的正当性和效率。</p> <p><strong>休息（Recess）</strong></p> <p>“休息”动议用于临时中断会议的进行。它允许参与者在会议期间进行短暂的休息，这通常用于长时间的会议中，以便成员休息、私下讨论或处理紧急事务。如果会议日程或时间表中安排了休息时间，待时间一到，无须动议，主持人即可直接宣布会议休息；如果主持人没有这么做，任何成员都可要求遵守议程。</p> <p>比如，在一次持续了几个小时的组织年会上，参与者可能需要休息、用餐或处理个人事务。在会议进行一段时间后，任何成员都可以提出”休息”动议。例如，一名成员可能会说：”我提议我们现在休息十分钟”。”休息”动议通常需要得到至少一名其他成员的支持（second）。一旦得到支持，会议主持人会对该动议进行表决。如果表决通过，会议将暂时休息，成员们可以离开会议室。如果动议未通过，会议将继续进行。</p> <p>休息动议的主要作用有：</p> <ul> <li>提高效率：定期休息有助于保持会议参与者的精神集中和效率。</li> <li>处理紧急事务：允许参与者处理会议期间可能出现的紧急事务。</li> <li>促进非正式讨论：休息期间，成员们可以进行非正式的交流和讨论，有助于促进思维碰撞和共识形成。</li> </ul> <p><strong>休会（Adjourn）</strong></p> <p>指在<em>已知下次会议何时召开的前提之下</em>，立刻结束本次会议。”休会”动议是一种常见的辅动议，用于结束当前会议的所有正式议程，将会议正式关闭。与”休息”动议（Recess）不同，”休会”动议标志着会议的完全结束，而不是暂时中断。</p> <p>例如，在一个社团的月度会议上，所有的议程项目已经讨论完毕。任何成员都可以在合适的时候提出”休会”动议。比如，一名成员可能会说：”我提议休会。”得到支持后，会议主持人会立即对该动议进行表决，无需讨论。如果表决通过，会议立即结束。如果动议未通过，会议将继续处理剩余的议程或讨论。</p> <p>休会可以保证会议按照正式程序结束，所有议程得到妥善处理；可以帮助控制会议的总体时间，避免无休止的讨论；也为会议参与者提供一个清晰的结束信号，确保所有人都知道会议已经结束。</p> <p><strong>指定后续会议的时间（Fix the Time to Which to Adjourn）</strong></p> <p>用于确定下一次会议的具体时间和日期，尤其是在当前会议即将结束，但下次会议的时间尚未确定的情况下。</p> <p>假设在一个志愿者组织的会议中，成员们正在讨论完接下来的活动计划，但意识到当前会议时间不足以完成所有的议程。在会议接近尾声但仍有重要议题未决时，一名成员可以提出”制定下次会议时间”动议。例如，该成员可能会说：”我提议我们将下一次会议定在下周三下午三点。”“制定下次会议时间”动议通常需要得到至少一名其他成员的支持（second）。得到支持后，会议主持人会对该动议进行表冠决。如果表决通过，下一次会议的时间和日期就按动议中提出的时间确定。如果动议未通过，可能需要重新提议一个不同的时间，或者在会议后通过其他方式确定下次会议时间。</p> <h2 id="偶发动议">偶发动议</h2> <p><strong>程序问题（Point of Order）</strong></p> <p>任何成员，只要认为有违反规则的现象发生，都可提出程序问题，要求主持人裁定并纠正，无须主持人</p> <p>成员A：我要提出程序问题。（或者直接说“程序问题！”） <em>正在发言的成员就座</em>。主持人则请成员A指出哪道程序出现了问 题，或者发言人哪些话违规。准许而发言。</p> <p>又例如，在一个社团的年会上，成员们正在讨论重要的决策事项。如果在讨论过程中，会议主持人未正确遵循议事规则（例如允许某个成员连续发言而不给其他人机会），任何成员都可以提出程序问题动议。例如，该成员可能会说：”我提出程序问题，我们的议事规则规定每位成员在同一议题上只能发言一次。”提出程序问题动议不需要二次动议（second），并且应由会议主持人立即处理。主持人需要判断提出的问题是否成立，并相应地采取措施。如果主持人认为程序问题成立，他们将采取措施纠正程序错误。如果主持人认为程序问题不成立，他们将解释为什么当前的做法是适当的。</p> <p><strong>申诉</strong></p> <p>申诉主要针对主持人而发。通过选举，成员把自己的部分权力与责任，特别是根据议事规则进行裁定的权力与责任，委托给主持人，同时，<em>成员必须保留收回这种授权的手段</em>，这个手段就是申诉。任何两个成员，一个动议，一个附议，便可以把裁定权从主持人手中收回，交还整个会议。</p> <p>只要是主持人做出的裁定，成员都可提出申诉。然后由主持人准确描述当前争议的问题，必要的话还可以阐述自己裁定的理由，宣布议题，提请表决。</p> <p><strong>暂缓规则（Suspend the Rules）</strong></p> <p>暂缓规则用于临时搁置或修改会议的一些特定<em>规则</em>，以便处理特殊情况或加快议程的进程。这种动议通常用于暂时放弃那些阻碍会议进行的正规程序规则，但它<em>不能用来暂停那些受到组织宪章、法律、或其他不可变规定所保护的规则</em>。</p> <p>例如，在一个俱乐部的例会中，成员们想要快速通过一个常规但非争议性的议题，以便有更多时间讨论另一个紧急且重要的议题。一个成员可能会提出”暂缓规则”动议：“我提议暂缓关于每项议题至少讨论10分钟的规则，以便我们可以快速通过当前的议题。<em>暂缓规则动议通常需要得到较高比例的支持</em>，如二分之三多数同意。这个动议不需要二次动议（second），并且应由会议主持人立即对其进行表决。如果表决通过，会议中的特定规则将暂时被搁置，以适应当前的特殊需求。如果动议未通过，会议将继续按照原有规则进行。</p> <p>暂缓规则动议提供了在特殊情况下调整会议流程的灵活性。有助于会议在必要时快速处理某些议题，特别是在时间紧迫或议题简单明了的情况下。同时也允许会议在不常见的或紧急情况下适当调整规则，以更好地满足会议目的。</p> <p><strong>反对考虑（Objection to the Consideration of a Question）</strong></p> <p>如果会议认为根本不应该或不值得对某个实质主动议进行讨论，则可提出反对考虑，直接阻挠。这个动议通常在议题刚被提出时使用，用于表达对讨论该议题的强烈反对，通常是因为议题被认为是不适当、冒犯性或与会议目的无关。</p> <p>比如，在一个组织的会议上，一个成员提出了一个可能引起争议或被认为不适当的议题。另一个成员可能立即提出“反对考虑”动议，例如说：“我反对考虑这个问题。”这个动议不需要二次动议（second），并且应立即进行表决。此类动议通常不进行讨论。如果大多数成员投票支持“反对考虑”，则该议题将不会被讨论或表决。如果大多数成员投票反对或动议未获得足够支持，则会议将继续讨论该议题。</p> <p>“反对考虑”动议是一种有效的工具，用于确保会议的顺利进行，防止不必要或不适当的讨论，保护会议的有效性和专业性。</p> <p><strong>拆分议题（Division of a Question）</strong></p> <p>如果一个动议，虽然关于同一主题，却包含若干部分，而且每一部分都可作为一个动议，那么可以将它们分开考虑并分别表决。拆分议题用于将复杂或多部分组成的主动议拆分为几个独立的议题，以便分别进行讨论和表决。这种动议适用于当原始动议包含多个相互独立且需要单独决策的部分时。</p> <p>例如，在一个组织的会议上，一个成员提出了一个包含多个部分的复杂动议，如“我提议我们增加预算用于购买新的办公设备，并且调整工作时间。”另一个成员可能觉得这些议题应该分别讨论和决定，因此提出“拆分议题”动议：“我提议将这个动议拆分为两部分：一部分关于增加预算购买办公设备，另一部分关于调整工作时间”。”拆分议题”动议通常需要得到至少一名其他成员的支持（second）。得到支持后，会议主持人会对该动议进行表决。如果表决通过，原始动议就被拆分成几部分，每部分将分别进行讨论和表决。如果动议未通过，原始的复合动议将作为一个整体继续进行讨论和表决。</p> <p>动议有助于使会议对复杂议题的讨论更加清晰和专注，保证会议能够对每个部分的议题进行充分和细致的审查，同时使会议成员能够对每个独立的议题作出更明确的决策，增加决策的透明度和成员的参与度。</p> <p><strong>逐段或逐条讨论（Consider by Paragraph or Seriatim）</strong></p> <p>一个篇幅较长的动议，可能会包含系列决议、段落或章节，它们事关一个主题，不可拆分，但是可以逐一对每个部分展开辩论与修改，如果主持人没有主动采取这样的处理方式，成员则可提出逐段讨论或逐条讨论。不过，如果一份文件所包含的主动议分别涉及不同主题，那么只要有一位成员反对，便不能逐段或逐条讨论，只能拆分议题。</p> <p>比如，在一个组织的年度大会上，需要审议和修改该组织的章程或一份长期规划文件。主持人或会议成员可以提议按照章程或文件的结构逐段（或逐条、逐项）进行讨论。通常，这不需要正式的动议，但可以通过动议来建议这种讨论方式。在逐段讨论的过程中，会议将集中于文本的一个特定段落或条款。对每个部分的讨论完成后，再移至下一个部分，直至整个文本讨论完毕。每个部分可以分别进行修改和表决，或在整个文本讨论完后，对所有提出的修改进行统一表决。</p> <p>逐段或逐条讨论有助于使对复杂文档的审查更有组织和系统性，确保每个部分都得到适当的注意和考虑，避免遗漏或忽视重要细节，同时使会议成员能够对文档的每个部分发表意见，增加整个过程的透明度和参与性。</p> <p><strong>起立重新表决（Division of the Assembly）</strong></p> <p>如果刚刚完成的表决采用的是口头表决，或是未予计数的举手表 决，那么任何成员都有权质疑表决结果，提出起立重新表决。重要的是，当一个成员要求进行起立表决时，这个请求<em>不需要二次动议（second）</em>。一旦提出，会议主持人应立即采取行动来进行起立表决，除非显然是为了延误会议而提出的无效请求。起立表决可以清楚地展示支持和反对的比例，因为它要求成员通过站立的方式来表示他们的投票意向。</p> <p><strong>关于表决方式的动议（Motion Regarding Voting Method）</strong></p> <p>关于表决方式的动议用于确定或改变某个具体议题的表决方式。这种动议允许会议成员提议采用特定的表决方法，如无记名投票、计数投票、举手投票或口头投票等，来替代或修改会议默认的表决方式。</p> <p>例如，在一个社团的年会上，成员们需要决定是否接受一项关于财务支出的提案。如果某个成员希望确保表决结果的准确性和透明性，他们可能会提出关于表决方式的动议：“我提议我们对这个财务支出提案进行无记名投票。”这种动议通常需要得到至少一名其他成员的支持（second）。得到支持后，会议主持人会对该动议进行表决。如果表决通过，那么接下来对提案的表决将采用提议的表决方法。如果动议未通过，会议将继续使用默认或之前决定的表决方式。</p> <p><strong>关于提名的动议</strong></p> <p>这种动议通常出现在需要选举官员或委员会成员时，可以用来开启、关闭提名过程，或修改提名程序。</p> <p>比如，在一个组织的年度选举会议上，成员们需要选举新的董事会成员。成员可能提出与提名过程相关的不同动议，例如：</p> <ul> <li>开始提名：一名成员可能提出动议：“我提议开始对董事会成员职位的提名。”</li> <li>关闭提名：在一定时间或所有意愿成员都被提名后，成员可能提出：“我提议关闭董事会成员的提名。”</li> <li>修改提名程序：有时也可能提出修改提名过程的动议，如提议采用无记名提名方式或提议提名时需有特定的支持者数量。</li> </ul> <p>这些动议通常需要得到至少一名其他成员的支持（second）。得到支持后，会议主持人会对该动议进行表冠决。如果表决通过，提名过程将按照提议的方式进行。如果动议未通过，则继续使用原有的提名方式或过程。</p> <p><strong>请求免责（Request for Excuse）</strong></p> <p>请求免责通常指的是会议成员就某项职责、任务或会议出席要求提出的正式请求，以获得免除或推迟履行这些职责的许可。这种请求可能是由于各种原因，如个人紧急事务、健康问题或其他无法控制的情况。</p> <p>例如，在一个董事会会议上，一名成员可能因为个人健康问题或紧急家庭情况，无法履行其作为董事的职责。该成员或另一名代表他的成员可以在会议上提出请求免责：“由于个人健康原因，我请求被免除下月的董事会职责。”这种请求通常会被会议主持人带到会议上进行讨论，可能需要进行表决决定是否批准该请求。如果会议成员同意该请求，该成员将被免除相关职责，直至他们能够恢复履行职责；如果请求未被批准，该成员仍需尽力履行其职责。</p> <p>请求免责提供了一种机制，允许成员在特殊情况下获得必要的灵活性，同时确保组织的工作不会因个别成员的特殊情况而受到不必要的干扰。通过在会议上公开讨论这些请求，增加了组织运作的透明度。请求免责有助于在<em>尊重个人情况</em>和<em>维护组织整体利益</em>之间找到平衡。</p> <p><strong>请求和咨询（Request and Inquiry）</strong></p> <p>通常指的是会议成员提出的关于会议程序、议事规则、议题内容或与会议相关的其他问题的正式请求或询问。这些请求和咨询旨在帮助成员更好地理解和参与会议过程，确保会议的顺利进行。成员可能不确定会议的某个程序如何操作，比如如何提出动议或动议的具体含义。成员可能问：“我可以在这个时候提出修改动议吗？”或“这个程序动议是指什么？”</p> <p>例如，成员可能对正在讨论的议题内容或背景需要更多的信息。成员可能问：“我们讨论的预算提案包括哪些主要项目？”或“此前的决议对当前讨论有何影响？”</p> <p>在会议中，这些请求和咨询通常由会议主持人或有相关知识的成员回答。主持人可能需要参考会议的规则手册、先前的决议或其他文档来提供准确的回答。对于复杂或特殊的问题，主持人可能建议暂停会议，以便进行更深入的研究或咨询。</p> <h2 id="再议类动议incidental-motions">再议类动议（Incidental Motions）</h2> <p>这一类动议可以让动议原地复活，死而复生。</p> <p><strong>恢复（reconsider）</strong></p> <p>其意图在于把暂停的动议或绑定在一起的系列动议重新提交给会议，作为待决动议来讨论。被暂停的动议始终处于暂停状态，可以在本次会议期间恢复；如果与下一次例行会议的时间间隔没有超过三个月，除了在本次会议期间，还可在下一次会议期间恢复。如果在上述时间范围之内都没有被恢复，那么暂停的动议自动失效，不再处于暂停状态，不过可以作为新动议重提。</p> <p>恢复动议允许会议成员提出重新考虑之前已经做出的决定。通常，”恢复”动议用于重新审议一个已经投票决定的议题，特别是如果有新信息出现，或者有人认为先前的决定需要重新评估。</p> <p>例如，在一个董事会的会议中，成员们可能已经对一个重要议题进行了投票，比如批准一项新的投资计划。如果在投票后出现了新的信息，或者有成员认为需要重新考虑之前的决定，他们可以提出”恢复”动议：“我提议重新考虑我们关于新投资计划的决定”。”恢复”动议通常需要由在原始表决中投了赞成票的成员提出，并且需要得到至少一名其他成员的支持（second）。之后，会议主持人会将该动议带到会议上进行表决。如果表决通过，原来的决定将被暂停，会议将重新对该议题进行讨论和表决。如果动议未通过，原先的决定将继续有效。</p> <p><strong>取消或修改已经通过的决议（Rescind or Amend Something Previously Adopted）</strong></p> <p>该动议用于改变或撤销之前会议上已经作出的决策，允许一个组织回过头来改变或取消先前做出的正式决定，这通常是基于情况的变化、新的信息或成员对原决定的重新考虑。</p> <p>例如，一个社团在几个月前的会议上通过了一项关于增加会费的决议。随着时间的推移，如果一些成员认为增加会费是不必要或不合适的，他们可以提出一个取消或修改该决议的动议：“我提议取消我们之前关于增加会费的决议。”或者“我提议修改我们关于增加会费的决议，将增幅调整为更低。”这类动议<em>通常需要得到较高比例的支持</em>，比如二分之三多数的同意。它需要得到至少一名其他成员的支持（second），然后在会议上进行表决。如果表决通过，原先的决议将被取消或按照新的提议进行修改。如果动议未通过，原先的决议将继续保持有效。</p> <p>总的来说，“取消或修改已经通过的决议”动议是一种重要的议事工具，用于确保组织的决策能够及时反映最新的情况和成员的共识。</p> <p><strong>收回动议（Withdraw a Motion）</strong></p> <p>收回委托指的是提议者<em>在动议还未被会议正式采纳或拒绝之前</em>，请求撤回他们所提出的动议。这通常发生在动议被正式讨论之前，但也可以在讨论过程中提出，只要尚未进行最终表决。</p> <p>比如，在一个组织的会议中，一名成员提出了关于更改会议时间的动议。在动议被讨论之前或讨论过程中，如果提议者发现了新信息，或者认为他们的动议不再合适或有争议，他们可以提出要收回他们的动议：“我请求撤回我关于更改会议时间的动议。”在动议被讨论之前，提议者可以单方面撤回动议。如果动议已经被讨论，通常需要得到会议的同意才能撤回。如果动议被允许撤回，那么该动议就好像从未提出过一样，会议将继续处理其他议题。</p> <p><strong>重议（Reconsider）</strong></p> <p>即把一个已经表决过的动议拿回来重新展开辩论和表决。其意图在于及时纠正那些草率的、被误导的或者本质上错误的决定。因为重议容易造成会议效率低下，所以有极严格的限制。一是重议的主体，必须是参与表决的多数方；二是重议的时间：如果是长度只有一天的一次会议，那么重议只能在被重议的动议表决当天提出；如果是长度超过一天的一次会议，那么提出重议的时间可以延长到下一个会议日。</p> <p>例如，在一个董事会会议中，成员们可能已经对一项重要的投资提案进行了表决。如果在表决后出现了新的信息，或者有成员认为需要重新考虑之前的决定，他们可以提出“重议”动议：“我提议重新考虑我们关于投资提案的决定。”重议”动议通常需要由原始表决中投了赞成票的成员提出，并且需要得到至少一名其他成员的支持（second）。之后，会议主持人会将该动议带到会议上进行表决。如果表决通过，原来的决定将被暂停，会议将重新对该议题进行讨论和表冠决。如果动议未通过，原先的决定将继续保持有效。</p> <p>总的来说，“重议”动议是一种重要的议事工具，用于确保会议决策能够在必要时进行适时的修正或重新评估。</p> <h2 id="一事一议原则">一事一议原则</h2> <p>一事一议原则（One Subject at a Time Rule）要求<em>在任何时候，会议只能讨论一个议题</em>，直到处理完毕后才能转移到下一个议题。这有助于确保会议的有序和高效，防止议题间的混淆和不必要的混乱。</p> <p>具体来说，一事一议原则意味着：</p> <ol> <li> <p>议题专注性：当一个动议（motion）被提出并处于讨论阶段时，所有的讨论必须仅限于这个动议的内容。不允许引入与当前动议无关的新议题或其他动议。</p> </li> <li> <p>动议处理完整性：在当前动议得到充分讨论并最终表决（通过或否决）之前，不得开始讨论另一个动议或议题。</p> </li> <li> <p>排他性：如果某个动议需要时间来决定或需要进一步信息，可以将其搁置，但在处理这个动议的过程中，不能同时讨论其他动议。</p> </li> </ol> <p>例如，假设在一个组织的会议上，有成员提出了关于增加年度预算的动议。根据一事一议原则，讨论必须集中在这个预算增加的议题上，直到决定是否接受或拒绝这个动议。在此期间，不可以将讨论转移到其他议题，如更改会议时间或引入新的活动计划，除非当前议题被正式解决或搁置。</p> <p>这个原则有助于保持会议的焦点，确保每个议题都得到适当的关注和处理。</p> <h2 id="动议的重提和不良动议">动议的重提和不良动议</h2> <p>一般而言，同一次会议之上，相同的或者本质上相同的动议，不得重复出现，除非使用再议类动议，如取消或修改已经通过的决定，或重 议。但是，按照前述规则本来不可重提的动议，如果措辞经过相当程度的修改，或者影响动议的环境条件发生了显著的变化，以至这个动议变成了一个新问题，则可重提。对于动议的重提，还得补充两点：第一，已经收回的动议，等于从未被提出，则不存在重提的限制，或者说随时可以重提；第二，如果一个主动议在本次会议提出之后未能得到通过，那么可以在此后任何一次会议重提。关于不良动议，我们已经谈过无效动议，这里再说故意拖延的情 形。所谓故意拖延性质的动议，指那些妨碍、阻挠会议整体意志的动议。任何在本质上不严肃、无意义、没有提出任何实质建议、荒谬的动议，都属于故意拖延，不应被引入。举例来讲，如不断对主持人的裁定提出申诉；在所有人都参与表决且结果明显的情况之下，要求起立重新表决，皆属故意拖延。</p> <h2 id="法定人数quorum">法定人数（Quorum）</h2> <p>所谓法定人数，指按照议事规则，<em>会议召开所必须满足的成员出席人数</em>（出席并在场的人数，而非表决之时参与投票的人数）。对此，一般在<em>组织章程</em>之中都该有所规定。若无规定，那么根据通用议事规则，对法定人数有默认：对于公众集会，出席人数即法定人数；对于代表大会，法定人数则是实际报到人数的过半数。</p> <p>法定人数确保了会议和所作决策的合法性。如果会议没有达到法定人数，那么会议所作的任何决定都可能是无效的。通过确保有足够的成员出席，法定人数帮助避免少数人做出可能影响整个组织的重要决策。在任何正式会议开始之前，通常会有一个确定是否达到法定人数的过程，以确保会议可以有效且合法地进行。若不满足法定人数条件，主持人可以适当等待；若等待一段时间之后依然没有希望满足法定人数，那么主持人仍可宣布会议开始，并立即宣布法定人数不足，然后建议成员采取一定行动，或者受理一个<em>休会动议</em>。</p> <p>在诸如立法机构这样有权强制成员出席会议的组织当中，有一种叫作<em>强制出席</em>的动议，可以用来实现法定人数的满足。请注意，<em>强制出席只适用于像立法机构这样的组织，而不适用于自愿性组织</em>。</p> <h2 id="会议程序">会议程序</h2> <p>标准会议程序分作基本程序与<em>可选标题</em>。所谓基本程序一般包括六项：宣读并批准会议纪要，官员报告、 董事会报告、常设委员会报告，临时委员会报告，特别议程，未完事务和普通议程，新事务。可选标题包括：开幕仪式或典礼，点名，快速处理列表，自由评论，声明，节目等。</p> <p>《罗伯特议事规则》提供了一套详细的会议程序指南，旨在使正式会议有序、高效地进行。以下是按照这些规则进行的典型会议流程：</p> <ol> <li>开会（Call to Order）。主持人宣布会议开始，确保会议在预定时间正式启动。</li> <li>确定法定人数（Determine a Quorum）。在会议开始之前，确认是否有足够的成员出席以满足法定人数的要求，从而确保会议的决策有效。</li> <li>审阅并批准议程（Review and Approve the Agenda）。主持人或秘书宣读会议议程，成员们可以提议对议程进行修改或补充，然后对最终议程进行表决批准。</li> <li>审阅并批准上次会议记录（Reading and Approval of Minutes）。秘书宣读上一次会议的记录，成员们有机会提出更正或修改，然后记录被正式批准。</li> <li>报告（Reports）。包括（1） 官员报告：董事长、财务官员等官员可能会提供更新或报告。（2）委员会报告：各委员会负责人报告他们的工作进展或成果等。</li> <li>未完成的业务（Unfinished Business）。处理上次会议遗留下来的或未完成的事务。</li> <li>新业务（New Business）。成员提出新的议题或动议进行讨论和表决。这些议题通常在会议开始前列入议程，但也可能在会议中提出。</li> <li>宣布（Announcements）。通知成员即将到来的活动、会议或重要日期。</li> <li>公开论坛（Open Forum）。在某些会议中，可能会有一个时间段供成员自由讨论或提出关切。</li> <li>休会（Adjournment）。会议主持人提出休会动议，一旦获得批准，会议正式结束。</li> </ol> <p>例如，在一个社区协会的月度会议中，主持人会按照上述步骤组织会议，确保所有的行政事务（如审批记录和报告）得到处理，并且提供一个平台供成员讨论新的提案或计划，并对它们进行表决。公开论坛可能被用来讨论社区的关切或即将发生的事件。</p> <h2 id="发言与辩论如何有效率有礼貌地争吵">发言与辩论：如何有效率有礼貌地争吵</h2> <p>在哪种情形之下，可以打断他人的发言？一般而言，在成员取得发言权并且开始发言之后，任何人，包括主持人，都不得随意打断他的发言，除非发言人的言行出现程序问题，如发言时间超出规定等。而一些特殊情况下，则可以如此，这些情形包括：提出要求遵守议程（因为出现了未遵守议程的情况），提出权益问题，提出程序问题，提出拆分议题，提出请求或咨询，提出申诉，提出反对考虑，提出起立重新表决等。</p> <p>再说辩论。辩论之时，常常出现发言人滔滔不绝、罗里吧嗦，甚至不知所云的情况。议事规则之为规则，要义之一，即在于对这些弊病的防范。如果会议组织没有制定特别议事规则，那么依通用议事规则，每次辩论发言的最长时间则为10分钟；<em>同一天内，对同一问题，同一成员的发言不能超过两次</em>。当然，可以有所变通，如主持人认为，假如宽延一分钟，发言人结束发言能够更加体面，那则不妨延长。</p> <p>辩论之时，要求切题、严禁攻击其他成员的动机、<em>所有辩论必须通过主持人</em>、避免称呼成员的姓名、禁止对已经做出的决定发表反面意见、<em>禁止对自己提出的动议发表反面意见</em>、<em>朗读文件需要会议批准</em>、<em>成员被主持人打断后就座</em>、禁止扰乱会场等。</p> <p>关于辩论，还有一点要补充：主持人作为组织成员，同样享有辩论权，不过，基于主持人角色的中立性，<em>他在会议期间则不得行使辩论权</em>，尤其在一些大型会议之上，主持人不能对待决议题的是非利弊发表任何意见，以免左右他人；必要之时，他的确可以参加辩论，只是在此之前，他得让出主持人之位，等到当前待决议题得到处理之后，才能恢复他的主持人职务</p> <h2 id="表决">表决</h2> <p>第一个要点是<em>表决额度</em>（Voting Thresholds），即“决定表决结果的底线”。除 了“过半数表决”和“三分之二表决”，还有<em>相对多数表决</em>，一般发生在有三个或三个以上竞争者的情况之下。此外，一般而言主持人也有表决权，如果采用的表决方式是“书面不记名表决”，那么主持人跟其他成员一样参与投票；如果采用其他表决方式，主持人这一票可能影响最终结局，他可以选择参与表决，也可以放弃。</p> <p>关于表决额度的种类主要有以下几种。</p> <ol> <li> <p>简单多数（Simple Majority）。即超过半数的投票。这是最常见的表决额度。用于大多数标准决策，如常规动议的通过。例如，在年会上，成员对是否增加年度活动预算进行表决。如果赞成票超过<em>出席成员的一半</em>，该提案通过。</p> </li> <li> <p>绝对多数（Absolute Majority）。即超过所有成员总数一半的投票。较少使用，适用于更重要或敏感的决策。例如组织修改章程时可能要求绝对多数表决，即赞成票需要超过<em>所有成员总数的一半</em>。</p> </li> <li> <p>三分之二多数（Two-thirds Majority）。要求至少三分之二的赞成票。多用于更重要的决策，特别是那些可能限制成员权利或需要更大共识的决定。例如，要取消或修改已通过的决议，或在会议中暂缓执行某项规则，通常需要三分之二多数的赞成票。</p> </li> <li> <p>固定数字或比例（Fixed Number or Proportion）。即规定了具体的数字或比例，而不是基于出席成员的比例。适用于特定情况，可能是由法律或组织的章程特别规定的。例如，某些组织可能规定，更改组织的主要政策或结构至少需要80%的赞成票。</p> </li> <li> <p>一致同意（Unanimous Consent）。要求所有出席成员的一致赞成。适用于那些需要完全一致同意的决策。例如，在非常敏感或重大的决策，如特殊荣誉的授予，可能要求一致同意。</p> </li> </ol> <hr/> <p>第二个要点是表决方式。主要有以下几种常见的表决方式。</p> <ol> <li> <p>口头表决（Voice Vote）。成员通过说“赞成”（aye）或“反对”（no）来表达他们的投票意见。例如，在社区会议上，主持人提出：“所有支持建设新公园的，请说‘赞成’；反对的，请说‘反对’。”会议成员随后大声表达他们的选择。</p> </li> <li> <p>举手表决（Show of Hands）。成员通过举手表示赞成或反对。如，董事会讨论是否批准新的预算案时，主持人说：“支持这个预算案的，请举手。”成员们随后举手表示支持或反对。</p> </li> <li> <p>站立表决（Standing Vote）。类似于举手表决，但要求成员站立以表示赞成或反对。例如，在一个年会上，为了更清楚地计数，主持人可能要求：“所有赞成新会员政策的，请站立。”</p> </li> <li> <p>无记名投票（Secret Ballot）。要求成员在选票上私下标记他们的选择，然后进行计数。例如，选举组织领导时，可能采用无记名投票以确保投票的隐私和客观性。</p> </li> <li> <p>逐点表决（Roll Call Vote）。即按照名单顺序呼叫每个成员的名字，成员在被叫到时公开表达他们的投票意见。例如，在一项重要且可能有争议的决议上，为了确保记录每个人的投票，会进行逐点表决。</p> </li> <li> <p>通行表决（General Consent）。对于没有争议的议题，主持人会提议如果没有反对意见，就认为议题通过。例如，主持人可能说：“如果没有人反对，我们就认为关于会议时间变更的提案通过了。”</p> </li> </ol> <p>每种表决方式都有其适用场景，选择合适的表决方式取决于议题的性质、所需的投票隐私程度和会议的具体要求。</p> <hr/> <p><strong>表决的权利和义务</strong></p> <p>对于拖欠会费的成员，只要未予除名、未被处分而暂停表决权，他便可以参与表决；表决适用一人一票原则，成员可以弃权；表决适用<em>回避原则</em>，如成员与待决议题有直接利害关系，他应该回避，不过这一点并不具备强制性。</p> <h2 id="提名与选举">提名与选举</h2> <p>提名和选举是选举官员或委员会成员的正式过程。</p> <p><strong>提名过程</strong></p> <ol> <li> <p>开放提名：会议可以允许会议上的任何成员提出提名。通常，主持人会询问是否有提名。例如，在社区协会的年度选举中，主持人询问：“是否有人要提名今年的协会主席？”成员们可以自由提出候选人的名字。</p> </li> <li> <p>提名委员会：某些情况下，可能有一个专门的提名委员会负责提出候选人的提名。例如，在公司董事会选举中，提名委员会提前准备了一份候选人名单，并在会议上宣布。</p> </li> <li> <p>自我提名：成员有时也可以自我提名。例如，在一个俱乐部的选举中，一名成员站起来说：“我想自我提名参加秘书的角色。”</p> </li> </ol> <p><strong>选举过程</strong></p> <ol> <li> <p>表决方式：选举通常通过无记名投票进行，尤其是在竞争性选举中。也可以通过举手或口头表决，如果没有反对。例如，在社区协会选举中，如果只有一个候选人，主持人可能会建议：“如果没有反对，我们将通过一致同意来选举这位候选人。”</p> </li> <li> <p>多轮投票：如果在首轮投票中没有候选人获得必要的多数票，可能需要进行多轮投票。例如，在董事会选举中，如果第一轮投票没有候选人获得超过一半的票数，就需要进行第二轮投票。</p> </li> <li> <p>选举结果：选举的结果根据获得多数票的候选人来确定。如果规定了特定的多数额度（如绝对多数），则必须达到该额度。例如，在学校董事会的选举中，候选人必须获得所有投票的三分之二才能当选。</p> </li> </ol> <h2 id="官员会议纪要和官员报告切不可有官架子">官员、会议纪要和官员报告：切不可有“官架子“</h2> <p>会议官员与官僚体制中的官员迥然不同，前者必须避免后者的种种习气与陋规。一般而言，组织都是从内部选择官员，不过，除非是秘密组织，否则章程并不一定排斥从成员之外选择官员，如许多立法机构的主持人并不是该机构的成员。</p> <p>官员可分作两块，一是选举产生的官员，包括主持人（临时主持人）、当选总裁／会长、副总裁／会长、秘书、联络秘书、财务官和财务秘书、其他官员（董事或理事、史记官、图书管理员、物管员、牧 、警卫员、门卫等）、荣誉官员或荣誉成员；二是指派产生的官员和顾问，包括执行秘书、议事规则专家（这里简单介绍一下：议事规则专家以顾问和专家的身份，向主持人、其他官员、委员会和所有其他成员提供议事规则方面的咨询和建议。</p> <p>官员当中，地位最高、责任最大、工作最忙的无疑是主持人。其职责包括在指定时间开始会议；依据既定的会议程序、日程、时间表以及议程宣布会议即将处理的下一项事务；判断并分配发言权；对所有正当、合乎规则的动议宣布议题、提请表决、宣布表决结果；对于明显具有扰乱、拖延性质的或荒诞的动议，直接拒绝受理或者裁定为不合规则；贯彻辩论规则，维护会议的秩序和礼节；在保障所有成员权利的前提之下提高会议的运行效率；对所有程序问题进行裁定，接受申诉；在成员咨询议事规则之时给予回应；在必要的时候，签署所有法案、命令、记录等文件；宣布休会等。由此可知，会议主持人除了要承担一般主持人的功能之外，还要扮演裁判的角色。</p> <p>秘书的一大职责是负责记录、整理并保管会议纪要。会议纪要的内容包括会议的类型、组织名称、日期、时间、地点；如果主持人和秘书出席，记下这个事实，如果缺席，记下替代者的姓名；所有主动议与未被否决、收回的辅动议、委员会报告、所有事先告知、所有程序问题和申诉（无论成立还是无效，同时记录主持人裁定的理由）；休会时间等。其中主动议这一块，可谓会议纪要的主体，必须详之又详，慎之又慎。注意，动议人的姓名应该记录；除非会议要求，否则不必记录附议人的名字。秘书要在会议纪要之上签字。如果会议要求，主持人也应签字。</p> <h2 id="纪律惩戒程序">纪律惩戒程序</h2> <p>如果只是轻微违纪，如辩论之时没有面对主持人而是面对另一位成员发言，或者发言脱离了当前议题，主持人只需轻击法槌，指出错误并警告其不要再犯；对于更严重的错误，如成员不断指名道姓攻击其他成员的动机，主持人<em>或其他任何成员</em>都可以立即请此人遵守秩序；对于屡加警告而无效的严重违纪行为，主持人可以点名批评；最坏的情况，则只能勒令其退场直至会议结束，或者勒令其退场直至公开道歉，或者要求暂停其会籍，或者要求开除。开除会员一般需要“三分之二表决”。具体而言，惩戒程序包括（但不限于）以下几种。</p> <ol> <li> <p>警告。对轻微或初次违规行为通常首先通过口头警告来处理。主持人可以直接提醒成员遵守会议规则。例如，如果一个成员在会议中反复打断他人，主持人可能首先给予口头警告，提醒该成员遵守会议的发言规则。</p> </li> <li> <p>禁言。对于持续的不当行为，会议可以投票决定暂时禁止该成员发言。例如，如果警告后成员继续打断会议，会议可以决定在剩余的会议时间内禁止该成员发言。</p> </li> <li> <p>请离会场。对于严重或不受控制的行为，会议可以投票决定要求成员离开会议场所。例如，如果一个成员表现出侮辱性行为或威胁他人安全，会议可以决定让该成员离开会场。</p> </li> <li> <p>弹劾或撤销职务。对于严重违反职责或不端行为的官员，组织可以通过正式程序进行弹劾或撤销其职务。例如，如果一名董事被发现滥用职权或严重违反组织规章，可以通过正式的弹劾程序撤销其职务。</p> </li> <li> <p>会员资格的暂停或终止。在极端情况下，组织可能决定暂停或终止某人的会员资格。例如，如果一个成员持续进行破坏活动或严重违反组织的原则，组织可能决定暂停或终止其会员资格。</p> </li> <li> <p>正式听证和调查。对于复杂或严重的案件，可能需要进行正式的听证或调查过程。例如，在处理严重的财务不当行为指控时，组织可能成立一个特别委员会来调查事实并进行听证。</p> </li> </ol> <p>这些程序旨在保持会议的秩序和尊重，同时确保对违规行为的处理既公正又适当。重要的是，这些程序应当在尊重成员的权利和保证程序公正的前提下进行。</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[当会议主持人的讲究]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Analytic Structure</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Analytic-Structure/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Analytic Structure"/><published>2023-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Analytic-Structure</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Analytic-Structure/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="holomorphic-and-meromorphic-functions">Holomorphic and Meromorphic Functions</h3> <p>Let $X$ be a Riemann surface and $(U_ {p},\phi_ {p})$ an coordinate patch of $X$ containing a point $p$ in it. A coordinate system of $X$ is a map $X\to \mathbb{C}$, a map $\mathbb{C} \to X$ would be called a parametrization. A coordinate system is a function on $X$.</p> <p>Let $Y\subset X$ be a open subset of $X$. Denote the set of all holomorphic function on $Y$ by $\mathcal{O}(Y)$ or $\mathcal{O}_ {Y}$. This notation reminds us of the sheaf theory.</p> <p>Let $Y\subset X$ be an open subset, a function $f$ on $Y$ is called a meromorphic function if $f$ is holomorphic on $Y$ except on a set $A$ of isolated points, $A$ is called the set of poles. Let $p\in A$ be a pole, then</p> \[\lim_{ x \to p } \left\lvert f(x) \right\rvert =\infty.\] <p><em>Note that the poles must be isolated points</em>.</p> <p>We denote the set of meromorphic functions by $\mathcal{M}(Y)$. A meromorphic function is of form</p> \[\text{meromorphic}= \frac{\text{holomorphic function }f}{\text{holomorphic function }g}\] <p>thus the poles are zeros of $g$. This is true because every holomorphic function, which is not identically zero, has only <em>isolated</em> points as zeros.</p> <p>Since the meromorphic functions are quotients of holomorphic functions, we can construct the inverse of it, thus all the meromorphic functions on $Y$, or $X$ for that matter, form a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">field</code>.</p> <p>Given two Riemann surfaces $X$ and $X’$, a holomorphic function $f: X \to X’$ is a functions that is holomorphic on all the coordinate patches. If $f$ is a bijection with an inverse $f^{-1}$ which is also holomorphic, then we call $f$ an <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">analytic holomorphic</code> function. <strong>Analytic is to holomorphism what continuous is to open sets</strong>.</p> <p>One of the most important topic is the classification of Riemann surfaces up to analytic holomorphism.</p> <p>Let $X$ be a compact Riemann surface and $f$ a global holomorphic function, then $f$ can only be a constant function. In other words,</p> \[\mathcal{O}(X) = \mathbb{C}.\] <hr/> <p>The Riemann sphere is a geometric model that extends the complex plane to include a point at infinity. Imagine the complex plane as a horizontal sheet. The Riemann sphere is then a sphere sitting on this plane, touching it at the origin. Every point on the complex plane is projected onto the sphere (except the point at infinity, which is represented by the top point of the sphere, or the “north pole”). This projection is typically done using stereographic projection, where each point on the complex plane is connected by a line to the north pole of the sphere, and the point of intersection on the sphere is the corresponding point.</p> <p>The one-dimensional complex projective space $\mathbb{C}\mathbb{P}^1$, or just $\mathbb{P}^{1}$ in this note, is formed by considering lines through the origin in a two-dimensional complex vector space $\mathbb{C}^2$. Essentially, you take all possible complex lines (one-dimensional subspaces) in $\mathbb{C}^2$, and each line is considered a point in $\mathbb{P}^1$. This space includes all the points of the complex plane, along with an additional “point at infinity” to account for limits along each possible direction in the complex plane.</p> <p>The equivalence between these two comes from how they treat points at infinity. In the Riemann sphere, there is a single point at infinity (the north pole of the sphere), which is the limit point for all directions in the complex plane. In $\mathbb{P}^1$, each line through the origin in $\mathbb{C}^2$ corresponds to a point in projective space. Lines parallel to the complex plane (but not within it) converge to a single “point at infinity,” similar to the north pole of the Riemann sphere.</p> <p>Both the Riemann sphere and $\mathbb{P}^1$ provide a way to compactify the complex plane by adding a point at infinity, thus allowing for a seamless handling of limits and behaviors that would otherwise be “infinite” or “undefined” in the regular complex plane. They are different representations of the same conceptual space, with the Riemann sphere providing a more geometric and intuitive picture, while $\mathbb{P}^1$ offers a more algebraic and abstract framework.</p> <hr/> <p>The principal part of a meromorphic function $f(z)$ at a pole $a$ refers to the portion of the function’s Laurent series that contains the terms with negative powers of $(z - a)$. Recall that a function is meromorphic on a domain if it is holomorphic throughout the domain <strong>except for isolated poles</strong>. For a meromorphic function near a pole $a$, you can express the function as a Laurent series. This is a series expansion that, unlike the Taylor series, includes terms with negative powers. The Laurent series for $f(z)$ around the pole $a$ can be written as:</p> \[f(z) = \sum_{n=-\infty}^{\infty} c_n (z - a)^n\] <p>where $c_n$ are the coefficients of the series.</p> <p>The principal part of $f(z)$ at the pole $a$ specifically refers to the sum of the terms of the Laurent series with negative powers of $(z - a)$. This part of the Laurent series looks like:</p> \[\sum_{n=1}^{\infty} c_{-n} (z - a)^{-n}\] <p>So, when we talk about the principal part of a meromorphic function $f(z)$ at a pole $a$, we’re focusing on the terms in the function’s Laurent series that capture the behavior of $f(z)$ as $z$ approaches $a$ and the function goes towards infinity.</p> <hr/> <p>Every meromorphic function on the Riemann sphere is a rational function (i.e. the quotient of two polynomials), we write</p> \[\mathcal{M}(\mathbb{P}^{1}) = \text{Quot}(\mathbb{C}[z]).\] <p>To see that, take $f\in\mathcal{M}(\mathbb{P}^{1})$. $f$ has only finite many poles. Around each pole, we can separate the function into the principal part (namely the divergent part) and the holomorphic part. We can subtract the principal parts from $f$ hence obtaining a holomorphic function. But then this new function must be a constant. Then $f$ must be the quotient of two polynomials.</p> <h2 id="divisor">Divisor</h2> <p>A divisor is a formal sum that provides a way to keep track of the zeros and poles of meromorphic functions on a complex manifold (like a Riemann surface). It is especially useful in the study of complex functions, algebraic curves, and algebraic geometry.</p> <p>A divisor on a complex manifold is a formal sum of points on the manifold, with each point $p$ associated with an integer $n_p$. It is typically written as</p> \[\text{Div} = \sum n_p p\] <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>where $n_p &gt; 0$ for a zero of order $n_p$, $n_p &lt; 0$ for a pole of order $</td> <td>n_p</td> <td>$, and $n_p = 0$ means that $p$ is neither a zero nor a pole of the function in question.</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>Divisors are used to study the properties of meromorphic functions and to formulate concepts like the degree of a divisor, the principal divisor (associated with a meromorphic function), and to define line bundles. In the context of Riemann surfaces, divisors play a crucial role in the formulation of the Riemann-Roch theorem, which is fundamental in the intersection of algebraic geometry and complex analysis.</p> <p>In short, given a Riemann surface $X$, the group of divisors $\text{Div}(X)$ is a group freely generated by points of $X$. We will denote the elements of $\text{Div}(X)$ as $D,D’$, etc. Let</p> \[D,D' \in \text{Div}(X), \quad D = \sum_ {a}n_ {a} a,\quad D' = \sum_ {a} m_ {a} a,\] <p>we define</p> \[D + D' = \sum_ {a}(n_ {a}+m_ {a})a.\] <p>We say $D&lt;D’$ iff $n_ {a}&lt;m_ {a}$ for all $a$.</p> <p>For $f\in\mathcal{M}(X)$ a meromorphic function defined on $X$, and a point $a \in X$, recall that the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">order</code> (or multiplicity) of $a$ is defined as</p> \[\text{ord}_ {a}(f) := \begin{cases} 0, &amp; \text{holomorphic at } a \text{ and } f(a)\neq 0 \\ k, &amp; \text{has a zero of multiplicity k at } a \\ -k,&amp; \text{has a pole of multiplicity k at } a \\ \infty, &amp; \text{identically zero.} \end{cases}\] <p>To every meromorphic function $f$ we may assign a divisor</p> \[(f) := \sum_ {a} \text{ord}_ {a}(f) \cdot a.\] <p>We call such divisors <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">principal divisors</code>.</p> <p>Principal divisors turn multiplication between functions into addition, similar to the exponent function. To be exact, given two meromorphic functions $f$ and $g$ we have</p> \[(f\cdot g) = (f)+(g),\quad (f^{-1} ) = - (f).\] <p>Principal divisors are important because they relate the geometry of the manifold (or variety) to the algebra of its function field. A notable property is that <em>the sum of the orders of zeros and poles of any meromorphic function on a compact manifold is zero</em>, leading to the principal divisor being of degree zero (which we will talk about later).</p> <hr/> <p><strong>Why the name divisor?</strong></p> <p>Just as a number’s divisor evenly divides the number, the divisors in complex analysis are related to the “division” of functions by their zeroes and poles. A zero of a function can be thought of as a point where the function ‘divides’ by the variable, whereas a pole is where the division becomes singular or undefined. To be more specific, a zero of a function $f(z)$ is a point $a$ in the complex plane where $f(a) = 0$. Metaphorically, this can be seen as the function $f(z)$ being “divisible” by the factor $(z - a)$. For example, if $f(z) = (z - a)g(z)$, where $g(z)$ is another function, then $f(z)$ has a zero at $z = a$. Here, $(z - a)$ is like a ‘divisor’ for the function $f(z)$, similar to how an integer divides another integer.</p> <p>On the other hand, a pole of a function $f(z)$ at a point $a$ is a place where $f(z)$ tends toward infinity as $z$ approaches $a$. In this metaphorical context, a pole can be thought of as a point where the division of the function by $(z - a)$ becomes ‘singular’ or ‘undefined’. This is analogous to how division by zero in arithmetic is undefined. For example, consider $f(z) = \frac{1}{(z - a)}$. As $z$ approaches $a$, the function approaches infinity, signifying a pole at $a$. Here, $f(z)$ behaves as if it were the result of a ‘division’ by $(z - a)$, and this ‘division’ is undefined or singular at $z = a$.</p> <p>The divisor is a formal sum of points (in the one-dimensional case, such as on Riemann surfaces) or subvarieties, each associated with an integer. This sum mirrors the way a number can be expressed as a product of its prime divisors raised to certain powers.</p> <p>In summary, a zero of a function is a point where the function can be “divided” by a certain factor without issues, resulting in the function being zero. A pole, on the other hand, is where this ‘division’ leads to an undefined or singular situation, akin to division by zero, resulting in the function tending towards infinity. The term “divisor” carries over the essence of division and factorization from basic arithmetic to the more sophisticated settings of complex analysis (and algebraic geometry), capturing the fundamental way in which functions can be ‘divided’ by their behavior at certain points or subspaces.</p> <hr/> <p>In contrast to principal divisors, a general divisor on a manifold or variety is simply a formal sum of points (in the one-dimensional case) or more generally, of subvarieties of codimension $1$, weighted by integers. These are not necessarily associated with any particular meromorphic function.</p> <p>We say two divisors are <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">linearly equivalent</code> $D \sim D’$ if their difference is a principal divisor</p> \[D - D' = (f) \text{ for some moromorphic function } f.\] <p>We use the name <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">divisor class</code> to denote the linear equivalence class of a divisor.</p> <p>Since principal divisors are so important, one of the main questions at this point is, which divisors are principal divisors? Phrased differently, given a divisor, are there functions with prescribed poles and zeros? The theorem of Riemann–Roch will give us the first part of the answer.</p> <p>But first, we need to define the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">degree</code> of a divisor $\text{deg}$.</p> <p><strong>Degree of a divisor.</strong> Given a divisor $\text{Div}(X)$ of a Riemann surface $X$, the degree of the divisor is an integer</p> \[\text{dig}: \text{Div}(X) \to \mathbb{Z}, \quad \sum_ {a}n_ {a} a \mapsto \sum_ {a} n_ {a}.\] <p>The set of divisors of degree zero, denoted by $\text{Div}^{0}(X)$, is the set of principal divisors, since <em>every meromorphic function has the same number of zeros as poles</em> ( as a consequence of the argument principle).</p> <hr/> <p>The quotient of all divisors by the principal divisors is called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Picard group</code> $\text{Pic}(X)$. Recall that the quotient by something is to regard the “something” as zero, so for a Picard group, we effectively treat all the principal divisors as zero. The quotient of all the zero-degree divisors $\text{Div}^{0}(X)$ by principal divisors are called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">restricted Picard group</code> $\text{Pic}^{0}(X)$.</p> <p>Now let’s define a space of meromorphic functions using the divisor. Let $D$ be an arbitrary divisor, let</p> \[L(D) := \left\lbrace f\in \mathcal{M}(X) \,\middle\vert\, (f)\geq -D \right\rbrace .\] <p>Recall how we compare to divisors, we say divisor $D&gt;D’$ if every coefficient of $D$ is bigger than that in $D’$.</p> <p>Since $L(D)$ is defined as the set of all meromorphic functions $f$ such that the divisor of $f$ satisfies $(f) \geq -D$, this condition means that the poles of $f$ are no worse than those specified by $D$, and possibly better (fewer or lower order). For example, if $n\cdot a, a\in X$ is a term in $D$, then the $f\in L(D)$ are allowed to have order at $a$ no less than $-n$, in other words, to have poles with multiplicity $\leq n$. If $-n\cdot a$ is a term in $D$ then $f$ can only have a zero at $a$ with multiplicity less or equal than $n$.</p> <p>$L(D)$ is indeed a vector space. First, notice that it is closed under addition, if $f$ and $g$ are in $L(D)$, then $f + g$ is also in $L(D)$. The reason is that the poles of $f + g$ cannot be worse than the worst poles of $f$ and $g$ separately. Since both $f$ and $g$ have their poles controlled by $D$, so does their sum. Secondly, it is closed under scalar multiplication of a complex number, if $f$ is in $L(D)$ and $c$ is a complex number, then $cf$ is also in $L(D)$. Multiplying by a scalar doesn’t introduce any new poles, so the pole structure of $cf$ is the same as that of $f$. Thirdly, there exist the zero element, the constant function 0 is in $L(D)$ because it has no poles, thus satisfying the condition trivially. Finally, it satisfies the condition of associativity and commutativity, these follow from the standard properties of function addition and scalar multiplication.</p> <p>The definition of $L(D)$ captures an essential aspect of the theory of divisors and Riemann surfaces or algebraic curves. It relates the geometric concept of a divisor to the space of meromorphic functions. $L(D)$ can be used to study the properties of divisors and the surfaces or curves they reside on.</p> <hr/> <p>Since $L(D)$ is a vector space, we can talk about the dimension of it. In some textbooks people define</p> \[l(D) := \text{dim }L(D)\] <p>but we will simply write $\text{dim } L(D)$. In certain cases we are able to determine the dimension of $L(D)$ directly.</p> <p><strong>Example 1.</strong> The Zero Divisor</p> <p>Let’s start with the simplest divisor, the zero divisor $D = 0$. The space $L(0)$ includes all meromorphic functions $f$ whose divisors $(f)$ satisfy $(f) \geq 0$. This means $f$ can only have zeros, no poles. Essentially, $L(0)$ is the space of all holomorphic functions.</p> <p>On a compact Riemann surface, the only globally defined holomorphic functions are constants (by Liouville’s theorem). Thus, the dimension of $L(0)$ is 1, spanned by the constant function 1.</p> <p><strong>Example 2.</strong> A Divisor with a Single Simple Pole</p> <p>Consider a divisor $D = p$, where $p$ is a point on the Riemann surface, indicating a simple pole at $p$. $L(p)$ consists of meromorphic functions that may have at most a simple pole at $p$ and no other poles. This includes constant functions and functions with a simple pole at $p$. Determining the exact dimension can depend on the specific Riemann surface and the point $p$. However, for a compact Riemann surface of genus $g$, a rough estimate can be given by the Riemann-Roch theorem, which we will talk about later. For a single point, the dimension often exceeds 1, but the exact number depends on the surface’s complex structure.</p> <hr/> <p>Next, let’s shortly talk about <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">canonical divisors</code>. On a Riemann surface, a canonical divisor $K$ is a divisor associated with the (holomorphic) differential forms on that surface or curve. Specifically, it is the divisor of a non-zero meromorphic differential form. Recall that, on a Riemann surface, a differential form is a complex-analytic object that generalizes the concept of functions. Holomorphic differential forms are those that are locally of the form $f(z) dz$, where $f(z)$ is a holomorphic function. The divisor of a differential form $\omega$ is defined similarly to the divisor of a function. It is a formal sum of points, where each point is weighted by the order of zero or pole of $\omega$ at that point.</p> <p>The canonical divisor $K$ represents the common “pole-zero” structure of all meromorphic differential forms on the surface. If $\omega$ is a meromorphic differential form, then $K = (\omega)$, the divisor of $\omega$.</p> <p>A simple example is the Riemann sphere (the complex projective line $\mathbb{P}^1$). On the Riemann sphere, consider the differential form $dz$. This form is holomorphic everywhere on the complex plane, which is part of the Riemann sphere. In this case, the canonical divisor $K$ is actually associated with a negative order (a pole) at infinity. This might seem a bit counterintuitive, but it reflects the fact that there are no non-trivial holomorphic differential forms on the Riemann sphere. In simpler terms, $K$ is the divisor corresponding to the differential form $dz$ with a pole of order $2$ at infinity, often denoted as $-2 \cdot [\infty]$.</p> <p>The fact that the differential form $dz$ has a pole at infinity can be better understood by considering the behavior of $dz$ under a change of coordinates that maps the neighborhood of infinity to a neighborhood of zero, namely the stereographic projection. Recall that under this projection, the north pole of the sphere maps to the point at infinity in the complex plane. To analyze the behavior at infinity, we introduce a new coordinate $w$ such that $w = 1/z$. In this new coordinate, the point $z = \infty$ corresponds to $w = 0$. In the $w$-coordinate, the differential $dz$ transforms as</p> \[dz = -\frac{1}{w^2} dw\] <p>This comes from the derivative of $z$ with respect to $w$, noting that $z = 1/w$, so $dz/dw = -1/w^2$. Now it is obvious that $-dw/w^2$ has a pole of order $2$ at $w = 0$.</p> <hr/> <p>The Riemann-Roch theorem is a fundamental result in the field of algebraic geometry and complex analysis, particularly regarding the study of Riemann surfaces. This theorem provides deep insights into the relationship between the <strong>geometry</strong> of a curve and the <strong>algebraic</strong> properties of divisors, and line bundles associated with it.</p> <p>For a compact Riemann surface, the Riemann-Roch theorem gives a formula to compute the <strong>dimension of the space of meromorphic functions</strong> associated with a given divisor. The theorem is stated as follows:</p> <p><strong>Riemann-Roch Theorem.</strong> If $D$ is a divisor on a compact Riemann surface, then</p> \[\text{dim } L(D) - \text{dim } L(K - D) = \text{deg}(D) - g + 1\] <p>where $K$ is the canonical divisor, associated with the differential forms on the surface, $\text{deg}(D)$ is the degree of the divisor $D$ and $g$ is the genus of the Riemann surface.</p> <p>The Riemann-Roch theorem links the geometric properties of Riemann surfaces (like genus) with the algebraic properties of divisors and function spaces. Also, it provides a powerful tool for understanding the behavior of divisors and line bundles on Riemann surfaces. This includes determining the number of independent meromorphic functions or sections of line bundles with certain properties. The theorem laid the groundwork for further developments in algebraic geometry, including sheaf cohomology and modern intersection theory.</p> <p>As an example, consider the zero divisor $D$ with $\text{deg}(D)=0$. Then the theorem says</p> \[1-\text{dim } L(K) = -g+1 \implies \text{dim }L(K) = g.\]]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Holomorphic and Meromorphic Functions]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introduction to Transseries Lecture 2</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Transseries-Lecture-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction to Transseries Lecture 2"/><published>2023-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Transseries-Lecture-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Transseries-Lecture-2/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>In history, formal power series are used extensively for finding the resolution of differential equations. If the resulting power series is convergent, it gives rise to a germ which can be analytically continued to (multi-valued) functions on a Riemann surface. However, very often, the power series we found from solving a differential equation is divergent, then it is not clear <em>a prior</em> how to attach reasonable sums to them.</p> <p>The modern theory of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">resummation</code> was developed systematically by Stieltjes, Borel and Hardy, who invented some resummation methods which <em>are stable under the common operators of analysis</em>. Later, Poincare established the equivalence between computations with formal power series and asymptotic expansions. Newton, Borel and Hardy were all aware of the systematic aspects of their theories and they consciously tried to complete their framework so as to capture as much of analysis as possible. The great unifying theory nevertheless had to wait until the late 20-th century and Ecalle’s work on transseries and Dulac’s conjecture.</p> <hr/> <p>Transseries have found significant applications in various areas of physics, particularly in high-energy physics. They are employed as algebraic tools to investigate self-consistent Dyson–Schwinger equations, which are integral equations that arise in the field of quantum field theory, specifically in Yukawa theory and quantum electrodynamics <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0003491616300793">1</a>. These equations are pivotal in understanding the interactions of particles and fields at a fundamental level.</p> <p>In the realm of general relativity, transseries are applied to asymptotic analysis. General relativity stands as one of the cornerstones of modern physics, governing the laws of gravitation and the dynamics of large-scale structures in the universe . By applying transseries in this domain, researchers can gain insights into the asymptotic behavior of gravitational fields and the dynamics of spacetime.</p> <p>Furthermore, transseries are used in the <em>extraction of non-perturbative physics from perturbation theory through resurgence and alien calculus</em>. Perturbation theory is a fundamental tool in quantum mechanics and quantum field theory, allowing for the approximation of complex systems. The non-perturbative effects are those that cannot be captured by perturbation theory alone, and transseries help to identify and understand these effects <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0003491619301691">2</a>.</p> <p>Additionally, in the context of integrable, asymptotically free field theories, transseries have applications in studying the free energy of such systems when coupled to a conserved charge. These studies are significant in high-energy physics, particularly in understanding the thermodynamics and statistical mechanics of particle systems <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/JHEP08%282022%29279">3</a>.</p> <p>These examples showcase the versatility and importance of transseries in advancing the understanding of fundamental physics, from the microscale of particle interactions to the macroscale of cosmic phenomena.</p> <hr/> <p>Define a ordered group ${\frak G}$ (frak G) of transmonomials. Define a differential field $\mathbb{T}$ of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">transseries</code>. Transmonomials are generalizations of monomials in polynomials, by including exponential and logarithmic. In this note and that follows, we will consider the limit where $x\to \infty$.</p> <p>Let’s start with exponents first.</p> <p><strong>Log-free transmonomials.</strong> They are of form \(x^{b}e^{ L },\quad b\in \mathbb{R},\; L \in \text{large log-free transseries.}\)</p> <p>For example, the following are all log-free transmonomials, \(x^{-1},\; x^{\pi}x^{x^{\sqrt{ 2 }}-3x},\; e^{ \sum_ {i}x^{-1}e^{ x } },etc.\)</p> <p>The multiplication is defined in the obvious way. The group identity is just $1$.</p> <p>We define a binary relation $\gg$, read “far larger than”. Keep in mind that we assumed $x\to \infty$. So how does this “far larger than” work? We compare the exponents $e^{ L }$ first, whichever with the largest exponent $L$ is far larger than others; if they have same exponents, then we compare the power of $x$, namely $x^{b}$, whichever with larger $b$ is far larger then others. To be specific, \(x^{b_ {1}}e^{ L_ {1} } \gg x^{b_ {2}}e^{ L_ {2} }\quad \text{ if } L_ {1} &gt; L_ {2} \;\lor\; (L_ {1}=L_ {2}\;\land\; b_ {1}&gt;b_ {2} ),\) where $\lor$ is logic or. For example, $x^{-5}\gg x^{20}e^{ -x }$ since $x^{-5}=x^{-5}e^{ 0 }$ and $0&gt;-x$.</p> <p><strong>Log-free transseries.</strong> A log-free transseries $T$ is a formal sum of log-free monomials ${\frak g}$, \(T = \sum_ {i} c_ {i} {\frak g}_ {i},\quad c_ {i} \in \mathbb{R} .\) We require the order of transmonomials be such that, each ${\frak g_ {i}}$ is far smaller than all previous terms, namely they appear in descending orders. This is similar to the case of regular polynomials where we usually put the highest powers at first.</p> <p>The transseries $T$ is said to be <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">purely large</code> if all transmonomials ${\frak g}_ {i}$ are far larger than $1$ (not $0$), namely ${\frak g_ {i}}\gg 1 \;\forall i$. $T$ is said to be <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">small</code> if all ${\frak g}_ {i}\ll 1$ (why isn’t it called purely small?). The largest (in the sense of far larger than) transmonomial is called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">dominant term</code>, let’s call it $c_ {0}{\frak g}_ {0}$. If the dominant term has positive coefficients, $c_ {0}&gt;0$, then $T$ is said to be positive. This enables us to compare the size of two transseries $S,T$, we say $S&gt;T$ if $S-T&gt;0$. So we just need to compare their dominant terms.</p> <hr/> <p>We consider only transmonomials and transseries of “finite exponential height”. For example, we don’t want \(e^{ x^{x^{x\dots}} }.\)</p> <p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">differentiation</code> of $T$ with respect to $x$ is defined the usual way.</p> <hr/> <p>Next let’s include logarithmic. $\log$ acting $m$ times is denoted $\log_ {m}x$ or $\log_ {(m)}x$, namely \(\log_ {(m)}x = \log \dots \log x,\quad m\; \log .\)</p> <p>A general transseries is obtained by substitution of some $\log_ {m}x$ for $x$ in a log-free transseries.</p> <p><em>Every nonzero transseries has a multiplicative inverse.</em> This is similar to formal power series.</p> <p><em>A lot of functions can now be regarded as a transseries</em>. For example, e hyperbolic sine is a two-term transseries.</p> <h2 id="formal-constructions">Formal Constructions</h2> <p>In mathematics, the move towards higher levels of formality entails adopting rigorous and precise language, definitions, and proofs, which brings clarity and precision, ensuring that mathematical concepts are universally understood and applied correctly. It allows for the development of solid, gap-free proofs, having a deeper understanding of mathematical structures and providing a robust foundation for complex theories. This precision in communication is critical in a global context, where scientists from different fields rely on universally recognized formalisms to understand each other effectively.</p> <p>However, this precision comes at a cost. It can make the subject less accessible to beginners (like myself), potentially hindering educational and interdisciplinary work. A focus on stringent formalism might even inhibit creative thinking, as the rigidity of formal proofs could constrain the exploratory, intuitive processes that often drive mathematical discovery. Moreover, the lengthy and detailed nature of formal proofs can make mathematical work less efficient, both in terms of personal understanding and communication with others. There’s also the risk of diminishing intuition, which is a crucial aspect of mathematical thought, particularly in the preliminary stages of research. It is definitely crucial to have a balance between concrete examples and general formalism, what is I hope to achieve in this note.</p> <hr/> <p>The set of monomials ${\frak G}$ form a field, which is also a group if we focus on multiplication alone. ${\frak G}$ is <em>not</em> finitely generated, to see this consider the finitely generated group with generator \(\mu_ {1},\mu_ {2},\dots,\mu_ {n},\) the generated group has elements of form \(\left\{ \mu_ {1}^{k_ {1}}\times \mu_ {2}^{k_ {2}}\times \dots \times \mu_ {n}^{k_ {n}} \,\middle\vert\, k_ {1},\dots,k_ {n} \in \mathbb{Z} \right\} .\) Note that the exponents must be integers.</p> <p>Let’s use capital letters to denote a set of indices, for example define \(K := (k_ {1},k_ {2},\dots,k_ {n})\) then \(\mu_ {1}^{k_ {1}}\dots \mu_ {n}^{k_ {n}} =: \mu^{K}.\)</p> <p>This will save some writing. The problem is that $\mu^{K}$ can also be interpreted as $\mu^{k_ {1}k_ {1}\dots k_ {n}}$, but it should be clear from the context.</p> <p>We will assume that all the generator $\mu \ll 1$. We will think of these as “ratios” between one term of a series and the next. A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ratio set</code> is a finite set of small monomials.</p> <p>Let $k \in \mathbb{Z}^{n}$ be an $n$-tuple of integers, it form a group under addition. Let $p$ be another such $n$-tuple, one say \(k \leq p \quad \text{ iff } k_ {i} \leq p _ {i} \;\forall\; i,\) where $k_ {i}$ is the $i$-th component of $k$.</p> <p>$J_ {m}$ is a partially ordered set. To be specific, a partially ordered set (or poset) is a set equipped with a binary relation that captures a certain level of order or precedence among its elements. This binary relation is denoted by $\leq$ and must satisfy the following properties for any elements $a, b$, and $c$ in the set:</p> <ol> <li><em>Reflexivity</em>: For all elements a in the set, $a\leq a$. In other words, every element is related to itself;</li> <li><em>Antisymmetry</em>: If $a \leq b$ and $b \leq a$, then $a = b$. This property ensures that <em>no two distinct elements are related in both directions</em>;</li> <li><em>Transitivity</em>: If $a \leq b$ and $b \leq c$, then $a \leq c$. This property means that if there’s an order relationship between $a$ and $b$, and another between $b$ and $c$, there’s also an order relationship between $a$ and $c$.</li> </ol> <p>A partially ordered set <strong>does not</strong> require every pair of elements to be comparable; that is, it’s possible for $a$ and $b$ to be in the set without $a\leq b$ or $b \leq a$ being true. This distinguishes partially ordered sets from <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">totally ordered sets</code>, where <strong>every pair of elements is comparable</strong>.</p> <p>For $m\in \mathbb{Z}^{n}$, define \(J_ {m} := \left\lbrace k \in \mathbb{Z}^{n} \,\middle\vert\, k\geq m \right\rbrace .\) Apparently $m \in J_ {m}$. The sets $J_ {m}$ will be used to define <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">grids</code> of monomials. For example, if \(\mu_ {1} = \frac{1}{x},\quad \mu_ {2}=e^{ -x }\) comprise the ratio group (recall that each element of a ratio group is required to be small), then we can define a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">grid</code> (about which we will say more later) \(\left\lbrace \mu^{k} \,\middle\vert\, k\in J_ {(-1,2)} \right\rbrace\) which is the same as \(\left\lbrace \mu^{k}=\mu_ {1}^{k_ {1}} \cdot \mu_ {2}^{k_ {2}} \,\middle\vert\, (k_ {1},k_ {2})\geq (-1,2) \right\rbrace .\)</p> <p>In our convention, the set of natural numbers $\mathbb{N}$ include zero.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="dicksons-lemma">Dickson’s lemma</h3> <p>It turns out that the set $J_ {m}$ is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">well-partially-ordered</code>, sometimes called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Noetherian</code>. A partially ordered set (poset) is said to be well-partially-ordered if it satisfies two conditions:</p> <ul> <li>It contains no <em>infinite strictly descending sequences</em>. This means there cannot be an infinite sequence of elements $a_1, a_2, a_3, \ldots$ in the set such that $a_1 &gt; a_2 &gt; a_3 &gt; \ldots$.</li> <li>It contains no <em>infinite antichains</em>. An <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">antichain</code> is a subset of the poset in which no two distinct elements are comparable. In a well-partially-ordered set, there cannot be an infinite set of elements where none are comparable to each other.</li> </ul> <p>On the other hand, a poset is called Noetherian if it satisfies the <strong>descending chain condition</strong> (<strong>DCC</strong>), which states that every descending sequence of elements eventually stabilizes. In other words, there cannot be an infinite strictly descending sequence of elements in the set.</p> <p>The primary difference between the two concepts is that being well-partially-ordered is a stronger condition than being Noetherian. While both require the absence of infinite strictly descending sequences (the Noetherian property), being well-partially-ordered also requires the absence of infinite antichains. Therefore, every well-partially-ordered set is Noetherian, but not every Noetherian set is well-partially-ordered.</p> <p><strong>Proposition.</strong> If $E \subseteq J_ {m}$ and $E \neq \emptyset$, then there is a minimal element $k_ {0} \in E$.</p> <p><strong>Proposition.</strong> Let $E$ from the previous proposition be infinite, then there is an infinite sequence $k_ {i}\subset E$ such that $k_ {0}&lt;k_ {1}&lt;\dots$.</p> <p><strong>Proposition.</strong> For the same $E$, the set of all the minimal elements $\text{min}(E)$ is finite. For every element $k\in E$ there is a $k_ {0} \in \text{min}(E)$ such that $k_ {0} \le k$.</p> <h3 id="convergence-of-sets">Convergence of sets</h3> <p>First let’s introduce the symmetric difference of two sets, which is a mathematical operation that results in a new set containing elements that are in <strong>either</strong> of the two sets, but <strong>not in their intersection</strong>. In other words, it combines the elements of each set that are not shared by both. The symmetric difference is denoted by the symbol $\Delta$.</p> <p>Formally, if you have two sets $A$ and $B$, their symmetric difference $A \Delta B$ is defined as: \(A \Delta B = (A - B) \cup (B - A).\) Here, $A - B$ represents the set of elements in $A$ but not in $B$, and $B - A$ represents the set of elements in $B$ but not in $A$. The union of these two sets ($\cup$) forms the symmetric difference.</p> <p>Another way to express this is using the union and intersection of sets: \(A \Delta B = (A \cup B) - (A \cap B).\) By subtracting the intersection from the union, you’re left with only those elements that are exclusively in either $A$ or $B$, but not in both.</p> <p>The symmetric difference has several interesting properties:</p> <ul> <li>It is commutative: $A \Delta B = B \Delta A$.</li> <li>It is associative: $(A \Delta B) \Delta C = A \Delta (B \Delta C)$.</li> <li>The symmetric difference of a set with itself is the empty set: $A \Delta A = \emptyset$.</li> <li>The symmetric difference of a set with the empty set is the set itself: $A \Delta \emptyset = A$.</li> </ul> <p>Now let’s define the convergence of a sequence of sets $E_ {i}, i\in I$, where $I$ is an infinite index set. For each $i\in I$, let $E_ {i} \in \mathbb{Z}^{n}$. We say the family $E_ {i,\,i\in I}$ is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">point-finite</code> if each $p\in \mathbb{Z}^{n}$ belong to $E_ {i}$ for only finite many $i$ (could be zero).</p> <p>Let $m\in\mathbb{Z}^{n}$ and define $J_ {m}$ as before. If the “limit” of $E_ {i}$ is empty, we write \(E_ {i} \xrightarrow{m}\emptyset,\quad \text{iff } E_ {i} \subset J_ {m} \text{ and } (E_ {i}) \text{ is point-finite.}\) More generally, we write \(E_ {i} \to \emptyset\) if there exist $m\in\mathbb{Z}^{n}$ such that $E_ {i}\xrightarrow{m}\emptyset$.</p> <p>Now we can generalize the situation to other than the empty set. To do that we need the concept of symmetric difference. Intuitively, if the limit of $E_ {i}$ is another set $E$, then there should be infinite sets $E_ {i, \, i&gt;j}$ for some $j$ such that they all “tend to” contain $E$. It implies that $E_ {i}-E$ should tend to be empty, for if there is some element $e$ in the limit of $E_ {i}-E$ then $e$ should be in the limit, too. On the other hand, the limit $E$ shouldn’t contain any more element that is not in $E_ {i}$’s. For example, if for all $i&gt;j$, some element $e’$ is not in $E_ {i,i&gt;j}$ then it should not be contained in the limit $E$ as well. These very hand-waving arguments inspires us to define the limit of $E_ {i}$ as follows.</p> <p>We write \(E_ {i}\xrightarrow{m} E,\quad \text{iff }E_ {i} \subset J_ {m} \text{ and } E_ {i}\Delta E\xrightarrow{m}\emptyset .\) All the properties we want for a limit of $E_ {i}$ are concisely contained in the condition that $E_ {i}\Delta E$ tend to the empty set. Also, we simply write \(E_ {i}\to E\) if there exists some $m$ such that $E_ {i}\xrightarrow{m}E$ and we don’t care about the details of $m$.</p> <p>Equivalently, we could say that $(E_ {i}\Delta E)$ is point finite.</p> <p><strong>Example.</strong> Consider $\mathbb{Z}^{n}=\mathbb{Z}^{1}=\mathbb{Z}$. Let $E_ {i} =\left\lbrace i,i+1,\dots \right\rbrace$ for $i\in \mathbb{N}$. Then the sequence $E_ {i}$ is point-finite. We have \(E_ {i}\to \emptyset .\) But if we let $F_ {i}=\left\lbrace -i \right\rbrace$, then even though $F_ {i}$ is point-finite but $F$ can not be contained in some $J_ {m}$ so it does not converge.</p> <p><strong>Notation.</strong> Let $k = (k_ {1},k_ {2},\dots,k_ {n})$ then define $\left\lvert k \right\rvert:=k_ {1}+k_ {2}+\dots+k_ {n}$.</p> <p>For two pints $p,q$ in $J_ {m}$, we can introduce the concept of distance by defining \(d(p,q):= 2^{-\left\lvert p-q \right\rvert }\) This reminds me of Krull topology.</p> <p>For two sets $E,F\subset J_ {m}$, define \(d(E,F):= \sum_ {k\in E\Delta F} 2^{-\left\lvert k \right\rvert },\) then for any $E_ {i}\subset J_ {m}$, we have $E_ {i}\to E$ iff $d(E_ {i},E)\to 0$. And $d$ is a metric on the grid $J_ {m}$.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hamiltonian Truncation in 3D</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Hamiltonian-Truncation-in-3D/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hamiltonian Truncation in 3D"/><published>2023-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Hamiltonian-Truncation-in-3D</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Hamiltonian-Truncation-in-3D/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="background">Background</h3> <h3 id="the-symplectic-manifold">The symplectic manifold</h3> <p>The finite-dimensional covariant Hamiltonian approach to field theory is vigorously developed from the seventies in its multisymplectic and polysymplectic variants. The final purpose is to covariant Hamiltonian quantization of field theory. For classical field theory, the Hamiltonian formalism provides an alternative to the Lagrangian formalism for deriving the equations of motion. Furthermore, the Hamiltonian approach offers a geometrical interpretation of the field theory, in a sense combines geometry and algebra together. To fully appreciate it, we need to know what is a symplectic manifold first.</p> <p>A symplectic manifold is a type of smooth manifold equipped with a special kind of geometric structure known as a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">symplectic form</code>. As we all know, a manifold is a <em>topological space</em> that <strong>locally resembles Euclidean space</strong>. In the case of a smooth manifold, this means that around every point, the manifold can be approximated by a patch of Euclidean space in such a way that the transition maps between these patches are smooth (infinitely differentiable). A symplectic form on a manifold is a specific kind of differential form that is <strong>closed</strong> and <strong>non-degenerate</strong>. In more concrete terms, a symplectic form is a $2$-form, and non-degeneracy means that the form pairs vectors in a way that is <strong>invertible</strong> – no non-zero vector is mapped to zero – ensuring that the form provides a kind of generalized volume element on the manifold.</p> <p>To be more mathematically rigorous, let $M$ be a topological space that is Hausdorff (any two distinct points have disjoint neighborhoods) and second-countable (has a countable basis for its topology). Additionally, $M$ is locally homeomorphic to $\mathbb{R}^n$, meaning every point in $M$ has a neighborhood that is topologically the same as an open subset of Euclidean space (this practically says that $M$ is a manifold). A smooth manifold is a manifold equipped with an atlas of charts such that the transition maps between overlapping charts are smooth. On $M$, a symplectic form $\omega$ is a closed, non-degenerate differential $2$-form. Mathematically, this means</p> <ul> <li><strong>Closed</strong>: The exterior derivative $d\omega$ is zero, $d\omega = 0$. This implies that $\omega$ is <strong>locally exact</strong>.</li> <li><strong>Non-degenerate</strong>: For any vector $v\in T_ {p}M$ where $p \in M$, if $\omega(v, w) = 0$ for all vectors $w$ at that point, then $v$ must be the zero vector. This ensures that the form $\omega$ pairs vectors in a fully invertible way.</li> </ul> <p>Note that a symplectic manifold is necessarily even-dimensional. If $M$ is a symplectic manifold with symplectic form $\omega$, and the dimension of $M$ is $2n$, then $\omega^n$ (the $n$-th wedge power of $\omega$) is a volume form on $M$, providing a natural orientation.</p> <p><strong>Darboux’s theorem.</strong> Locally, all symplectic manifolds of the same dimension are isomorphic. This means that around any point in a symplectic manifold, one can find local coordinates (often called “canonical coordinates” or “Darboux coordinates”) $(q_1, \ldots, q_n, p_1, \ldots, p_n)$) in which the symplectic form has the standard expression $\omega = \sum_{i=1}^{n} dq_i \wedge dp_i$.</p> <p>In classical mechanics, symplectic manifolds serve as the stage for Hamiltonian dynamics. The <em>phase space of a classical mechanical system</em>, which includes both its positions and momenta, <em>can be treated as a symplectic manifold</em>. The symplectic form encodes the fundamental <em>Poisson brackets</em> of the system, which are central to Hamiltonian mechanics. It provides the geometric framework within which the evolution of the system can be elegantly expressed using Hamilton’s equations. The structure of symplectic manifolds imposes several interesting properties. For instance, in <strong>even-dimensional</strong> spaces, they allow for the formulation of Hamiltonian vector fields and symplectic transformations. These concepts have far-reaching applications not only in physics but also in areas like symplectic topology, geometric quantization, and more.</p> <h3 id="hamiltonian-equations">Hamiltonian equations</h3> <p>Most readers are much more comfortable with the Lagrangian formalism of field theory than the Hamiltonian formalism, so let’s start with the former. The transition from Lagrangian to Hamiltonian is achieved by <strong>Legendre transformation</strong>. We first define the canonical momenta $\pi_i$ conjugate to each field $\phi_i$ by \(\pi_i = \frac{\partial \mathcal{L}}{\partial (\partial_t \phi_i)},\) where $\mathcal{L}$ is the Lagrangian density and $\partial_t \phi_i$ is the time derivative of the field.</p> <p>The Hamiltonian density $\mathcal{H}$ is then given by \(\mathcal{H} = \sum_i \pi_i \partial_t \phi_i - \mathcal{L},\) where the sum runs over all fields in the theory.</p> <p>The equations of motion in the Hamiltonian formalism for field theory are then given by Hamilton’s equations, analogous to the Hamiltonian formalism in classical mechanics. These equations are \(\frac{\partial \phi_i}{\partial t} = \frac{\delta \mathcal{H}}{\delta \pi_i},\) \(\frac{\partial \pi_i}{\partial t} = -\frac{\delta \mathcal{H}}{\delta \phi_i},\) where $\frac{\delta}{\delta \phi_i}$ and $\frac{\delta}{\delta \pi_i}$ represent functional derivatives with respect to the field $\phi_i$ and its conjugate momentum $\pi_i$, respectively.</p> <p>From now on let’s assume there are only one type of field and canonical momentum, so we can neglect the subscript $i$. Note here the functional derivative $\delta / \delta \phi$ is not equivalent to the partial derivative $\partial / \partial \phi$. To see this, recall how $\delta \mathcal{H}$ and $\delta \mathcal{H} / \delta \phi$ is defined, \(\delta H =: \int d^{d-1}x \, \delta \mathcal{H} = \int d^{d-1}x \, \delta \phi \frac{\delta \mathcal{H}}{\delta \phi},\) thus all we need to do is to perform a variation of the field $\phi$ and leaving the canonical momentum $\pi$ untouched, then massage the variation of the Hamiltonian in the form given above. For a generic Hamiltonian $\mathcal{H}(\pi,\phi,\partial_ {x}\phi)$ where $x$ denotes all the spatial coordinates, under the field variation $\phi\to\phi+\delta \phi$ we have \(\begin{align*} H\to H' &amp;= \int d^{d-1}x \, \mathcal{H}(\phi+\delta \phi,\partial_ {x}\phi+\partial_ {x}\delta\phi, \cdots) \\ &amp;= \int d^{d-1}x \, \left[ \frac{\partial\mathcal{H}}{\partial \phi }\delta \phi + \frac{\partial \mathcal{H}}{\partial(\partial_ {x}\phi)}\delta(\partial_ {x}\phi) \right] \\ &amp;= \int d^{d-1}x \, \left[ \frac{\partial\mathcal{H}}{\partial \phi }\delta \phi + \frac{\partial \mathcal{H}}{\partial(\partial_ {x}\phi)}(\partial_ {x}\delta\phi) \right] \\ \\ &amp;= \int d^{d-1}x \, \left[ \frac{\partial\mathcal{H}}{\partial \phi }\delta \phi - \left( \partial_ x\frac{\partial \mathcal{H}}{\partial(\partial_ {x}\phi)} \right) \delta\phi \right] \\ \\ &amp;= \int d^{d-1}x \, \delta\phi \left[ \frac{\partial\mathcal{H}}{\partial \phi } - \left( \partial_ x\frac{\partial \mathcal{H}}{\partial(\partial_ {x}\phi)} \right) \right] \\ &amp;= : \int d^{d-1}x \, \delta \phi \frac{\delta \mathcal{H}}{\delta \phi} \end{align*}\) thus, \(\frac{\delta \mathcal{H}}{\delta \phi} = \frac{\partial\mathcal{H}}{\partial \phi } - \left( \partial_ x\frac{\partial \mathcal{H}}{\partial(\partial_ {x}\phi)} \right).\) Taking this back to the Hamiltonian equations we recover the familiar Euler-Lagrange equation.</p> <p>These equations describe how the fields and their conjugate momenta evolve over time, analogous to how the position and momentum of a particle evolve in classical mechanics. They provide a complete description of the dynamics of the field system within the Hamiltonian framework.</p> <h2 id="hamiltonian-truncation">Hamiltonian Truncation</h2> <p>The starting point of defining a quantum field theory is the choice of a manifold $M$ of dimension $d$. We mostly (but not always) regard the manifold as a Riemannian manifold with a <strong>smooth</strong> metric on it. The manifold may or may not have boundaries, if it does then some additional information is needed at the boundaries to define the theory.</p> <p>Having defined the manifold $M$, the next ingredient is the choice of objects to consider over $M$, the so-called “degree of freedoms”, or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">fields</code>. Now it is helpful to adopt a statistical viewpoint toward QFT, in order to extract the information about physical observables we need “just” to know the partition function, which is obtain via a so-called path-integral. That is, we integrate all the possible field configurations with a weight, which is essentially given by the exponent of the action. For example, we may consider a principal bundle with a connection over $M$. In physics terminology the choice of the connection is the same as picking a gauge field. We may also be considering the section of a vector bundle over $M$, these fields are sometimes called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">matter field</code>.</p> <p>As another example of QFT we may consider the space of maps \(X: M\to N\) where $N$ is the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">target</code> manifold. The field theories associated with integrating over the space of such maps are called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sigma models</code>.</p> <p>In quantum field theories we are typically interested in integrating over infinite-dimensional spaces. It turns out that the greater the dimension $d$ of $M$, the more complicated the integrations over these spaces. In fact (ignoring gravitational theories), the only non-trivial quantum field theories that are believed to exist (i.e., for which some kind of integration over the infinite-dimensional space exists) have $d \leq 6$ and most of the standard ones have $d \leq 4$.</p> <p>Quantum field theories in different dimensions can be related to each other by an operation known as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Kaluza–Klein reduction</code>. Roughly speaking this means considering the situation where \(M = N \times K,\quad K \ll N\) The action may be very large for field configurations that are <strong>not</strong> constant over $K$, so the path-integral, which is weighted by $e^{ -S_ {E} }$, localizes to field configurations that are constant along $K$. This gives rise to an <strong>effective</strong> path integral over field configurations that have only constant modes along $K$.</p> <h3 id="definitions">Definitions</h3> <p>In our case, we consider the phi-fourth theory defined on \(M = \mathbb{T}^{2} \times \mathbb{R},\) where $\mathbb{T}^{2}$ is the flat torus space of size $L \times L$, and the time direction $\mathbb{R}$ is left uncompactified. Since the space manifold is compact, the spectrum of the free theory is discrete and free of IR divergence. Following the procedure of canonical quantization, we first expand the scalar field in terms of ladder operators (in discrete form) as \(\phi(\vec{x}) = \sum_ {k_ {1},k_ {2}} c_ {k} a_ {k}e^{ +i \vec{k}\cdot \vec{x} } + \text{h.c.} \tag{1}\) where $\vec{k}$ is the two-dimensional momentum vector $\vec{k}=(k_ {1},k_ {2})$. Since the space is a torus of size $L \times L$, the momentum can only take values \(k_ {i} = \frac{2\pi n_ {i} }{L},\quad n_ {i} \in \mathbb{Z}.\) The coefficient $c_ {k}$ is defined to be \(c_ {k} = \frac{1}{L\sqrt{ 2\omega_ {k} }},\quad \omega _ {k} = \sqrt{ k^{2}+m^{2} }.\) The canonical quantization in terms of the ladder operator is rather simple, \([a_ {k} , a_ {k'}^{^{\dagger}}] = \delta_ {k,k'},\quad \text{zero otherwise.}\) The free Hamiltonian is \(\mathcal{H}_ {0} = \frac{1}{2} \pi^{2} + \frac{1}{2 } (\nabla \phi)^{2} + \frac{m^{2}}{2} \phi^{2},\) where $\pi$ is the canonical momentum. So far we have assumed that the field configuration is static so there is no contribution from the canonical momentum. Taking Eq. (1) to $\mathcal{H}_ {0}$ we have \(H_ {0} = \int _ {L^{2}} d^{2}x \, \mathcal{H}_ {0} = \sum_ {k} \omega_ {k} a_ {k} ^{\dagger} a_ {k} + \text{Const},\) where the constant term is the zero point energy.</p> <p>The free vacuum is defined by $H_ {0} \left\lvert{0}\right\rangle=0$.</p> <p>The interacting Hamiltonian is defined as \(\mathcal{H} (E_ {T}) = \mathcal{H}_ {0} + \mathcal{V}, \quad \mathcal{V}=g_ {2} \mathcal{V}_ {2} + g_ {4} \mathcal{V} _ {4}+ C(E_ {T}),\) where \(\mathcal{V}_ {n} = \frac{1}{n!} :\phi^{n}:\) and $:\bullet:$ denotes the normal ordering. $E_ {T}$ is the truncation energy and $C(E_ {T})$ is a counter terms which will be needed later.</p> <hr/> <p>The Hilbert space is spanned by the eigenstates of the <strong>free</strong> Hamiltonian, $\left\lvert{E_ {i}}\right\rangle$. In the Hamiltonian truncation approach, we only consider the the states with $E_ {i} &lt; E_ {T}=: \Lambda$. In this case, the <strong>full</strong> Hamiltonian can be considered as a finite-dimensional matrix \(H_ {ij} := \left\langle{E_ {i}}\right\rvert H \left\lvert{E_ {j} }\right\rangle .\) At weak coupling, the spectrum of the truncated Hamiltonian can be computed using Hamiltonian Perturbation Theory (HPT).</p> <h3 id="hamiltonian-perturbation-theory">Hamiltonian Perturbation Theory</h3> <p>In quantum field theory, Lagrangian perturbation theory has been dominant, especially in the study of scattering processes and elementary particle physics. This approach’s explicit covariance has been crucial in implementing the renormalization program. However, it complicates the identification of physical states defined as eigenstates of the Hamiltonian and the Hilbert space they span.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Background]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Homotopy-and-Chern-Forms</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Homotopy-and-Chern-Forms/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Homotopy-and-Chern-Forms"/><published>2023-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Homotopy-and-Chern-Forms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Homotopy-and-Chern-Forms/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="lifting-spheres-from-the-base-to-the-bundle">Lifting spheres from the base to the bundle</h2> <p>Let $E\to M$ be a bundle.</p> <p><strong>Sphere lifting theorem.</strong> Any map of a $k$-sphere into $M^{n}$ (with base point $x_ {0}$) can be covered by a map of a $k$-disk into the bundle space $E$, in which the boundary $(k-1)$-sphere is mapped into the fiber $F=\pi^{-1}(x_ {0})$.</p> <p>Recall that a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">covering space</code> is simply a bundle over $M$ with a <em>discrete</em> fiber. The above theorem implies the below theorem.</p> <p><strong>Theorem.</strong> If $\pi: \overline{M} \to M$is a covering space, then the homomorphism induced by projection \(\pi_ {\ast }: \pi_ {k}(\overline{M}, \overline{\ast }) \to \pi_ {k}(M,\ast )\) is an isomorphism for $k\geq 2$. Furthermore, if $k=1$ \(\pi_ {\star}: \pi_ {1}(\overline{M}, \overline{\ast }) \to \pi_ {1}(M,\ast )\) is an isomorphism.</p> <p>We will neglect the proof here, we just mention that this is a result of the fiber $\pi_ {-1}(x_ {0})$ being discrete. And the reason why $k\geq 2$ is special is that the boundary of $k$-sphere, if $k\geq 2$, is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">continuous</code>, hence the image of it also has to be discrete, however the fiber is discrete, so the image must be a single point.</p> <p>As simple corollaries we have \(\pi_ {k}(\mathbb{R}P^{n}) = \pi_ {k}(\mathbb{S}^{n}),\) \(\pi_ {k}(T^{n}) = \pi_ {k}(\mathbb{R}^{n}),\) all for $k\geq 2$.</p> <hr/> <p>We know that $SU(N)$ are all simply connected, $\pi_ {1}(SU(N))=0$. Now we show that $\pi_ {2}(SU(N))$ also vanish.</p> <p>Recall the $SU(N)$ fibering \(SU(N-1) \rightarrow SU(N) \rightarrow \mathbb{S}^{2N-1},\) where $SU(N-1) \rightarrow SU(N)$ represents the inclusion of $SU(N-1)$ into $SU(N)$. Essentially, $SU(N-1)$ can be thought of as a subgroup of $SU(N)$, where the matrices in $SU(N-1)$ are extended to $N \times N$ matrices by adding 1 as an additional diagonal entry. $SU(N) \rightarrow \mathbb{S}^{2N-1}$ is a bit more complex. $\mathbb{S}^{2N-1}$ represents the $(2N-1)$-dimensional sphere, which can be thought of as a set of points in a complex $N$-dimensional space $\mathbb{C}^N$. The map from $SU(N)$ to $S^{2N-1}$ can be understood as taking a matrix in $SU(N)$ and mapping it to a point on the sphere, typically using the action of $SU(N)$ on a fixed point in $\mathbb{C}^N$. In other words, the $\mathbb{S}^{N-1}$ can be considered as the first column of $SU(N)$ and $SU(N-1)$ can be considered as the subgroup of $SU(N)$.</p> <p>From here we have the exact homotopy sequence \(\cdots \to \pi_ {3}(\mathbb{S}^{2N-1})\to\pi_ {2}(SU(N-1))\to\pi_ {2}(SU(N))\to\pi_ {2}(\mathbb{S}^{2N-1})\cdots\) for $N\geq 3$ this gives \(0 \to \pi_ {2}(SU(N-1))\to\pi_ {2}(SU(N))\to 0.\) To see this, recall that we may assume that $f(\mathbb{S}^{k})$ does not cover all of $\mathbb{S}^{n}$ when $k&lt;n$. Suppose then that the south pole of $\mathbb{S}^{n}$ is not covered. By pushing away from the south pole we may push the entire image to the north pole; we have deformed the map into a constant map. Thus $\pi_ {k}(\mathbb{S}^{n})=0$ if $k&lt;n$.</p> <p>Thus, \(\pi_ {2}(SU(N)) = \pi_ {2}(SU(N-1))\dots=\pi_ {2}(\mathbb{S}^{3}) =0.\)</p> <p>In fact, E. Cartan has shown that every map of a $2$-sphere into any Lie group is contractible to a point, \(\pi_ {2}G=0,\quad G\text{ a Lie group.}\) Also, \(\pi_ {3}(SU(N)) = \pi_ {3}SU(2) = \mathbb{Z} \text{ for } n\geq 2\) thus every element of the shape $\mathbb{S}^{3}$ in $SU(N\geq 3)$ can be deformed to lie in an $SU(2)$ subgroup.</p> <hr/> <p>Heinz Hopf discovered an <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">essential map</code> of $\mathbb{S}^{3}$ onto $\mathbb{S}^{2}$, that is, a map $\pi: \mathbb{S}^{3}\to\mathbb{S}^{2}$ which is not homotopic to a constant map. This cannot happen in the case of a 2-sphere mapped into a 1-sphere. With our machinery we can easily exhibit this map. We know that $SU(2)$ acts on its Lie algebra (with three basis, namely the Pauli matrices) as a double cover of $SO(3)$ rotation, and the stability subgroup of the hermitian matrix $\sigma_ {3}$ is the subgroup \(\begin{pmatrix} e^{ i\theta } &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; e^{ -i\theta } \end{pmatrix} \sim \text{ a circle.}\) Thus we have the fibration \(\mathbb{S}^{1}\to SU(2) \to \mathbb{S}^{2}.\) From the homotopy sequence \(0=\pi_ {3}\mathbb{S}^{1}\to\pi_ {3}SU(2)\to\pi_ {3}\mathbb{S}^{2}\to\pi_ {2}\mathbb{S}^{1}=0\) we see that \(\pi_ {3}SU(2) = \pi_ {3}\mathbb{S}^{2} = \mathbb{Z}.\)</p> <p>We have shown that $\mathbb{S}^{3}=SU(2)$ is a fiber bundle over $\mathbb{S}^{2}$ with (nonintersecting) circles as fibers. This is the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Hopf fibration</code>.</p> <h2 id="chern-forms-as-obstructions">Chern Forms as Obstructions</h2> <p>Consider a $U(1)$ bundle.</p> <p><strong>Theorem.</strong> Let $E\to M$ be a hermitian line bundle (that is, a bundle with hermitian metric, $\left\langle u,v \right\rangle=\overline{\left\langle v,u \right\rangle}$), with pure imaginary connection $\omega$ and curvature $\theta$. Let $V$ be any closed, oriented surface embedded in $M$, then \(\frac{i}{2\pi} \int _ {V} \, \theta = \int _ {V} \, c_ {1}\) is an integer and represents the sum of the indices of any sections $s: V\to E$ of the part of the line bundle over $V$. It is assumed that $s$ has but a finite number of zeros on $V$.</p> <p>It is only when this integer vanishes that one can possibly find a nonvanishing section (that is, a frame over all of $V$).\</p> <p>Next, instantons are associated to $SU(2)$ bundles. The winding number of an instanton is given by \(\frac{1}{24\pi} \int _ {\mathbb{S}^{3}} \, \mathrm{Tr}\,\omega \wedge \omega \wedge \omega = - \int _ {\mathbb{R}^{4}} \, c_ {2}.\) It is only when the winding number is zero then we can construct a global frame on $\mathbb{R}^{4}$.</p> <hr/> <p>We have defined the Chern forms for a complex $U(N)$ bundle $E$, \(\det\left( I+\frac{i\theta}{2\pi} \right) = 1+c_ {1}(E) + c_ {2}(E)+\dots\) and we showed that each $c_ r$ is a closed form, and thus defines a de Rham cohomology class. The factor $i$ is to make each $c’s$ real. This cohomology class, with real coefficients, is independent of the connection used, a change of connection (a gauge transformation) will add to the coefficients an exact form hence does not change the de Rham class. The factor $\frac{1}{2\pi}$ ensures the periods are integers.</p> <p><strong>Obstruction cocycle</strong></p> <p>The existing of nonzero $c_ {2}$ is an obstruction of having a nonzero frame over the manifold. It can be shown by fist triangularize the base $M$, then try to extend the section from the $0$-skeleton to $1$-skeleton and so on.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="Geometry"/><category term="Frankel"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lifting spheres from the base to the bundle]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introduction to Resurgence Lecture 2</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Resurgence-Lecture-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction to Resurgence Lecture 2"/><published>2023-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Resurgence-Lecture-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Resurgence-Lecture-2/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="an-example-by-poincare">An example by Poincare</h3> <p>To get some feeling about resurgence, let’s start with an example first given by Poincare. This example shows <strong>how an divergent series emerges from a function.</strong></p> <p>Fix $w\in \mathbb{C}$ and $\left\lvert w \right\rvert&lt;1$. Consider the series of functions of the complex variable $t$, \(\phi_ {k}(t) := \frac{w^{k}}{1+kt},\quad \phi(t):= \sum_ {k\geq 0} \phi_ {k}(t).\) This series is uniformly convergent on \(U:=C^{\ast } - \left\{ -1,-\frac{1}{2},-\frac{1}{3},\dots \right\} .\) Hence the sum $\phi$ is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">holomorphic</code> in $U$. Actually $\phi$ is meromorphic on $\mathbb{C}^{\ast}$ (not on $\mathbb{C}$ since the origin would be a limiting point of the poles) with simple poles at $1 / \mathbb{N}$.</p> <p>We now show how this function $\phi$ gives rise to a divergent formal series when $t$ approaches $0$. The idea is to expand each $\phi_ {k}$ first in terms of $t$. For each $k \in \mathbb{N}$, we have a <em>convergent</em> Taylor expansion at $t=0$, \(\phi_ {k}(t) = w^{k}\sum_ {n\geq 0}(-1)^{n}(kt)^{n}, \quad \left\lvert t \right\rvert&lt; \frac{1}{k} .\)</p> <p>One might be tempted to recombine the (convergent) Taylor expansion of $\phi_ {k}$ to give $\phi(t)$. It amounts to considering the well-defined <strong>formal series</strong> \(\tilde{\phi}(t) := \sum_ {n\geq 0}(-1)^{n} b_ {n} t^{n}, \quad b_ {n}:= \sum_ {k\geq 0}k^{n} w^{k}.\) We see that $b_ {n}$ is convergent since \(\lim_{ k \to \infty } \frac{(k+1)^{n}w^{k+1}}{k^{n}w^{k}} = w &lt;1 \text{ by construction}.\)</p> <p>However, it turns out that <strong>this formal series is divergent!</strong></p> <p>To see this, make the substitution $w = e^{ s }$. Then, since $\text{Re }w &lt;1$, we have \(b_ {0}=(1-w)^{-1} = (1-e^{ s })^{-1}\) and \(b_ {n} = \left( w \frac{d}{dw} \right)^{n}b_ {0} = \left( \frac{d}{ds} \right)^{n} b_ {0}.\) There is an easy way to tell if a series has non-zero radius of convergence, by some kind of a “dominance criterion”. If the series of study $a_ {n}$ is dominated by $AB^{n}$ where $A,B$ are real and $A,B&gt;0$, namely for all but finite $n$ we have $\left\lvert a_ {n} \right\rvert \leq AB^{n}$. Then the formal series \(F(\xi) := \sum(-1)^{n} a_ {n} \frac{\xi^{n}}{n!}\) would have infinite radius of convergence. <strong>$F$ can be seen as a map of the formal series to a function of $\xi$, note that we have inserted a factor of $1 / n!$ into the sum to make is more convergent</strong>. In our case of $b_ {n}$, we see that \(F(\xi) = \sum(-1)^{n} b_ {n} \frac{\xi^{n}}{n!} = \sum(-1)^{n} \frac{\xi^{n}}{n!}\left( \frac{d}{d s} \right)^{n} b_ {0}(s) = b_ {0}(s-\xi) = \frac{1}{1-e^{ s-\xi }} .\) This functions has finite radius of convergence, since the last expression in the equation above diverges at $\xi=s+2\pi i \mathbb{Z}$. The radius of convergence is not infinite! Thus $\tilde{\phi}$ must have zero radius of convergence.</p> <hr/> <p>Now the question is to understand the relation between $\tilde{\phi}$ and $\phi$. We shall see in this note that the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Borel-Laplace</code> summation is a way of going from the divergent formal series $\tilde{\phi}$ to the finite function $\phi$. $\tilde{\phi}$ is actually the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">asymptotic expansion</code> of $\phi(t)$ at $t=0$. We shall explain what it means next.</p> <p>We can already observe that the moduli of the coefficients $b_ {n}$ satisfy \(\left\lvert b_ {n} \right\rvert &lt;AB^{n} n! ,\quad n \in \mathbb{N}\) for some $A,B&gt;0$. Such inequalities are called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">1-Gevrey estimates</code> for the formal series $\tilde{\phi}(t)=\sum b_ {n}t^{n}$.</p> <p>We remark that, since the original function $\phi(t)$ is not holomorphic (nor meromorphic) in any neighborhood of 0, because of the accumulation at the origin of the sequence of simple poles $- \frac{1}{k}$. Thus it would be very surprising to find a positive radius of convergence for $\tilde{\phi}$.</p> <hr/> <p>Resurgence theory can also be used to study power series of the form \(\sum_ {i} \left( \sum_ {j} a_ {ij}t^{j} \right) e^{ -c_ {j} / t }\) note that the variable $t$ appears at two places, once in the series and once in the exponent. The exponent term is the small correction that is invisible to Taylor expansion at $t=0$, and the formal series in the parenthesis diverges.</p> <p>There are many examples of such series in physics. For example, the series could represent the solution of an ordinary differential equation, or the value of some integral, or the perturbative results. In the below is a list of where you might find series like this:</p> <ul> <li>Normal forms for dynamical systems</li> <li>Gauge theory of singular connections</li> <li>Quantization of symplectic and Poisson manifolds</li> <li>Floer homology and Fukaya categories</li> <li>Knot invariants</li> <li>Wall-crossing and stability conditions in algebraic geometry</li> <li>Spectral networks</li> <li>WKB approximation in quantum mechanics</li> <li>Perturbative expansions in quantum field theory (QFT).</li> </ul> <p>There has been some recent work in the physics literature suggesting the possibility that the divergent series obtained from the perturbative expansion may have more information about the true nature of the QFT that one might naively expect.</p> <p>In the next note we will dive into the details of resurgence theory, beginning with the differential algebra $(\mathbb{C}[[1 / z]],\partial)$.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="PureMath"/><category term="CategoryTheory"/><category term="Notes"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An example by Poincare]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introduction to Resurgence Lecture 3</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Resurgence-Lecture-3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction to Resurgence Lecture 3"/><published>2023-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Resurgence-Lecture-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Resurgence-Lecture-3/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="the-differential-algebra">The differential algebra</h3> <p>It will be convenient for us to set $z = 1/t$ in order to “work at $\infty$” rather than at the origin, since we will often talk about compactified spaces. This means that we shall deal with expansions involving <em>non-positive</em> integer powers of the indeterminate. We denote the set of all the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">formal power series</code>, i.e., polynomials in $1 / z$ by \(\mathbb{C}[\![z^{-1}]\!] = \left\{ \phi=\sum_ {n\geq 0}a_ {n}z^{-n} \,\middle\vert\, a_ {i} \in \mathbb{C} \right\}.\) This is a vector space with basis $1, z^{-1},z^{-2}$, etc. It is also an algebra when we take into account the Cauchy product \(\left( \sum a_ {n}z^{-n} \right) \left( \sum b_ {n} z^{-n} \right) = \sum c_ {n} z^{-n}, \quad c_ {n} = \sum_ {p+q=n} a_ {p} b_ {q}.\)</p> <p>The derivation \(\partial = \frac{d}{d z}\) further makes it a <em>differential algebra</em>, which simply means $\partial$ is a linear map which satisfied the Leibniz rules.</p> <p>This is the derivative in terms of $z$, it is natural to ask what is the derivative in terms of $t$. The answer is straightforward, \(\partial = \frac{d}{d z} = \frac{d}{d t^{-1}} = \frac{d}{-t^{-2}dt} =-t^{2} \frac{d}{d t} .\) Then, in mathematical terminology, there is an isomorphism of differential algebra between $(\mathbb{C}[[z^{-1}]],\partial)$ and $(\mathbb{C}[[t]],\partial)$.</p> <hr/> <p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">standard valuation</code>, or sometimes called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">order</code>, on $\mathbb{C}[[z^{-1}]]$ is the map \(\text{val}: \mathbb{C}[\![z^{-1}]\!] \to \mathbb{N} \cup \infty\) defined by $\text{val }(0)=\infty$ and \(\boxed{ \text{val }(\phi) := \text{min } \left\{ n\in \mathbb{N} \,\middle\vert\, a_ {n}\neq 0 \right\} ,\quad \phi =\sum a_ {n} z^{-n} \neq 0. }\)</p> <p>For $\nu \in\mathbb{N}$, we will use the notation \(z^{-\nu}\mathbb{C}[\![z^{-1}]\!] = \left\{ \sum_ {n\geq \nu} a_ {n}z^{-n} \,\middle\vert\, a_ {\nu},a_ {n+1},\dots \in \mathbb{C} \right\}.\)</p> <p>This is the set of all the complex polynomials in $z^{-1}$ such that the standard valuation is no less than $\nu$.</p> <p>From the viewpoint of the ring structure, ${\frak I} = z^{-1}\mathbb{C}[[z^{-1}]]$ is the maximal ideal of the ring $\mathbb{C}[[z^{-1}]]$. It is often referred to as the <em>formal series without constant term</em>.</p> <p>It is obvious that \(\text{val }(\partial \phi) \geq \text{val }(\phi)+1\) with equality iff there is no constant term.</p> <hr/> <p>With the help of the standard valuation, we can introduce the concept of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">distance</code> into the ring of the formal series. Define \(d(\phi,\psi) := 2^{-\text{val }(\phi-\psi)},\quad \phi,\psi \in \mathbb{C}[\![z^{-1}]\!]\) as the distance between $\phi$ and $\psi$. It can only take discrete values, such as $1, 1 / 2, 1 / 4,$ etc.</p> <p>With the definition of distance, $\mathbb{C}[[z^{-1}]]$ becomes a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">complete metric space</code>. The topology induced by this distance is called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Krull topology</code> or the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">topology of the formal convergence</code> (or the ${\frak I}$-adic topology). It provides a simple way of using the language of topology to describe certain algebraic properties.</p> <p>We mention that a sequence $\phi_ {n}$ of formal series is a Cauchy sequence iff for each $i\in\mathbb{N}$, the $i$-the coefficient is stationary, namely the $i$-th coefficient of $\phi_ {n}$ becomes a constant when $n$ is larger than certain natural number.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="PureMath"/><category term="CategoryTheory"/><category term="Notes"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The differential algebra]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Note-on-Cutoff-Kinks</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Note-on-Cutoff-Kinks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Note-on-Cutoff-Kinks"/><published>2023-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Note-on-Cutoff-Kinks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Note-on-Cutoff-Kinks/"><![CDATA[<p>Let $H’$ be the regularized Hamiltonian in the Kink sector, $H$ be that in the vacuum sector. Then $D_ {f}$ is the Morphism that maps from $H’$ to $H$. It should be invertible since there is no loss of information in the process, namely there should exist another map from $H$ to $H’$. Regard different sectors as objects in a category, this category is defined by a (classical) Lagrangian with a quantization functor (maybe), together with a lattice, or equivalently a momentum cutoff $\Lambda$. The map from $H$ to $H’$ is given by \(\boxed { H' = \mathcal{D}_ {f}^{\dagger} H \mathcal{D}_ {f}, }\) where $\mathcal{D}_ {f}$ is the shift operator defined by a function $f$, which usually corresponds to certain classical solitonic solutions.</p> <p>The</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Let $H’$ be the regularized Hamiltonian in the Kink sector, $H$ be that in the vacuum sector. Then $D_ {f}$ is the Morphism that maps from $H’$ to $H$. It should be invertible since there is no loss of information in the process, namely there should exist another map from $H$ to $H’$. Regard different sectors as objects in a category, this category is defined by a (classical) Lagrangian with a quantization functor (maybe), together with a lattice, or equivalently a momentum cutoff $\Lambda$. The map from $H$ to $H’$ is given by \(\boxed { H' = \mathcal{D}_ {f}^{\dagger} H \mathcal{D}_ {f}, }\) where $\mathcal{D}_ {f}$ is the shift operator defined by a function $f$, which usually corresponds to certain classical solitonic solutions.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introduction to Resurgence Lecture 1</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Resurgence-Lecture-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction to Resurgence Lecture 1"/><published>2023-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Resurgence-Lecture-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Resurgence-Lecture-1/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="motivation">Motivation</h3> <p>Why do I want to spend time on this subject? Because they are super interesting!</p> <p>But I should maybe say more about it, so that in the future if I were to apply for some research grant, when someone who knows absolutely nothing about resurgence and its application but who decides whether to give me the money, asks me why is this project important, what use does it have and, eventually, why should I give you the money, then I can come back here and just copy the answer. I would say that god knows I have already wasted too much time on grant applications… but thank god I am atheist.</p> <p>The following is an incomplete list of the potential applications of resurgence theory.</p> <ul> <li>Normal forms for dynamical systems</li> <li>Gauge theory of singular connections</li> <li>Quantization of symplectic and Poisson manifolds</li> <li>Floer homology and Fukaya categories</li> <li>Knot invariants</li> <li>Wall-crossing and stability conditions in algebraic geometry</li> <li>Spectral networks</li> <li>WKB approximation in quantum mechanics</li> <li><strong>Perturbative expansions in quantum field theory (QFT)</strong></li> </ul> <p>The most surprising result, at least for me, of resurgence theory in QFT is that one can uncover the non-perturbative results from perturbative expansion alone! Usually to find the non-perturbative results one need to use anything but perturbative results, such as the topology of the vacuum manifold, the homotopy of the solutions to the equation of motion (instanton solutions, etc.), on and on. But resurgence theory lets us to get the non-perturbative results, for instance the contribution of instantons, from analytical continuation of the perturbative results! On the one hand, it is like black magic; on the other hand, I guess I shouldn’t be too surprised since if we know all the perturbative expansions then we know everything about the equation of motion, which eventually contains all the non-perturbative results, so in principal the perturbative expansion should be able to generate the non-perturbative results. But that is only in principal. It is still jaw-dropping to see it actually happen.</p> <p>And I guess it is impossible to make sense out of perturbation theory <strong>without</strong> knowing some of the resurgence theory. After all, is we consider enough terms in perturbative expansion, the power series in coupling actually diverges, so why would it make any sense to just consider the first few terms? Claiming they give the dominant results would also be ridiculous. The answer lies in resurgence theory.</p> <hr/> <p>H. Poincare mentions the so-called “a kind of misunderstanding between geometers and astronomers about the meaning of the word convergence”, He proposed a simple example, the two series \(\sum \frac{1000^{n}}{n!} \text{ and }\sum \frac{n!}{1000^{n}},\) Poincare says that for geometers, namely mathematicians in his time, the first one converges because at large $n$ the terms gets smaller and smaller. But for astronomers the first one is as good as divergent since the next terms doesn’t get smaller until $n$ is larger than $1000$. For them the second series diverges because the first $1000$ terms decreases quickly.</p> <p>He then proposes to reconcile both points of view by clarifying the role that divergent series (in the sense of geometers) can play in the approximation of certain functions. This is the origin of the modern theory of asymptotic expansion.</p> <hr/> <p>In this note we shall focus on <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">formal power series</code>, such as the Stirling series. Thus the previous example should be written as \(\sum \frac{1000^{n}}{n!}t^{n} \text{ and }\sum \frac{n!}{1000^{n}}t^{n}\) where the first one has <strong>infinite</strong> <strong>radius of convergence</strong> while the second one has <strong>zero radius of convergence</strong>. For us, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">divergent series</code> will usually mean a formal power series with zero radius of convergence.</p> <p>First we will speak of the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Borel-Laplace sumamtion</code>, which obtains a function from a divergent formal series. The relation between the obtained function and the original power series is an example of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">asymptotic expansion of Gevrey type</code>. We shall also introduce the phenomenon for which J. Ecalle coined the name <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">resurgence</code> at the beginning of the 1980s.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="analytic-continuation-and-monodromy">Analytic Continuation and Monodromy</h3> <p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Formal power series</code> is a generalization of normal power series, or polynomial, in the sense that we consider a power series of infinite order and don’t care if it is convergent or not. Provided a ring $R$, consider the set of formal power series in $X$, denoted by $R[[X]]$, is another ring, in the same sense that all the polynomials over $R$ forms another ring (for example, multiply one polynomial to another gives as another polynomial). It is called the <strong>ring of formal power series in the variable $X$ over $R$</strong>.</p> <p>We say a complex-valued function $f:\Omega \to \mathbb{C}$ is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">analytic</code> if $f$ is represented by a convergent power series expansion on a neighborhood around every point $a\in\Omega$.</p> <p>We say a complex-valued function $f:\Omega \to \mathbb{C}$ is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">holomorphic</code> iff it satisfied Cauchy-Riemann relation, which is equivalent to $\partial f/\partial \overline{z}=0$ . If we regard $z$ and $\overline{z}$ as independent variables, a holomorphic function $f$ is only a function of $z$ not $\overline{z}$.</p> <p>A differential manifold is a topological space (given by closed sets and all that stuff) with differential structure, which practically means that you can find a way to do derivatives on the manifold. A n-Dimensional real (Complex) manifold is locally homeomorphic to $\mathbb{R}^N (\mathbb{C}^n)$, plus the condition that the transition from one chart (coordinate system) to another is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">homeomorphic (holomorphic)</code> and vice versa.</p> <p>An <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">open disk</code> of radius $r$ around $z_0$ is the set of points $z$ on $\mathbb{C}$ that satisfies \(|z-z_0| &lt; r.\) A <strong>open deleted disk of radius $r$ around $z_0$</strong> is the set of points with \(0 &lt; |z-z_0| &lt; r.\) a deleted disk is also called a punctured disk.</p> <p>A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">complex atlas</code> on a 2-dimensional manifold is a set of holomorphically compatible charts which cover the manifold. Two complex charts $\mathfrak{U}$, $\mathfrak{U}’$ are said to be <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">analytically equivalent</code> if any atlas in $\mathfrak{U}$ is holomorphically compatible with any other atlas in $\mathfrak{U}’$.</p> <p>By a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">complex structure</code> on a manifold, we mean an equivalent class of analytically equivalent complex atlases on the manifold. If we give a manifold a complex atlas, then we have given it a complex structure.</p> <p>A Riemann surface is a pair $(X,\Sigma)$ where $X$ is a connected 2-dimensional manifold and $\Sigma$ is a complex structure on $X$. The simplest Riemann surface is the complex plane itself.</p> <hr/> <ul> <li>$\mathbb{C} P^n$ Model: The (n+1)-tuple $z = (z^0,\cdots,z^n)$ defines a vector in space $\mathbb{C}^{n+1}$. Define a equivalence relation $\sim$ between two vectors, \((u^0,\cdots,u^n) \sim (v^0,\cdots,v^n) \text{ if } \exists \lambda\neq 0 \in \mathbb{C} \text{ so that } \mathbf{u} = \lambda \mathbf{}{v}\) then \(\mathbb{C} P^{n} \equiv (\mathbb{C}^{n+1}-\{0\})/\sim,\) and the $n+1$ numbers are call <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">homogeneous coordinates</code> and is denoted by $[z^0,\cdots,z^n]$. We can make one of them constantly equal to 1, then only the rest are really coordinates, it is called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">inhomogeneous coordinates</code>.</li> </ul> <p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Meromouphic functions</code> are functions holomorphic except at poles.</p> <p>A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">domain</code> in $\mathbb{C}$ is a connected non-empty open subset of $\mathbb{C}$.</p> <hr/> <p><strong>Riemann Sphere</strong></p> <p>There are two ways to think of $\overline{C} \equiv \mathbb{C} \cup {\infty}$, i.e. the complex plane compactified, by adding a point called infinity, $\infty$ is not included in $\mathbb{C}$.</p> <ul> <li>complex projective plane $\mathbb{C}P^1$.</li> <li>a 2D sphere $\mathbb{S}^2$. The coordinates is given by the stereographic projection, except for the north pole $N$, $\pi : \mathbb{S}^2-{N} \to \mathbb{C}$.</li> </ul> <p>The space $\overline{\mathbb{C}}$ has the structure of e Riemann surface and it is called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Riemann sphere</code>. We can introduce two charts on the Riemann sphere, \(\mathfrak{U}_1 = \mathbb{C},\quad \mathfrak{U}_2 = \mathbb{C}^\ast \cup \{\infty\}\) where $\mathbb{C}^\ast$ is the punctured complex plane, $\mathbb{C}^\ast \equiv \mathbb{C} - {0}$.</p> <p><strong>Theorem.</strong> A function is meromorphic on $\mathbb{C}$ iff its restriction on $\mathbb{C}$ is a rational function.</p> <p>By the restriction of a function, we mean that to restrict the domain so that the it is well defined, no singularities. For example, the function $f:x\to 1/x$ has a singularity at $x=0$, then if we want something which is just like $f$ but has no singularity, we can just restrict the domain to $\mathbb{R} - {0}$, which is said to be a restriction of $f$.</p> <p>A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">germ</code> of functions at a point $\mathbb{C}$ is a set of function defined in the neighborhood of $a$ which all have the same Taylor expansion. A more mathematical definition is as following.</p> <p>Use $\mathcal{O}(a)$ to denote the set of functions which are defined in a neighborhood of $a$ and is holomorphic at $a$. Define an equivalence relation $\sim$ so that if $f\sim g$ for $f,g \in \mathcal{O}(a)$, then $f,g$ are identical on some neighborhood of a. The equivalence class is called a germ of holomorphic functions at $a$.</p> <p>Intuitively, the germ of a function tells us how a function behaves locally at point $a$.</p> <hr/> <p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Fundamental Uniqueness Theorem (FUT)</code> for holomorphic functions:</p> <p><strong>Theorem.</strong> If $f,g$ are holomorphic functions on a domain $D\in\mathbb{C}$ and $f \sim g$ for some point $a\in D$, namely f and g are in the same germ at a, then f is identical to g on $D$.</p> <p>The germ of $f$ will be denoted by $\overline{f}$, if there is no ambiguity about around which point it is defined.</p> <hr/> <p><strong>Analytic Continuation, Monodromy</strong></p> <p>First we introduce the analytic continuation in a different way, more formal and more mathematical. We begin by defining <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pairs</code>. The idea is that, a function is not only defined by the values but also the domain on which it is defined.</p> <p>A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pair</code> $(U,f)$ is a non-zero open disk $U\subset \mathbb{C}$ (why does it has to be open? I don’t know.) and a function, holomorphic on $U$, such that the radius of $U$ is the maximum radius of convergence of the series expansion of $f$. The center of the pair is the center of $U$. Usually $U$ will stop at some singular point.</p> <p>Another concept is adjacency, two pairs $(U,f)$ and $(V,g)$ are said to be <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">adjacent</code> if $U\cap V \neq 0$ and $f \equiv g$ on $U\cap V$.</p> <p>If there is a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">finite</code> sequence of pairs $(U_i,f_i),\quad i = 0,1,\cdots, n$ so that for all $i$, $(U_i,f_i)$ is adjacent to $(U_{i\pm 1},f_{i\pm 1})$, then $(U_0,f_0)$ is said to be the analytical continuation of $(U_n,f_n)$.</p> <p>We can define a analytical continuation along a curve $\gamma: [0,1] \to \mathbb{C}$. The definition is kind of intuitive so I will skip it here. Now the question is, is the analytical continued function $(U_n,f_n)$ dependent on the path? The answer is the monodromy theorem:</p> <p><strong>Theorem.</strong> If the two path are homotopic, then the analytical continuation results to the same functions.</p> <p>If in any doubt, just think of the $\ln{z}$ function.</p> <hr/> <p><strong>Linear Differential System</strong></p> <p>A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">linear system</code> is short for a complex linear ordinary differential system. A linear system of order p is a system with p first order ordinary differential equations.</p> <p>\(\frac{dy(x)}{dx} = A(x) y(x),\quad y(x) = \begin{pmatrix} y_1(x)\\ \vdots \\ y_p(x) \end{pmatrix}\) where $y(x)$ is a column vector of functions, and $A$ is the $p\times p$ coefficient matrix. The system is referred to as $(S)$.</p> <p>We used $\mathbb{C}(x)$ to denote the field of complex rational functions, and $\mathscr{M}(D)$ the field of meromorphic functions on domain $D$, and $\mathscr{O}(D)$ the ring of holomorphic functions on domain $D$.</p> <p>A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">fundamental solution</code> of $(S)$ is a $p\times p$ matrix whose columns are $\mathbb{C}$-linear independent solutions to $(S)$.</p> <p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Wronskian</code> for $n$ functions are defined to be \(W(f_1,\cdots, f_n)(x) \equiv \begin{vmatrix} f_1(x) &amp; \cdots &amp; f_n(x)\\ f'_1(x)&amp; \cdots &amp; f'_n(x)\\ \cdots \\ f^{(n-1)}(x) &amp; \cdots &amp; f^{(n-1)}(x) \end{vmatrix}.\)</p> <p>Let $\Sigma= { a_1,\cdots,a_n }\subset \overline{\mathbb{C}}$ be the set of singular points of $(S)$. Let $U_\Sigma \equiv \overline{\mathbb{C}}\backslash \Sigma$.</p> <p>Recall a nice property of Wronskian: Let $\mathscr{D}$ a domain in $U_\Sigma$, $W$ a $p\times p$ solution of $(S)$, the following are equivalent:</p> <ul> <li>W is a fundamental solution of $(S)$</li> <li>$\det{W(x)}\neq 0$ for some $x \in \mathscr{D}$</li> <li>$\det{W(x)}\neq 0$ for all $x \in \mathscr{D}$</li> </ul> <p>In other words, the Wronskian is either nonzero on the entire domain, or identically zero.</p> <hr/> <p><strong>Differential Galois Theory</strong></p> <p>A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">differential field</code> $(k,\partial)$ is a field $k$ with derivation. A \hl{differential homomorphism} $\phi:(k_1,\partial)\to(k_2,\partial)$ from $k_1$ to $k_2$ is a field homomorphism that commutates with $\partial$. A triple $(k_1, \phi, k_2)$ is called a differential extension. $k_2$ is also called a differential extension of $k_1$.</p> <p>A differential system \(\partial y = A y\) where $A$ is a $p \times p$ matrix.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="Math"/><category term="Transseries"/><category term="Notes"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Motivation]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Categorical Equivalence and the Renormalization Group</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Categorical-Equivalence-and-the-Renormalization-Group/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Categorical Equivalence and the Renormalization Group"/><published>2023-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Categorical-Equivalence-and-the-Renormalization-Group</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Categorical-Equivalence-and-the-Renormalization-Group/"><![CDATA[<p><em>Disclaimer: Nothing in this note is original.</em></p> <p>A short introduction about sheaf can be found <a href="https://www.mathlimbo.net/blog/2023/Basic-Algebraic-Geometry-6/">here</a>.</p> <h4 id="gauged-linear-sigma-model">Gauged linear sigma model</h4> <p>A gauged linear sigma model (GLSM) is a type of quantum field theory that incorporates both gauge symmetry and a set of scalar fields which interact with each other through a potential that is usually taken to be a function of the sum of the squares of the scalar fields. These models are a generalization of the linear sigma models that were originally introduced to describe the dynamics of pions in particle physics.</p> <p>The term “linear” in this context refers to the fact that the potential energy function for the scalar fields is quadratic, at least around the vacuum of the theory. This means that the interactions can be written in terms of fields and their derivatives in a polynomial form that does not exceed second degree when expanded about the vacuum expectation value.</p> <p>Often, GLSMs are discussed in the context of supersymmetry. This means that for every boson (like the scalar fields and gauge fields in the model), there is a corresponding fermion. Supersymmetric GLSMs are particularly interesting for string theory and the study of Calabi-Yau manifolds.</p> <p>In essence, the gauged linear sigma model allows for the study of a wide array of phenomena including spontaneous symmetry breaking, phase transitions, and the dynamics of topological defects. By gauging a symmetry, you add a rich structure to the model that includes interactions mediated by gauge bosons and the possibility of incorporating richer topological properties.</p> <p>A key feature of GLSMs is that they can have a “Higgs phase,” where the gauge symmetry is spontaneously broken and the gauge bosons acquire mass via the Higgs mechanism, and a “Coulomb phase,” where the gauge symmetry is unbroken and the gauge bosons remain massless. Transitions between these phases can often be studied using GLSMs, providing insights into non-perturbative aspects of quantum field theories.</p> <h4 id="toric-variety">Toric variety</h4> <p>We all know what a variety is. So what is a toric variety?</p> <p>A toric variety is a type of variety that is built from combinatorial objects known as fans, which are collections of cones. Toric varieties are particularly nice because they provide a bridge between algebraic geometry and combinatorics, and they are also rich in geometric properties.</p> <p><strong>Algebraic Torus.</strong></p> <p>Start with an algebraic torus $( \mathbb{C}^* )^n$, which is the product of $n$ copies of the multiplicative group $\mathbb{C}^* = \mathbb{C} \setminus {0}$. This group acts on itself by multiplication, and this action can be extended to act on other algebraic varieties.</p> <p><strong>Fans and Cones.</strong></p> <p>A fan is a set of cones (not in the usual sense of solid geometry, but in the sense of vector spaces). These cones are generated by a set of vectors in $\mathbb{R}^n$ that satisfy certain combinatorial conditions – they must be strongly convex (no line can be contained in a cone), and the intersection of any two cones in the fan must be a face of each. The dimension of the toric variety is equal to the dimension of the space where the fan lives.</p> <p><strong>Construction of Toric Varieties.</strong></p> <p>Each cone in the fan corresponds to an affine variety that is invariant under the action of a subtorus of $( \mathbb{C}^* )^n$. The toric variety is constructed by “gluing” these affine varieties together in a way that corresponds to how their cones intersect.</p> <p><strong>Divisors and Line Bundles.</strong> Toric varieties are also interesting because there is a correspondence between the combinatorial data of the fan and the divisor class group of the variety. This makes the calculation of certain cohomological and geometric properties much simpler than in general varieties.</p> <p>A key feature of toric varieties is that they come with a lot of symmetry – namely, the action of the torus. This symmetry makes them easier to study and gives them a rich structure. Toric varieties have applications in many areas of mathematics, including combinatorics, symplectic geometry, and mirror symmetry in string theory. They serve as local models in the Minimal Model Program and are also used in the study of singularities.</p> <p>For a concrete example, consider the complex projective space $\mathbb{CP}^n$, which is a toric variety. The fan for $\mathbb{CP}^n$ consists of cones that correspond to the origin and the standard basis vectors in $\mathbb{R}^n$, as well as all their faces. The rich interplay between the algebraic and combinatorial structures of toric varieties makes them a fascinating subject of study in modern algebraic geometry.</p> <h4 id="stacks">Stacks</h4> <p>Let $\mathcal{T}$ be the category of topological spaces, where the objects are topological spaces and the morphisms are continuous maps.</p> <p>A <strong>groupoid fibration,</strong> or a category fibered <em>in</em> groupoids, over $\mathcal{T}$ is another category (which is a groupoid) $\mathcal{X}$, together with a functor \(F: \mathcal{X} \to \mathcal{T}\) such that there exists a pullback and the pull back is unique. First, some terminologies. If the functor maps $X \in \mathcal{X}$ to $T \in \mathcal{T}$ then we say that $X$ lies over $T$, or that $X$ is a $\mathcal{X}$-family parametrized by $T$, and we write $X / T$. If the morphism $\eta: X \to Y$ is mapped by $F$ to $f: T\to S$ then we say that $\eta$ lies over $f$, or $\eta$ <em>covers</em> $f$. The requirement of pullback essentially says that for every $\mathcal{X}$-family $X / T$ and a morphism $T’ \to T$ there exists another $\mathcal{X}$-family $X’ / T’$ such and such. And this pullback is essentially unique. $X’ / T’$ is said to be the pullback of $X / T$ via the continuous map $f$. We use notations \(X' = f^{\ast } X \text{ or } X' = X \mid _ {T'}.\)</p> <p>Groupoid fibration captures two notions at once:</p> <ul> <li>isomorphism of families. By the arrows in $\mathcal{X}$ (Since $\mathcal{X}$ is a groupoid).</li> <li>pullback.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="Geometry"/><category term="Frankel"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Disclaimer: Nothing in this note is original.]]></summary></entry></feed>