<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-01-18T01:03:40+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Baiyang Zhang</title><subtitle>A place dedicated to sharing insights and reflections on mathematics, physics, and social sciences. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Note on the kink mass correction in 3D</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2024/Note-on-Kink-Mass-Correction-in-3D/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Note on the kink mass correction in 3D"/><published>2024-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2024/Note-on-Kink-Mass-Correction-in-3D</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2024/Note-on-Kink-Mass-Correction-in-3D/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="1-introduction">1 Introduction</h1> <h2 id="11-background">1.1 Background</h2> <p>We will establish the model and notation in this section. First, some nomenclatures.</p> <p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Shape modes</code>: In theories with a kink solution, the equation of motion in the background of the kink typically has discrete, bounded solutions. They are called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">shape modes</code>. They are localized around the kink. Shape modes represent small fluctuations or deformations of the kink’s shape. Unlike the continuum of delocalized modes that represent free particle states, the shape modes are confined to the vicinity of the kink, with discrete energy levels.</p> <p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Oscillons</code>: They are localized, non-solitonic, and semi-stable field configurations that oscillate in time. They are interesting because they represent a form of partial stable, localized energy concentration that can persist for long times, even though they are not topologically protected like solitons or kinks. Oscillons are found in various nonlinear field theories and have been studied in different contexts, including cosmology and condensed matter physics. Their persistence and behaviors under various conditions are subjects of ongoing research in theoretical physics. However, it is believed that quantum correction will make oscillons rapidly decay into a pair of fundamental particles.</p> <p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">The Unruh effect</code>: The Unruh effect is a prediction in quantum field theory, stating that an observer accelerating through a vacuum will perceive a thermal bath of particles, whereas an inertial observer would see none. This effect arises from the realization that <em>the concept of a vacuum state (or empty space) is observer-dependent</em>. For an accelerating observer, what appears as empty space to an inertial observer is seen as a warm gas of particles. This effect, named after physicist William Unruh, highlights the interplay between quantum theory and relativity, especially in contexts like black hole physics.</p> <p>In the frame work of the linearized soliton perturbation theory, we can systematically study the quantum corrections to both static and time-dependent solitonic solutions.</p> <hr/> <p>Firstly, we work in the Schrodinger picture where the operator are time-independent while the wave functions (vectors in Hilbert space) are time dependent. Secondly, we will start with the Hamiltonian formalism where the canonical momentum, $\pi$, is considered as a fundamental ingredient, rather than the time derivative of $\phi$, the field of the Lagrangian.</p> <p>In $2+1$ dimension, the Hamiltonian $H$ is the integral of the Hamiltonian density $\mathcal{H}$ over the 2D manifold of space alone,</p> \[H = \int_ {M} d^{2}x\, \mathcal{H}(\phi,\pi),\quad \mathcal{H}=\frac{1}{2}\pi^{2}(x)+\frac{1}{2} (\partial_ i \phi)^{2} + \frac{1}{\lambda}V(\sqrt{ \lambda }\phi(x))\] <p><strong>Dimensional analysis</strong></p> <p>In Lagrangian formalism, $[S]=[\hbar]$ where $S$ is the action, and $S = \int d^d x \, \mathcal{L}$, where $\mathcal{L}$ is the Lagrangian (density) and $d$ is the space-time dimension. Note that right now we are working with a partially “natural” units, where $c=1$ but $\hbar \neq 1$. Since $c=1$ we still have $[x] = [t]$, namely $L=T$ ($L$ is length and $T$ is time), but no longer do we have $T=E^{-1}$ since this is a result of $[\hbar]=ET=1$ (recall that $\hbar \omega=E$, meaning $[\hbar \omega]=E$, and $\omega$ is the frequency with dimension $1 / T$ ).</p> <p>Let $d$ be the dimension of spacetime, in the partial natural unit we have \(\int d^{d}x \, \mathcal{L}\sim \hbar \implies [\mathcal{L}]=[\hbar] L^{-d}\) Take a specific term, say $(\partial \phi)^{2}$, to continue the analysis, \([(\partial \phi)^{2}] = L^{-2} [\phi^{2}] = [\mathcal{L}] = [\hbar]L^{-d} \implies [\phi^{2}]=[\hbar] L^{2-d}\) which is \([\phi] = [\sqrt{ \hbar }] \, L^{1-d / 2}.\tag{1}\) This agrees with the convention that field operator $\phi$ scales as $\sqrt{ \hbar }$. Furthermore, this scaling property does not depend on the spacetime dimension $d$, it holds for any spacetime dimension.</p> <p>I don’t think the $\hbar$-dependence given by Eq. (1) is unique, apparently there exist other possibilities, we can move $\hbar$ around in the Lagrangian, just to make sure that the action altogether is of dimension $\hbar$. However it seems that $\phi\sim \hbar^{1/2}$ is indeed the most convenient option. Another way to see the advantage of this choice is from the action, \(S \sim \hbar \sim \int d^{4}x \, (m^{2} \phi^{2}+(\partial \phi)^{2} +U(\phi)),\) then \(\int d^{4}x \, \left[ m^{2} \xi^{2}+(\partial \xi)^{2} + U(\xi) \right] \sim 1, \quad \xi:= \frac{\phi}{\sqrt{ \hbar }} .\) In this way, we can absorb $\hbar$ into the definition of $\phi$, this is similar to absorbing the coupling $g$ into the field definition in gauge theory. We now <em>define</em> $\xi$ to be <em>independent</em> of $\hbar$.</p> <p>Having fixed the $\hbar$-dependence of $\phi$, we can substitute it to the potential $U$, for example the $\phi^{4}$ model to determine the $\hbar$ dependence of the coupling, \([S]\sim\int d^{d}x \, \lambda \phi^{4} \sim L^{d} [\lambda][\hbar^{2}] L^{4-2d} = L^{4-d}[\hbar^{2}][\lambda],\) on the other hand we already know that $S\sim \hbar$ so \(L^{4-d}[\hbar^{2}][\lambda] = [\hbar] \implies [\lambda \hbar] = L^{d-4}.\) If we choose $L$ to be the fundamental unit instead of energy $E$, it is clear the $\lambda \hbar$ is independent of $\hbar$. Plus, we see that $d=4$ is special.</p> <p>For the sake of completeness, let’s consider the mass term in the Lagrangian. Similar to what we have for the kinetic term, \([m^{2} \phi^{2}] = E^{2}\, [\phi^{2}] = [\mathcal{L}] = [\hbar]\,L^{-d} \implies [\phi] = [\sqrt{ \hbar }]L^{-d/2}E^{-1} . \tag{2}\)</p> <p><strong>Dimension and measurement</strong></p> <p>If two things are of the same dimension, for example, say \([A] \sim [a] = L\) where $\sim$ means having the same dimension. Then we can use one of them as the unit to measure the other, say, use $a$ as the “ruler” to measure $A$, the result $\widetilde{A} :=A / a$ is a dimensionless number.</p> <p>Suppose $[\phi]=[\hbar]^{1/2}$, another way to say the same ting is $\phi \sim \sqrt{ \hbar }$, note that the tilde does not imply any relation between the <em>values</em> of $\phi$ and $\sqrt{ \hbar }$, it only means that they have the same dimension. The point is, since they have the same dimension, we can use one of them to measure the other, for example we can define \(\tilde{\phi} = \phi / \sqrt{ \hbar }\) which is a dimensionless number. Since $\hbar$ scales the “quantumness”, the more classical the world is, the smaller $\hbar$ (and $\sqrt{ \hbar }$), hence the bigger numeric value of $\tilde{\phi}$.</p> <hr/> <p>In the partial natural units, I’d like to think there are two fundamental “rulers” to measure all the quantities, such as mass, coupling, field, etc. One of them is the unit of energy, for example $\text{MeV}$, the other is $\hbar$ whose dimension is $ET$. To measure the length of something, we can use $\frac{\hbar}{\text{MeV}}$ as unit. The advantage of the partial natural unit is that it makes explicit the $\hbar$ factor, revealing the direct relations between quantities with $\hbar$, which is the scale of quantumness, this enables us to discern the importance of various quantities in the classical limit, making the analysis regarding semi-classical more straightforward.</p> <h2 id="12-digression-on-hbar-expansion">1.2 Digression on $\hbar$-expansion</h2> <p>To appreciate the importance of $\hbar$, just recall that in canonical quantization $[x,p]=i\hbar$, $\hbar$ enters explicitly in the commutation relation, providing the fundamental basis of quantum theory. This is also true in the case of quantum field theory. Furthermore, at each order of an expansion in $\hbar$, the physical symmetries (Lorentz invariance, $U(1)$ symmetry, etc.) must be satisfied, otherwise there will be some special value of $\hbar$ only at which the symmetries are preserved, which is just strange.</p> <p>In the unit where $c=1$, the Planck’s constant $\hbar$ has the unit of action, or rather the action has the unit of $[\hbar]=ET$, where $E$ is the energy scale and $T$ the time. It turns out that there are more than one way to assign $\hbar$-dependence for quantities such as the mass $m$, the coupling $g,\lambda$ etc. A criterion for the “right” choice is that, at $\hbar\to 0$ limit, the quantum theory agrees with the classical theory. As an example, Stanley Brodsky and Paul Hoyer in their <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1009.2313.pdf">paper</a> used the quantum mechanical harmonic oscillator as an example in Eq.(1). The gist is that, you can rescale $x$ to $x / \sqrt{ \hbar }$, then the propagator is formally independent of $\hbar$. However, this will change how we view distance, in the $\hbar\to 0$ limit, for a fixed distance $L$, the “length” measure will increase as $1 / \sqrt{ \hbar }$, hence we are going to smaller and smaller area.</p> <p>It is generally understood that each loop contribution to amplitudes is associated with one factor of $\hbar$. However, to fully define the $\hbar\to 0$ limit one need to specify the $\hbar$ dependence of various quantities in the Lagrangian as mentioned before, such as the field operator, the mass, the coupling, etc. This is not as straightforward as one might think, for $\hbar$ not only appears in the action $iS / \hbar$ but also appears in the Lagrangian. In Brodsky’s paper mentioned above, the authors proposed a way to establish the $\hbar$ dependence such that the loop and $\hbar$ expansions are equivalent. We will go to more details in the following.</p> <p><strong>First, regard $\hbar$ as a constant of nature with certain dimension, use $\hbar$ to make terms in the Lagrangian dimensionless.</strong></p> <p>Again, let’s work with the assumption that $c = \epsilon_ {0} = 1$. Require $[S]=\hbar$, and $\alpha_ {s} = g^{2} / 4\pi \hbar$ is dimensionless, the latter implies that $[g]=\sqrt{ \hbar }=\sqrt{ ET }=\sqrt{ EL }$. From the self-energy of gluons $G_ {\mu \nu}G^{\mu \nu}$ where $G = \partial A - \partial A +ig / \hbar [A,A]$ we have<br/> \([A] = \sqrt{ \frac{E}{L} }.\) For the same reasons, in the scalar QED the classical electric charge $e$ and mass $m$ are divided by $\hbar$, \(S_ {\text{sQED}} = \int d^{4}x \, \left\lbrace \left\lvert D\phi \right\rvert ^{2}-\frac{m^{2}}{\hbar^{2}}\left\lvert \phi \right\rvert ^{2} \right\rbrace , \quad D = \partial +i \frac{e}{\hbar }A.\) The boson field dimension \([\phi]=[A]= \sqrt{ \frac{E}{L} }.\) Fermion fields are more complicated, since they have no classical counterparts, their dimensions are convention-dependent. We will deal with fermions in a different note perhaps.</p> <p><strong>Second step is to specify $\hbar$ dependence of all quantities appearing in the action.</strong></p> <p>The choice made by Brodsky and Hoyer is as following: \(\widetilde{A}:= \frac{A}{\sqrt{ \hbar }},\quad \tilde{\phi}:= \frac{\phi}{\sqrt{ \hbar }}\) where $\widetilde{A},\tilde{\phi}$ are $\hbar$-independent. Similarly, define the following $\hbar$-independent quantities \(\widetilde{g}:= \frac{g}{\hbar},\quad \widetilde{e}:= \frac{e}{\hbar},\quad \widetilde{m}:= \frac{m}{\hbar}.\) Then one can write the Lagrangian in terms of these $\hbar$-independent quantities to check the $\hbar$ dependence explicitly. It turns out that, at least in the simple models discussion in the paper, $\hbar$ always appears in the combination \(\widetilde{g}\sqrt{ \hbar } \quad \text{and}\quad \widetilde{e}\sqrt{ \hbar }\) that is, with the coupling. Hence loop correction of $\mathcal{O}(g^{2},e^{2})$ will be of order $\hbar$.</p> <p>This derivation is equivalent to the standard one of, for example, Mark Srednicki’s textbook, which associates a factor $\hbar$ to each propagator and $h^{-1}$ with each vertex, and assume the parameters appearing in the action to be independent of $\hbar$.</p> <p>Fore more details please refer to Brodsky and Hoyer’s paper mentioned above.</p> <h1 id="2-kinks-in-3d">2 Kinks in 3D</h1> <p>In R. Jackiw’s <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/037015737690048X">1976 paper</a>, he made three assumption:</p> <ol> <li>The energy (mass) is finite;</li> <li>The energy is locally minimum, meaning the soliton is stable;</li> <li>The potential $U$ depends on a coupling constant $\lambda$ according to the scaling law \(U(\phi;\lambda) = \frac{1}{\lambda}U(\sqrt{ \lambda }\,\phi;1).\) The choice is such that all the $\lambda$ dependence are now moved to the pre-factor $1 / \lambda$. As for $\hbar$-expansion, we take the scheme such that $\hbar$-expansion agrees with $\lambda$-expansion, namely each loop brings in a factor of $\hbar$.</li> </ol> <p>Let the Hamiltonian be \(H = \int d^{2}x \, : \mathcal{H} :_ {a},\quad \mathcal{H}(x) = \frac{\pi^{2}}{2} + \frac{(\partial_ {x}\phi(x))^{2}}{2} + \frac{1}{\lambda} V\left(\sqrt{ \lambda}\, \phi(x) \right).\) Now, in order to get the equation of motion, we have two options: 1) Legendre-transform the equation to the Lagrangian formalism and adopt Euler-Lagrange equation, or 2) stick with the Hamiltonian formalism and adopt the Hamiltonian equations of motion (Hamilton equations) instead. Here we will take the second option.</p> <p>Recall that the Hamilton equations in classical field theory reads \(\begin{align*} \frac{\delta \mathcal{H}}{\delta \phi_i} &amp;=-\dot{\pi}(x), \\ \frac{\delta \mathcal{H}}{\delta \pi_i} &amp;= \dot{\phi}_i. \end{align*}\) This is a non-trivial generalization of the familiar Hamiltonian in classical mechanics, non-trivial since the connection between variational derivative and partial derivative is not as simple as one might think, we have \(\frac{\delta \mathcal{H}}{\delta \phi} = \frac{\partial\mathcal{H}}{\partial \phi } - \left( \partial_ x\frac{\partial \mathcal{H}}{\partial(\partial_ {x}\phi)} \right).\)</p> <p>Taking everything into consideration, we can obtain the equation of motion by straightforward calculation. But before going there, let’s rewrite the Hamiltonian in a more compact form: \(\boxed{ \lambda \, \mathcal{H} = \frac{1}{2} \tilde{\pi}^{2} + \frac{1}{2} \vec{\nabla}^{2}\,\tilde{\pi} + V(\tilde{\phi}),\quad \tilde{\pi} := \sqrt{ \lambda }\, \pi,\quad \tilde{\phi} := \sqrt{ \lambda }\,\phi. }\) Then we can first obtain the EOM in terms of $\tilde{\phi}$ and $\tilde{\pi}$, the changing to un-tilded version is trivial. Finally we have \(\ddot{\phi} - \vec{\nabla}^{2} \phi(x,t) + \frac{1}{\sqrt{ \lambda }} V^{(1)}(\sqrt{ \lambda }\phi) = 0\) with definition \(V^{(n)} := \frac{ \partial^{n } V(\tilde{\phi})}{ \partial \tilde{\phi}^{n}}.\)</p> <h2 id="21-normal-modes-and-quantization">2.1. Normal modes and quantization</h2> <p>When kink solutions are placed in more than one spatial dimension, they become extended planar structures called “domain walls.”</p> <p>Now, how can we borrow the kink result form 2D directly to 3D? Consider a static kink solution in the $x$ direction \(\phi(x,y) =: f(x,y)=: f_ {1}(x)\times f_ {2}(y) ,\) where we have assumed the possibility of separation of variables. To say the kink is in the $x$ direction is to say the solution satisfies the equation of motion in the $x$ direction, \(\frac{ \partial^{2} f(x,y) }{ \partial x^{2} } = \frac{1}{\lambda} \frac{ \partial V }{ \partial \phi } = \frac{1}{\sqrt{ \lambda }} \frac{ \partial V }{ \partial \tilde{\phi} } = \frac{1}{\sqrt{ \lambda }}V^{(1)}(\tilde{\phi}).\)</p> <hr/> <p>First, consider the case in 2D. Writing the filed as a kink background plus fluctuation, \(\phi(x,t) =: f(x) + {\mathfrak g}(x) e^{ -i\omega t }\) where $f(x)$ is the 1-dimensional kink solution, the equation of motion in terms of ${\mathfrak g}$ reads \([-\omega^{2}-\partial_ {x}^{2}+V^{(2)}(\sqrt{ \lambda }f(x))]\, {\mathfrak g}(x) = 0.\)</p> <p>As we mentioned before, there are three kinks of solutions: the zero mode, the shape mode and the continuum.</p> <hr/> <p>The equation of motion is the Sturm-Liouville equation. A general Sturm-Liouville problem is typically written in the form: \(\frac{d}{dx}\left[ p(x) \frac{dy}{dx} \right] - q(x)y + \lambda r(x)y = 0\) Here, $y$ is the function of the variable $x$ that we are solving for, and $p(x)$, $q(x)$, and $r(x)$ are known functions that specify the particular Sturm-Liouville problem. The parameter $\lambda$ is often referred to as the eigenvalue.</p> <p>Key characteristics and applications of the Sturm-Liouville equation include:</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Eigenvalue Problem</strong>: The Sturm-Liouville equation is an eigenvalue problem. The solutions $y(x)$ are eigenfunctions, and the associated values of $\lambda$ are eigenvalues. These eigenvalues are typically discrete and can be ordered as a sequence $\lambda_1, \lambda_2, \lambda_3, \ldots$, where each $\lambda_n$ corresponds to a particular eigenfunction $y_n(x)$.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Orthogonality and Completeness</strong>: The eigenfunctions of a Sturm-Liouville problem are orthogonal with respect to the weight function $r(x)$. This property is crucial in solving partial differential equations, as it allows the expansion of functions in terms of these eigenfunctions (similar to Fourier series).</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Boundary Conditions</strong>: Sturm-Liouville problems are typically accompanied by boundary conditions that the solutions must satisfy. These conditions are usually specified at the endpoints of the interval in which the equation is defined.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Physical Applications</strong>: The Sturm-Liouville problem appears in various areas of physics, such as quantum mechanics (in solving the Schrödinger equation), heat conduction, wave propagation, and vibrations analysis. It is essential in the separation of variables technique for solving partial differential equations.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Self-Adjoint Form</strong>: The equation is often referred to as a self-adjoint form, which has important implications in the theory of linear operators and functional analysis.</p> </li> </ol> <p>In our case, the weight function is trivial.</p> <hr/> <p>We will denote the zero mode by ${\mathfrak g}_ {B}$ and the shape mode by ${\mathfrak g}_ {S}$. The $B$ in ${\mathfrak g}_ {B}$ has a historical reason, but in our note it is just part of the name. The normalization conditions are \(\int dx \, {\mathfrak g}_ {S}^{2} = \int dx \, {\mathfrak g}_ {B}^{2} = 1 , \quad \int dx \, {\mathfrak g}_ {B}{\mathfrak g}_ {S} = 0 ,\quad \int dx \, {\mathfrak g}_ {k}(x){\mathfrak g}_ {p}(x) = 2\pi i\delta(p-k).\)</p> <p>The sign of ${\mathfrak g}_ {B}$ is fixed using \({\mathfrak g}_ {B}(x) = - \frac{f'(x)}{\sqrt{ Q_ {0} }},\) where $f$ is again the kink solution.</p> <p>We choose to expand in the $x$ direction in normal modes (in the kink background), while in the $y$ direction in plane waves. The 2D momentum $\vec{k}=\left\lbrace k_ {x},k_ {y} \right\rbrace$, where $k_ {x}=\left\lbrace B,S,k \right\rbrace$, $B$ for the zeromode (bounded solution), $S$ for the shape mode (also bounded) and $k$ for the continuum. A nice illustration of normal modes in the background of kink is shown in the figure below, which I shamelessly copied from Tanmay Vachaspati’s book, all the credits goes to Vachaspati.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/img/kinkLevel-480.webp 480w,/img/kinkLevel-800.webp 800w,/img/kinkLevel-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/img/kinkLevel.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A trivial potential on a periodic space with period $L$ is shown on the left, while the normal modes in the background of a kink solution is shown on the right. What used to be the $n=0$ mode in the trivial potential (on the left) becomes the lowest bound state, the zero mode, in the non-trivial potential. Similarly a linear combination of the $n=\pm 1$ modes in the trivial case may become the second bound state ($n=+1$ in the illustration), and the other states remain unbounded but shift in form. </div> <p>We want to expand the static fluctuation field $\phi(r)$ (defined by $\phi=f_ {\text{kink}}+g$) in terms of normal modes. Since we have defined the indices $k$ in ${\mathfrak g}_ {k}(x)$ to include everything, we can conveniently write the field expansion as \(\begin{align*} \phi(r) &amp;= \sum\!\!\!\!\!\!\!\!\int \frac{\;d^{2}k}{(2\pi )^{2}} \, \left( B_ {k} ^{\ddagger} +\frac{B_ {-k}}{2\omega _ {k} } \right){\mathfrak g}_ {k} (r),\\ \pi(r) &amp;= \sum\!\!\!\!\!\!\!\!\int \frac{\;d^{2}k}{(2\pi )^{2}} \, \left( B_ {k} ^{\ddagger} -\frac{B_ {-k}}{2} \right){\mathfrak g}_ {k} (r), \end{align*}\) where $r = (x,y)$. We adopt the convention \(B^{\ddagger}_ {k} = \frac{B^{\dagger}_ {k} }{2\omega _ {k} }.\) This helps us to jump between different conventions for the field expansion.</p> <p>We have omitted the vector sign (or bold font) in $r$ since it would not raise any misunderstanding. We assume (quite reasonably) the separation of variables $x$ and $y$ for 2D normal modes ${\mathfrak g}(r)$, \({\mathfrak g}(r) = {\mathfrak g}_ {x}\times g_ {y},\quad {\mathfrak g}_ {x} = \text{kink normal modes},\, {\mathfrak g}_ {y} = \text{plane waves.}\) The quantization in terms of $\phi$ and $\pi$ reads \([\phi(r),\pi(r')] = i\delta^{(2)}(r-r').\) This represents the fundamental quantization relation, unaffected by the selection of sectors. We haven’t given a formal definition of sectors, roughly speaking, within each sector, there exists a distinct set of normal modes for expanding both $\phi$ and $\pi$. Each mode must conform to the aforementioned relation, namely the quantization relation given in space-time positions $r$. Ultimately, the difference across different sectors lies in the diverse backgrounds (regarded as classical functions) used for field expansion. However, as we are analyzing the same theory within the same space-time, the theory should be quantized only once, and, all sectors must consistently align with the same quantization process.</p> <h2 id="22-renormalization-methods-review">2.2 Renormalization methods review</h2> <p>Things does get more complicated when renormalization is included. The commonly used renormalization method include (but not limited to):</p> <ol> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Dimensional regularization</code>. This is particularly useful in 4D. This technique regularizes integrals by analytically continuing the number of dimensions of space $d$, usually reduce it by an infinitesimal quantity $\epsilon$. It preserves the gauge symmetry and Lorentz invariance.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Cutoff regularization</code>. This method introduces a high-energy cutoff in the energy. By doing this we are making the momentum integrals finite by force, but as a price we would introduce a new parameter $\Lambda$ with the dimension of energy. This $\Lambda$ has profound physical consequence, such as in dimensional transmutation and, most importantly, the Wilsonian RG flow.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Pauli-Villars Regularization.</code> This approach involves adding hypothetical heavy particles to the theory to cancel out the divergences. The mass of the heavy particles acts effectively as the cutoff in the integrals.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Lattice reguglarization</code>. This method discretizes the spacetime into a lattice. Computations are performed on this lattice, the spacing between different sites, or the resolution of the lattice serves as a cutoff.</li> </ol> <p>There also exist tons of other renormalization methods, such as holographic renormalization, Hopf algebra renormalization, Connes-Kreimer renormalization, and so on. They sounds like fun but, unfortunately, they lie beyond the scope of our work and my comprehension.</p> <p>Different renormalization methods may yield different results depending on the specific sector they are applied to. For instance, the momentum cutoff method produces distinct outcomes when used in the trivial vacuum sector compared to the one-kink sector. From my perspective, it seems more appropriate to <em>consider the regularization method as an integral part of the quantization process</em>. Quantization itself is not a natural, free functor (just means a ); whether one opts for geometrical quantization or path integral quantization (among other methods), additional elements are always needed. For example, incorporating a momentum cutoff is often a crucial step.</p> <p>Different sectors also seem to give different perspectives regarding the relations between different regularization methods. For example, in trivial vacuum sector (which we will just call vacuum sector), the momentum cutoff method is closely connected to the lattice renormalization method, by roughly $\Lambda = 2\pi / a$ where $a$ is the lattice spacing. This very relation is harder to see in, for instance, one-kink sector (which we will just call kink sector).</p> <p>A natural question that follows is, if there exists a regularization method that applies to all the sectors (unlike the momentum cutoff renormalization) equally well? If so, which one? Apparently the space-time itself is the common ground of all sectors, since the lattice regularization is dependent on spacetime alone, it is independent of the specific mode-expansion we adopt for fields, so it seems reasonable to use it as the renormalization scheme. Other advantages of lattice renormalization includes, 1) it made obvious the Wilsonian RG flow, which is continuous change of various parameters in the theory depending on a continuous change of the lattice size. 2) The connection between the lattice quantization and momentum-cutoff renormalization is already know in the trivial vacuum sector. We just need to find a way to generalize it to other sectors.</p> <h2 id="23-lattice-quantization">2.3. Lattice quantization</h2> <p>In our work we will start with the lattice quantization. Recall that the canonical quantization relation in a continuous $d$-dimensional spacetime reads \([\phi(r),\pi(r')] = i \delta^{(d)} (r-r'), \tag{2.1}\) In lattice quantization, the continuous spacetime of the theory is replaced by a discrete set of points, and the fields are defined only at these points. It is a powerful, comprehensive change of viewpoint, not only of numerical importance, but really alters our view of spacetime. In principal we can translate all concepts we have defined in spacetime continuum into the lattice spacetime, such as the gauge connection, gauge field strength, etc. Sometimes, it is convenient to think the lattices as “sample points” of a spacetime continuum. In this view, between the lattice sites there maybe exists something other than the pure void, but it is meaning less to talk about them anyway. This view is rather useful when discussing the connection between lattice quantization and momentum cutoff quantization.</p> <p>The commutation relation on a lattice should take the form \([\phi_ {i},\pi_ {j}] =i\delta_ {ij}, \tag{2.2}\) where $i,j$ are the indices of different sites.</p> <p>Recall that in canonical quantization, Eq. (2.1) translate to the momentum space rather trivially, yielding \([a_ {p},a^{\dagger}_ {p'}] = i (2\pi)^{d} \delta^{(d)}(p-p').\) So the question is, how does the lattice commutation relation translates to different sectors? Particularly, in the trivial vacuum sector and the one-kink sector?</p> <h3 id="231-latticization-of-scalar-field">2.3.1 Latticization of scalar field</h3> <p>Write the scalar field $\phi$ in continuum as as function of spacetime position $\phi(x)$, and write the lattice position as a label of the field $\phi_ {a^{\mu}}$, where $a^{\mu}=m^{\mu} a$, $m^{\mu}\in \mathbb{N}^{d}$ is the $d$-dimensional count of the lattice site, $a$ is the lattice distance. The summation on lattices goes to integral in the continuous limit with the following dictionary, \(\begin{align*} \sum_ {m^{d}} &amp;\to \int, \\ a^{d} &amp;\to d^{d}x,\\ f_ {a^{\mu}} &amp;\to f(x) \end{align*}\) where $m^{d}$ indicates the $d$-dimensional lattice. Combined together we have the familiar formula \(\sum_ {m^{d}} a^{d} f_ {a^{\mu}} \to \int d^{d}x \, f(x).\) We can define two types of differences, corresponding to derivatives in the continuous case \(\begin{align*} \partial_ {\mu} f_ {x} &amp;= \frac{1}{a} (f_ {x+\hat{a}^{\mu}}-f_ {x}),\\ \partial'_ {\mu} f_ {x} &amp;= \frac{1}{a} (f_ {x}-f_ {x-\hat{a}^{\mu}}), \end{align*}\) where $\hat{a}^{\mu}$ is a vector in direction $x^{\mu}$ of length $a$, namely $\hat{a}$ moves to the next lattice site in the $x^{\mu}$ direction. These two differences are like differences “from right” and “from left”. For smooth functions of course their continuous limit all give the derivative.</p> <p>The interesting thing is that these two types of differences are kind of dual to each other. Define an inner product \((f_ {x},g_ {x}) := \sum_ {x} f_ {x} g_ {x},\) similar to what we have for differential forms, then \((f_ {x},\partial g_ {x}) = (-\partial' f_ {x},g_ {x}),\) which corresponds to the integral by part \(\int \, f\partial g = \int \,(-\partial f) g.\)</p> <h3 id="232-second-quantization-in-the-vacuum-sector">2.3.2 Second quantization in the vacuum sector</h3> <p>First let’s review how the second quantization is achieved in the vacuum sector without latticization, namely on a continuum of spacetime of dimension $d+1$. This is what we learnt from textbooks.</p> <p>Note that we will adopt a slight change of variable here. Before we used $\vec{r}$ to denote the spatial vector where $\vec{r}=(x,y, \cdots)$ since in two dimensional space time, it is easier to write $x,y$ than $x_ {1},x_ {2}$. However, since now we are dealing with $d+1$ dimensional spacetime, we will also adopt a different convention, namely $x=(t,\vec{x})$ where $\vec{x}$ is a $d$-dimensional vector with components $x_ {1},\cdots,x_ {d}$. In summary, Latin letters without a vector sign $x$ are covariant $d+1$-vectors, the generalization of $4$-vector to arbitrary dimension.</p> <p>The simplest special relativistic equation of motion a field $\phi$ can satisfy is the massless Klein-Gordon equation, \(\partial^{2}\phi=0,\quad \partial^{2}=\partial_ {\mu}\partial^{\mu}=\partial_ {t}^{2}-\nabla^{2}.\) Decompose $\phi$ into a continuum of momentum mode, each mode can be written as \(a_ {p} (t) e^{ i\vec{p}\cdot \vec{x} }\) where we have assume the separation of variable $t$ and $\vec{x}$, and the time-dependent part of the Klein-Gordon equation gives \((\partial_ {t}^{2}+\vec{p}\cdot \vec{p})a_ {p} (t) = 0\) with solutions \(a_ {p} (t) =a_ {p} e^{ \pm i\omega t},\quad \omega^{2}= \vec{p}^{2}.\) where $a_ {p}$ now is just some c-number, constant in time. The field can be expanded as a linear combination of all the momentum modes \(\phi(t,\vec{r}) = \int \frac{d^{d}p}{(2\pi)^{d}} \, (a_ {p} e^{ -ipx }+a_ {p} ^{\ast }e^{ipx })\) where the second term in the parenthesis is to make sure that $\phi$ is real. We have assembled $\omega$ and $\vec{p}$ into $p=(\omega,\vec{p})$.</p> <p>Now the second quantization kicks in. This is usually first done in the momentum space, since we are treating each mode as a harmonic oscillator. You can already see one aspect of the difference between the previously define lattice quantization and the textbook second quantization. We introduce the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">equal-time commutation relation</code> \([a_ {k} ,a_ {p}^{\dagger}] = (2\pi)^{d} \,\delta^{d}(\vec{k}-\vec{p}),\) where we have omitted the vector sign in the superscript $k,p$ to avoid overly cumbersome notation. The factors of $2\pi$ are a convention, stemming from our convention for Fourier transform, for the details see my other blog on conventions.</p> <p>We want the operators $a_ {p}^{\dagger}$ to create particles with momentum $\vec{p}$. Let $\left\lvert{\vec{p}}\right\rangle$ be a physical state with a single particle with momentum $\vec{p}$, <em>define</em> \(a_ {p} ^{\dagger}\left\lvert{\Omega}\right\rangle = \frac{1}{\sqrt{ 2\omega _ {p} }}\left\lvert{\vec{p}}\right\rangle ,\) where $\left\lvert{\Omega}\right\rangle$ is the ground state in the vacuum sector. This factor of $1 / \sqrt{ 2\omega _ {p} }$ is just another convention.</p> <p>From the normalization $\left\langle \Omega \middle\vert \Omega \right\rangle=1$ and the commutation of $a,a^{\dagger}$ we get \(\left\langle \vec{p} \middle\vert \vec{k} \right\rangle =2\omega _ {p} (2\pi)^{d}\delta^{d}(\vec{p}-\vec{k}).\) As a result, the identity operator for one particle states is \(\mathbb{1}=\int \frac{d^{d}p}{(2\pi)^{d}} \, \frac{1}{2\omega _ {p} }\left\lvert{\vec{p}}\right\rangle \left\langle{\vec{p}}\right\rvert .\) We define the quantum field as integrals over $a_ {p}$ and $a_ {p}^{\dagger}$, \(\phi_ {0}(\vec{x})= \int \frac{d^{d}p}{(2\pi)^{d}} \, \frac{1}{\sqrt{ 2\omega }} (a_ {p} e^{ i\vec{p} \cdot \vec{x}} + a_ {p} ^{\dagger}e^{ -i\vec{p}\cdot \vec{x} })\) where the subscript $0$ indicates this is a free field. The traditional view is to take it as the definition of the field operator $\phi_ {0}$ constructed from the creation and annihilation operators $a_ {p}$ and $a_ {p}^{\dagger}$ (<em>Schwartz M.D.</em>), but we shall try an opposite viewpoint, as will be shown later.</p> <p>Later we will work with the Schrodinger picture which is less commonly used compared to the Heisenberg or interaction pictures. To finish the review on the second quantization, we just mentioned that in Heisenberg picture, all the time dependence is in operators such as $\phi$ and $a_ {p}$, the field operator reads \(\phi_ {0}(\vec{x},t) = \int \frac{d^{d}p}{(2\pi)^{d}} \, \frac{1}{\sqrt{ 2\omega _ {p} }}(a_ {p} e^{ -ipx } + a_ {p} ^{\dagger}e^{ ipx }),\) which is also Lorentz invariant.</p> <hr/> <p>Instead of the traditional view of harmonic oscillator quantization in the momentum space, let’s take Eq.(2) as the starting point. Adopt a somewhat un-conventional field expansion \(\begin{align*} \phi(\vec{x}) &amp;= \int \frac{d^{d}p}{(2\pi)^{d}} \, e^{ -i\vec{x}\cdot \vec{p} }\phi_ {p},\\ \pi(\vec{x}) &amp;= \int \frac{d^{d}p}{(2\pi)^{d}} \, e^{ -i \vec{x}\cdot \vec{p} }\pi_ {p}. \end{align*}\) The next question is how to inverse it on a lattice…</p> <h3 id="24-21-dimensional">2.4 (2+1)-dimensional</h3> <p>For now, let’s accept (1) the ultraviolet cutoff $\Lambda$ and (2) the harmonic quantization <em>in the trivial vacuum sector</em> and translate it to the physical spacetime. As a result we get a non-local commutation relation in spacetime, \([\phi(x),\pi(y)]_ {\Lambda} = i \int_{-\Lambda}^{\Lambda} \frac{dp}{2\pi} \, e^{ -ip(x-y)} = i \frac{\sin(\Lambda x)}{\pi x} .\) This is non-local in the sense that for certain $x\neq y$ the commutator is nonzero. However, this commutation relation does agree with the lattice picture, if we set the lattice spacing to be $\pi / \Lambda$! (check for yourself)</p> <p>Now we can define the normal ordering in the vacuum sector, then propagate it to the kink sector via the displacement operator, which we will talk about shortly.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[1 Introduction]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Representables in Category Theory</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2024/Representables-in-Category-Theory/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Representables in Category Theory"/><published>2024-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2024/Representables-in-Category-Theory</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2024/Representables-in-Category-Theory/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="representables">Representables</h3> <p>A category is a world of objects, all looking at one another. Each sees the world from a different viewpoint. Take the category of topological spaces for example, consider the object with only one point, denoted $\star$, given another topological space $T$, a map \(\star\to T\) can be regarded as $\star$ looking at $T$. What does $\star$ see? Since $\star$ itself is a point, the image given by a continuous map (by definitions the morphisms in the category of topological spaces are continuous maps) of $\star$ is another point in $T$, that’s to say, a point can only see points! It can’t see any other structures, limited by what it is. This is similar to what happens in a society with real people in it. A curve, on the other hand, could see much more. It can see a point if it wants, but it can also see another curve in other objects. In the language of category theory, all the things an object could see translates into <em>the set of arrow going out from it</em>.</p> <p>We can also ask the dual question: <em>fixing an object of a category, what are maps into it</em>? Take the category $\text{Set}$ of sets for example. Consider a set with only two elements. Given any set $X$, the maps from $X$ to the two element set is the subset of $X$!</p> <p>In the following we will talk about how each object sees and is seen by the category. This naturally leads to the notion of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">representable functors</code>, or just <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">representables</code>.</p> <hr/> <p>Fix an object $A \in \mathcal{A}$. Consider the <em>totality</em> of maps <em>out of</em> $A$. To each $B\in \mathcal{A}$, there is assigned the set $\mathcal{A}(A,B)$ of maps from $A$ to $B$. This assignation is actually <strong>functorial</strong>, in the sense that to <em>each</em> $B\in\mathcal{A}$, there is a set $A(A,B)$, and to each arrow in $A$, there is another arrow in the codomain of this functorial, which we will define shortly.</p> <p><strong>Definition 1.</strong> Let $\mathcal{A}$ be a locally small (meaning that the arrows from one object to another actually form a set) category and $A\in \mathcal{A}$. Define a functor \(H^{A}: B \mapsto \mathcal{A}(A,B)\) where $\mathcal{A}(A,B)$ are the collection of arrows from $A$ to $B$, here $\mathcal{A}(A,B)$ is regarded as a set. Thus \(H^{A}: \mathcal{A}\to \text{Set}\) where $\text{Set}$ is the category of sets, of which the objects are all kinds of sets and the arrows are function from one set to another. Let $B\in \mathcal{A}$ be an object in $\mathcal{A}$. Obviously $H^{A}$ is a <em>set-valued functor</em> defined on $\mathcal{A}$. For $A’ \in \mathcal{A}$, \(H^{A}(A') := \mathcal{A}(A \to A') \text{ regarded as a set}.\)</p> <p>An easy way to remember the direction of arrow (at least for me) is to think of $A$ in $H^{A}$ standing up high, since it is a superscript, it is standing “upstairs”, as a result $A$ has a pretty good view, allowing it to “see” other objects (say, $B$) in $\mathcal{A}$, and the arrow $A \to B$ represents that $A$ is watching $B$. With this analogy, in novel <em>1984</em> by Orwell, the big brother is watching everyone in the nation, making him the <em>initial object.</em> Similarly, given $A \in \mathcal{A}$, when we need to talk about arrow coming from other objects <em>into</em> $A$ later, we will define the functor $H_ {A}$ where $H_ {A}(B)$ is the set of arrows from $B$ to $A$ this time, for $A$ sits at the bottom and everyone can see $A$.</p> <p>For a map $g: A’ \to A’’$ in $\mathcal{A}$, $H^{A}$ maps $g$ to another map from $H^{A}(A’)$ to $H^{A}(A’’)$ by composition, that is<br/> \(H^{A}(A'): A \to A', \quad H^{A}(A'') : A\to A'', \quad H^{A}(g): (A\to A') \to (A\to A'')\) where $H^{A}(g)$ is realized by \(A\to A' \xrightarrow{g} A''\) which is a map from $A$ to $A’’$, hence an element of $H^{A}(A’’)$.</p> <p>To explain it in a different way, consider object $X\in H^{A}(A’)$, $X$ by construction is a map from $A$ to $A’$. Let $Y \in H^{A}(A’’)$, then $Y$ is nothing but a map from $A$ to $A’’$. Now, what is an arrow from $X$ to $Y$? It is something that maps $A\to A’$ to $A \to A’’$, which can be achieved by the composition $g\,\circ\,X$, where $g: A’ \to A’’$.</p> <p>Sometimes $H^{A}(g)$ is written as $g\,\circ\,-$, where $-$ is a commonly used symbol as a place holder; or written as $g_ {\ast}$, reminding us that it is somehow “induced” by $g$. All are frequently used in publications.</p> <hr/> <p>Again, let $A$ be a locally small (the collection of morphisms between any two objects is a set) category. A functor \(X: \mathcal{A} \to \text{Set}\) is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">representable</code> if \(X \cong H^{A} \text{ for some } A \in \mathcal{A}.\) $A$ is said to be a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">representation</code> of $X$, together with an isomorphism between $H^{A}$ and $X$. In other words, when dealing with a representable functor $X$, identifying a representation for $X$ requires more than just specifying an object $A$; we must also precisely determine how $X$ is isomorphic to $H^A$.</p> <p>Representable functors are sometimes just called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">representables</code>. Only set-valued functors (functors with codomain $\text{Set}$) can be representable.</p> <p>Representable functors are important for a few reason in category theory. The Yoneda Lemma, which is the topic of this note, is a fundamental result in category theory that involves representable functors. We will introduce the Yoneda lemma shortly, but shortly put it, it states that <em>every functor</em> is <em>naturally isomorphic</em> to a functor represented by some object in the category. This lemma provides a powerful tool for embedding any locally small category into a category of functors (where the arrows are natural transformations). The Yoneda embedding, which arises from this, embeds a category into a category of presheaves, preserving and reflecting properties of objects and morphisms. If you don’t know (or not interested in) what a presheave is, just ignore it.</p> <p>Representable functors are key in the study of natural transformations. The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">naturality condition</code> in the definition of natural transformations can be better understood and characterized using representables. Representables also play a role in the study of adjoints and limits, which are some key-important concepts in category theory. For instance, adjoint functors can often be characterized using representables, and the existence of certain limits and colimits (limits where all the arrows are reversed) can be analyzed through representable functors. Representable functors are also indispensable to sheaf theory and topos theory, providing a link between geometric intuition and abstract category-theoretic formalism. Unfortunately these fascinating results lie outside the scope of this simple note, or for that matter lie outside of my comprehension.</p> <hr/> <p>Since we are already talking about the category of functors, it is perhaps timely to mention two similar but distinct definitions in category theory, namely the category of functors and the so-called $2$-category.</p> <ul> <li> <p><strong>Category of Functors</strong>: This is a construction where the objects are functors and the morphisms between these objects are natural transformations. Specifically, given two categories $\mathcal{C}$ and $\mathcal{D}$, the category of functors, often denoted $\text{Fun}(\mathcal{C}, \mathcal{D})$, has as objects all functors from $\mathcal{C}$ to $\mathcal{D}$ and as morphisms the natural transformations between these functors.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>$2$-Category</strong>: A $2$-category is a more general and abstract concept. In a $2$-category, there are objects, morphisms between objects (also called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">1-morphisms</code>), and morphisms between morphisms (called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">2-morphisms</code>), or “arrows between arrows”. This structure introduces a new level of morphisms.</p> </li> </ul> <p>In a certain sense, the category of functors between two categories can be seen as a specific example of a 2-category, where the objects are the categories, the 1-morphisms are the functors between these categories, and the 2-morphisms are the natural transformations between these functors. However, the concept of a 2-category is broader and can be applied to many other contexts beyond just categories and functors.</p> <hr/> <p><strong>Ex.1</strong> Consider the category of sets, denoted $\text{Set}$, let $1$ be the set of only one element. Now, what would $H^{1}$ be? It can be written as \(\text{Mor}(1,-) \text{ or } \text{Hom}(1,-) \text{ or } \text{Set}(1,-),\) they all mean the same thing: the maps from $1$ to something else. Let $S \in Set$, $H^{1}(S)$ would be the collection of the maps from $1$ to $S$, which is itself another set, hence \(H^{1}: \text{Set} \to \text{Set}.\) Since a map from $1$ to a set $S$ amounts to an element of $S$, we have \(H^{1}(S) \cong S \quad \;\forall\; S \in \text{Set}.\) It can be shown (which I will not do here) that this isomorphism is <em>natural</em> in $S$, so $H^{1}$ is naturally isomorphic to the identity functor $\mathbb{1}_ {\text{Set}}$. Hence $\mathbb{1}_ {\text{Set}}$ is representable, by $1$.</p> <hr/> <p>Representability is not a property shared by just any set-valued functor. In fact, rather few functors are representable, consider the total amount of functors we could construct. However, forgetful functors <em>tend to be</em> representable. We state without proof the following proposition.</p> <p><strong>Proposition.</strong> Any set-valued functor with a left adjoint is representable.</p> <hr/> <p>We have defined, for each object $A$ of category $\mathcal{A}$ , a functor $H^{A}\in[\mathcal{A},\text{Set}]$ (given two categories $\mathcal{A}$ and $\mathcal{B}$, $[\mathcal{A},\mathcal{B}]$ is the functor category from the former to the latter). This describes how $A$ sees the world. As $A$ varies, so does the view. On the other hand, it is always the same world being seen, so the different views from different objects are somehow related. Generally speaking, whenever there is a map between objects $A$ and $A’$, there is also a map between $H^{A}$ and $H^{A’}$. Since $H^{A}$ are $H^{A’}$ are both functors (the “view” of $A,A’$), a map between them are potentially natural transformation, potentially since we need to show that this map satisfies the rule of naturality.</p> <p>Precisely, a map \(f: A' \to A,\quad A,A'\in \mathcal{A}\) induces a natural transformation \(H^{f} : H^{A} \to H^{A'}.\) An interactive diagram of this can be found <a href="https://q.uiver.app/#q=WzAsMixbMCwwLCJcXG1hdGhjYWx7QX0iXSxbMywwLCJcXHRleHR7U2V0fSJdLFswLDEsIkheQSIsMCx7ImN1cnZlIjotNH1dLFswLDEsIkhee0EnfSIsMix7ImN1cnZlIjo0fV0sWzIsMywiSF5mIiwwLHsic2hvcnRlbiI6eyJzb3VyY2UiOjIwLCJ0YXJnZXQiOjIwfX1dXQ==">here</a>.</p> <p>Recall that a natural transformation $\alpha$ between two functors $F$ and $G$, both from category $\mathcal{C}$ to category $\mathcal{D}$, is made up of components. Each component is a morphism in category $\mathcal{D}$.</p> <p>For each object $X$ in category $\mathcal{C}$, the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">component</code> of the natural transformation $\alpha$ at $X$ is a morphism in category $\mathcal{D}$: \(\alpha_ X : F(X) \rightarrow G(X)\) These components must satisfy a naturality condition, which states that for every morphism $f: X \rightarrow Y$ in category $\mathcal{C}$, the naturality diagram commutes. The naturality condition must hold for all objects and morphisms in category $C$, making the transformation “natural” in the sense that it works consistently across the entire category.</p> <p>Coming back to $H^{f}$. Let $B\in \mathcal{A}$, what would the component $H^{f}_ {B}$ be? Recall that $f$ maps from $A’$ to $A$, by construction $H^{f}$ maps in the opposite direction, it is the function \(H^{A}(B) \equiv \mathcal{A}(A,B) \to H^{A'}(B)\equiv \mathcal{A}(A',B),\) in terms of the elements, let $p \in \mathcal{A}(A,B)$ we have \(H^{f}: p \mapsto p\,\circ\,f.\)</p> <p>Notice that, each $H^{A}$ is <em>covariant</em> (meaning they preserve the direction of the arrows), however they come together to form a <em>contravariant</em> thing! What exactly is this thing then? To understand it, the following definition is important:</p> <p>Let $\mathcal{A}$ be a locally small category, the functor \(H^{-}: \mathcal{A}^{\text{op}} \to [\mathcal{A},\text{Set}]\) is defined on objects $A$ by $H^{-}(A)=H^{A}$, and on maps $f$ by $H^{-}(f)=H^{f}$.</p> <p>A lot of explain regarding the notations is in order. Apparently the dash $-$ in $H^{-}$ is a placeholder, to be filled by whatever it acts on, no matter if it is an object or an arrow. $\mathcal{A}^{\text{op}}$ is the opposite, or dual category of $\mathcal{A}$, with same objects but reversed arrows (all of them). $\mathcal{A}^{\text{op}}$ is a category, $[\mathcal{A},\text{Set}]$ is another category ( of functors from $\mathcal{A}$ to $\text{Set}$), thus $H^{-}$ is a functor. $H^{-}$ of $A$ is $H^{A}$, which is a set-valued functor on $\mathcal{A}$, hence $H^{A}$ is an object of $[\mathcal{A},\text{Set}]$.</p> <p>All of the definitions presented so far in this chapter can be dualized. At the formal level, this is trivial: just reverse all the arrows! But in our analogy, after dualize it, we are no longer asking what objects see, but <em>how they are seen</em>:</p> <p>Let $\mathcal{A}$ be a <em>locally small</em> category and $A\in \mathcal{A}$. We define a functor $H_ {A}$ as follows, \(H_ {A} := \mathcal{A}(-,A): \mathcal{A}^{\text{op}}\to\text{Set}\) where</p> <ul> <li>for objects $B \in \mathcal{A}$, put $H_ {A}(B) = \mathcal{A}(B,A)$;</li> <li>For maps $g:B’\to B$, define \(H_ {A}(g) = \mathcal{A}(g,A) = g^{\ast } = - \,\circ\,g: \mathcal{A}(B,A)\to\mathcal{A}(b',A)\) by \(p\mapsto p\,\circ\,g \quad \;\forall\; p: B\to A.\)</li> <li> <ul> <li>-</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>Note that a map $B’\to B$ induces a map in the opposite direction, $H_ {A}(B)\to H_ {A}(B’)$.</p> <p>We now define representability for <em>contravariant set-valued</em> functors.</p> <p>Let $\mathcal{A}$ be a locally small category, and $X$ be a set-valued contravariant functor, \(X: \mathcal{A}^{\text{op}} \to \text{Set}.\) We say $X$ is <strong>representable</strong> is $X \cong H_ {A}$ for some $A\in \mathcal{A}$. A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">representation</code> of $X$ is a choice of $A$ and an isomorphism between $X$ and $H_ {A}$.</p> <p>As an example, take the power set (contravariant-)functor $\mathcal{P}$ for example. Recall that the power set $\mathcal{P}(S)$ of a set $S$ is the collection of subsets of $S$. Let $S,S’\in \text{Set}$ be two sets, and $f: S \to S’$ a map (morphism) in the category of sets. Since we are regarding $\mathcal{P}$ as a contravariant functor, we should define $\mathcal{P}(f)$, which is a map from $\mathcal{P}(S’)$ to $\mathcal{P}(S)$, notice the inversed direction. Well, turns out this can be done in a more or less direct way: we define $\mathcal{P}(f)$ to be in a sense the <em>inverse</em> of $f$! Take $U\in\mathcal{P}(S’)$, we define the action on $U$ by $\mathcal{P}(f)$ by $f^{-1}(U)$, where $f^{-1}$ is <strong>not</strong> the inverse of $f$, for we didn’t assume that $f$ is invertible at all, but rather the preimage of $f$, \(f^{-1} (U) := \left\lbrace s\in S \,\middle\vert\, f(s)\in U \right\rbrace .\) On the other hand, the subsets of $S$ can be regarded as a maps from $S$ to $2$, the set with two elements, which we call <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">true</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">false</code>. To see how it works, take $S=\left\lbrace 1,2 ,3\right\rbrace$, the subset $\left\lbrace 1,2 \right\rbrace$ can be regarded as a map $g: S\to \left\lbrace \text{true,false} \right\rbrace$ where $1,2$ are map to true and $3$ is mapped to false. Such maps are sometimes called the characteristic functions. This provides as another way to look at power sets, and confirms the idea that in category theory everything is a morphism!</p> <p>Note that $\chi:=\left\lbrace \text{true,false} \right\rbrace$ is itself an object in $\text{Set}$, so we can talk about the Hom-functor $H_ {\chi}$, defined by maps from other stuff into $\chi$. Maybe not too surprisingly, $H_ {\chi}$ is isomorphic to the power functor $\mathcal{P}$, \(\mathcal{P} \cong H_ {\chi}.\) Try to convince yourself with it, better with some simple examples. Thus we say the power functor $\mathcal{P}$ is representable, and the representation is $\chi$.</p> <hr/> <p>Just as we assembled the covariant representables $H^{A}$s into a big functor $H^{-}$, we can do the same for the contravariant representables. If $f: A \to A’$ is a map in $\mathcal{A}$, there is an induced natural transformation $H_ {f}$: \(H_ {f}: H_ {A} \to H_ {A'},\quad H_ {A,A'}: \mathcal{A}\to\text{Set}.\)</p> <hr/> <p>Let $\mathcal{A}$ be a locally small category. The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Yoneda embedding</code> of $\mathcal{A}$ is the functor \(H_ {-}: \mathcal{A} \to [A^{\text{op}},\text{Set}]\) defined on objects $A \in \mathcal{A}$ as $H_ {-}(A)=H_ {A}$ and arrows $H_ {-}(f)=H_ {f}$.</p> <p>Note that in $[\mathcal{A}^{\text{op}},\text{Set}]$, the objects are functors from $\mathcal{A}^{\text{op}}$ to $\text{Set}$ and the arrows are natural transformations.</p> <p>For each object $A\in\mathcal{A}$, the Yoneda embedding assigns a functor $H_ {A}$, it is sometimes called the Yoneda functor. In a sense, the Yoneda embedding allows as to regard each $A$ as arrows. Or, more precisely, it allows us to represent each $A$ as a set-valued functor. Yoneda embedding is a one-to-one correspondence between objects in $\mathcal{A}$ and functors in $[\mathcal{A},\text{Set}]$. In a sense to be explained, $H_ {-}$ embeds $\mathcal{A}$ into $[\mathcal{A},\text{Set}]$.</p> <hr/> <p>Let $\mathcal{A}$ be a locally small category, the functor \(\text{Hom}_ {\mathcal{A}}: \mathcal{A}^{\text{op}}\times \mathcal{A}\to\text{Set}\) is defined by the following diagram, <img src="/img/hom.png" alt="hom"/></p> <p>This is like a generalization of $\text{Hom}(A,B)$ that we have encountered before. Recall that $\text{Hom}(A,B)$ is the set of the morphisms from $A$ to $B$, now $\text{Hom}_ {\mathcal{A}}$ is generalized such that it can also take two maps $f,g$ as well.</p> <hr/> <p>Given an arbitrary object in an arbitrary category, it is in general meaningless to talk about the “element” of this object since it not necessarily a set. However, in the category of sets, an element is the same thing as a map $1\to A$. This inspires the following definition.</p> <p>Let $A$ be a locally small category. A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Generalized element</code> of $A$ is a map with codomain $A$. A map $S\to A$ is a generalized element of $A$ of shape $S$.</p> <p>For example, a generalized element of a set $S$ of shape $\mathbb{N}$ is nothing but a sequence in $S$. In the category of topological spaces, the generalized elements of shape $1$ (the one point space) are points, and the generalized elements of shape $\mathbb{S}^{1}$ are loops.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Representables]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Best Way to Write Math Notes</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/The-Best-Way-to-Write-Math-Notes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Best Way to Write Math Notes"/><published>2023-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/The-Best-Way-to-Write-Math-Notes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/The-Best-Way-to-Write-Math-Notes/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="latex">Latex</h3> <p>Needless to say that LaTeX is the best language so far to write mathematical formula. A user-friendly introduction can be found online called <a href="https://www.dickimaw-books.com/latex/novices/">LaTeX for Complete Novices</a>, which can be read for free. After having gained a pretty good general idea of how to use Latex, other online resource might come in handy in everyday life working with LaTeX, I used to use the famous <em>Latex Companion</em> as a dictionary, but nowadays I found GPT4 to be most helpful.</p> <p>Also I like to edit Latex file on some local editor, such as WinEDT. The best online editor is <a href="https://www.overleaf.com/project">Overleaf</a>.</p> <h3 id="obsidian--markdown">Obsidian + Markdown</h3> <p>Obsidian can be installed online. Make sure you have installed the <strong>Latexsuit</strong> plugin. There you can define your own snippet.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Latex]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Renormalization method in PDF</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Renormalization-method-in-PDF/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Renormalization method in PDF"/><published>2023-12-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Renormalization-method-in-PDF</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Renormalization-method-in-PDF/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3> <p>The application of renormalization group method in solving the differential equation in the momentum space, and the error estimation of the solution with finite sized lattice size.</p> <h3 id="introduction">Introduction</h3> <p>The question we want to answer here is very simple: If we solve the PDF in the momentum space with a given cutoff $\Lambda$, how does the solution change with respect to $\Lambda$?</p> <h3 id="first-order-homogeneous-linear-differential-equation">First Order Homogeneous Linear Differential Equation</h3> <p>We want a well behaved function $\mathbb{R} \to \mathbb{R}$ so we begin with Gaussian function $g(t) = e^{-\lambda t^2}$. The equation it solves is \(\dot{g}(t) + 2 \lambda t g(t) = 0, \tag{1}\) which is a homogeneous first order ODE.</p> <p>Imagine that the function is defined on a grid with lattice spacing $a$, then the equation takes the discrete form</p> \[\frac{g(t_ {i+1})-g(t_ i)}{a} + 2 \lambda t g(t_ i) = 0,\quad \forall i \in \text{ lattice},\] <p>the solution will naturally depend on the lattice size, in the $a\to 0$ limit we will recover the continuous solution. We want to know what explicitly the dependence on $a$ looks like, and how to perform the error estimate with small but finite $a$.</p> <p>As the first attempt, in our simplified example, we go to the frequency space by substitute</p> \[g(t) = \frac{1}{\sqrt{2\pi}}\int_ {-\infty}^{\infty} d\omega \tilde{g}(\omega) e^{-i\omega t}.\] <p>The Fourier transformed equation reads</p> \[\int_ {-\infty}^{\infty} \frac{d\omega}{\sqrt{2\pi}} e^{-i\omega t} \left\{ -i \omega \tilde{g}(\omega) - 2i\lambda \frac{d}{d\omega} \tilde{g}(\omega) \right\}.\] <p>A lower bound in the lattice size $a$ corresponds to an upper bound $\Lambda$ in the momentum (exchangeable with frequency in our discussion) space, $a \sim 1/\Lambda$, thus we have \(\begin{align} &amp;\int_ {-\Lambda}^{\Lambda} \frac{d\omega}{\sqrt{2\pi}} e^{-i\omega t} \left\{ -i \omega \tilde{g}(\omega) - 2i\lambda \frac{d}{d\omega} \tilde{g}(\omega) \right\} = 0, \\ \implies &amp; \omega \tilde{g}(\omega) + 2\lambda \frac{d}{d\omega} \tilde{g}(\omega) = 0\, \forall \, |\omega| &lt; \Lambda, \quad 0 \text{ otherwise} \end{align}\) The equation for $\tilde{g}(\omega)$ takes the same form (up to some multiplicative constants) as that for $g(t)$, reflecting the fact that the Fourier transformed Gaussian function takes the same form as the original function.</p> <p>Here comes the key point: what happens if we decrease the momentum cutoff by infinitesimal, $\Lambda \to b\Lambda$, $b = 1-\epsilon$. With new cutoff $b\Lambda$ the equation above still holds trivially, since different modes are entirely independent of each other, we get</p> \[\omega \tilde{g}(\omega) + 2\lambda \frac{d}{d\omega} \tilde{g}(\omega) = 0\, \forall \, |\omega| &lt; (1-\epsilon)\Lambda, \quad 0 \text{ otherwise}.\] <p>In other words, for the modes that survive the renormalization flow, we have the trivial RG equation</p> \[\frac{d}{d\Lambda}\tilde{g}(\omega) = 0, \quad |\omega| &lt; b\Lambda.\] <p>Switch back to the physics space from frequency space, the error estimate is most easily done by subtracting $g^{(\Lambda)}(t)$ from $g^{(\infty)}(t)$, where</p> <p>\(g^{(\Lambda)}(t) \equiv \frac{1}{\sqrt{2\pi}}\int_ {-\Lambda}^{\Lambda} d\omega \tilde{g}(\omega) e^{-i\omega t}\) where the Fourier transform of Gaussian function is</p> \[\mathcal{F}\left\{e^{-\lambda x^2}\right\}(\omega) = \frac{1}{\sqrt{2 \lambda }}e^{-\frac{\omega ^2}{4 \lambda }}\] <p>Define \(\boxed{\Delta g^{(\infty - \Lambda)}(t) \equiv g^{(\infty)}(t) - g^{(\Lambda)}(t)},\) we have \(\begin{align} \notag \Delta g(t) &amp;= \left( \int_ {-\infty}^{-\Lambda} + \int_ {\Lambda}^\infty \right) \left( \frac{d\omega}{\sqrt{2\pi}} \frac{1}{\sqrt{2\lambda}} e^{-\omega^2/4\lambda} e^{-i\omega t} \right) \\\notag &amp;=\frac{1}{\sqrt{\pi\lambda}} \int_ {\Lambda}^\infty d\omega e^{-\omega^2/4\lambda} \cos{\omega t} \\\notag &amp;= \frac{i}{2} e^{-\lambda t^2} \left(-2 i +\text{erfi}\left(\frac{-2 \lambda t+i \Lambda }{2 \sqrt{\lambda }}\right)+\text{erfi}\left(\frac{2 \lambda t+i \Lambda }{2 \sqrt{\lambda }}\right)\right)\\ &amp;= e^{-\lambda t^2} - e^{-\lambda t^2}\text{Re}\,\text{erf}\left( \frac{\Lambda + 2i\lambda t}{2\sqrt{\lambda}} \right) \end{align}\)</p> <p>where we have simplified notations, Re erf is the real part of the error function, and $\text{erfi}(z)$ is the so-called imaginary error function defined by $\text{erfi}(z) = -i \,\text{erf}(iz)$. For more properties of error function, see App.~\ref{sec:error}.</p> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>Well, the last expression is not super helpful, we can do better by looking at $</td> <td>\Delta g^2</td> <td>$ as an estimate of the overall error. Square the second line in the previous equation we get</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> \[\begin{align} \notag \Delta g(t)^2 &amp;=\frac{1}{4\pi\lambda} \int_ {|\omega_ 1|&gt;\Lambda} d\omega_ 1 \int_ {|\omega_ 2|&gt;\Lambda} d\omega_ 2 \, e^{-\omega_ 1^2/4\lambda - \omega_ 1^2/4\lambda} \cos(\omega_ 1 t) \cos(\omega_ 2 t) \\\notag &amp;=\frac{1}{4\pi\lambda} \int_ {|\omega_ {1,2}|&gt;\Lambda} d^2\omega e^{-\omega^2/4\lambda} \cos(\omega_ 1 t) \cos(\omega_ 2 t) \\ &amp; &lt; \frac{1}{4\pi\lambda} \int_ {|\omega_ {1,2}|&gt;\Lambda} d^2\omega e^{-\omega^2/4\lambda} \end{align}\] <p>where $\omega^2 = \omega_ 1^2 + \omega_ 2^2$. The integral region is shown in the Figure below, the four corners where $\omega_ {1,2}&gt;\Lambda$ corresponds to the integral region. We can extend the region first to $(\mathbb{R}^2 - \text{square})$, then to $(\mathbb{R}^2 - \text{disk})$, each step will increase the error, thus we will get an upper bound. The reason for changing the square to circle is that so we can use the rotation symmetry. Continue with the integral,</p> <p>\(\begin{align} \notag |\Delta g(t)|^2 &amp;&lt; \frac{1}{4\pi\lambda}\int_ {\omega^2&gt;\Lambda^2} d^2\omega e^{-\omega^2/4\lambda}\\\notag &amp;= \frac{1}{4\pi\lambda} \int_ {\omega^2&gt;\Lambda^2} d^2\omega e^{-\omega^2/4\lambda} \\\notag &amp;= \frac{1}{4\pi\lambda}2\pi \int_ {\Lambda}^\infty \int d\omega \, \omega e^{-\omega^2/4\lambda} \end{align}\) where we have used $d^2 \omega = d\omega \omega d\theta$, \(\begin{align} |\Delta g(t)|^2 &amp;&lt; \frac{1}{4\lambda} \int_ {\Lambda}^\infty \int d\omega^2 \, \omega e^{-\omega^2/4\lambda} \\ &amp;= e^{-\Lambda^2/4\lambda}. \end{align}\)</p> <p>The conclusion is that at each $t$, the error $[g^{(\infty)}-g^{(\infty)}]^2 &lt; e^{-\Lambda^2/4\lambda}$.</p> <p><img src="/img/region.png" alt="region"/></p> <p>Out of a more differential point of view, let us consider the change of the function as we vary the cutoff $\Lambda$. We can calculate $\boxed{\frac{d}{d\Lambda} g^{(\Lambda)}(t)}$. Note that sometimes we will neglect the independent variable $t$ to save some space.</p> <p>If we increase $\Lambda$ infinitesimally, we have \(\begin{align} \notag g^{(\Lambda+\epsilon)}(t) &amp; = g^{(\Lambda)} + \frac{1}{\sqrt{\pi\lambda}} \int_ \Lambda^{\Lambda+\epsilon} d\omega e^{-\omega^2/4\lambda} \cos(\omega t)\\ &amp;= g^{(\Lambda)} + \frac{\epsilon}{\sqrt{\pi\lambda}} e^{-\Lambda^2/4\lambda} \cos(\Lambda t), \end{align}\) Thus \(\boxed{ \frac{d}{d\Lambda} g^{(\Lambda)}(t) = \frac{e^{-\Lambda^2 / 4\lambda}}{\sqrt{\pi\lambda}} \cos(\Lambda t) = \text{Re}\,\frac{e^{-\Lambda^2 / 4\lambda}}{\sqrt{\pi\lambda}} e^{i\Lambda t} = \text{Re}\,\frac{e^{-\lambda t^2}}{\sqrt{\pi\lambda}} e^{-\frac{1}{4\lambda} (\Lambda-i2\lambda t)^2}. }\) It can be solved to give, \(g^{(\Lambda)}(t) = C_ 1 - e^{-\lambda t^2} \text{Re} \, \text{erf}\left(i\sqrt{\lambda} t - \frac{\Lambda}{2\sqrt{\lambda}}\right),\) where $C_ 1$ is the constant of integration. To eliminate $C_ 1$, recall that $f^{\infty}(t) = e^{-\lambda t^2}$, thus we have $C_ 1 = 0$. By the end of the day we have \(\boxed{ g^{(\Lambda)}(t) = - e^{-\lambda t^2} \text{Re} \, \text{erf}\left(i\sqrt{\lambda} t - \frac{\Lambda}{2\sqrt{\lambda}}\right) },\) which agrees with the previous equations. The value of $\Delta g(t)$ can also be estimated with the help of Hans Heinrich Burmann’s theorem, \(\text{erf}{x} = \frac{2}{\sqrt{\pi}}\text{sgn}\cdot \sqrt{1-e^{-x^2}} \left( \frac{\sqrt{\pi}}{2}+ \sum_ {k\in \mathbb{Z}^+} c_ k e^{-k x^2} \right), \, c_ 1 = \frac{31}{200},\, c_ 2 = -\frac{341}{8000},\, \cdots.\)</p> <p>In summary, We have obtained the lattice spacing dependence, or equivalently the momentum cutoff dependence, both the error estimate and the RG flow are discussed.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="in-homogeneous-linear-differential-equation">In-homogeneous Linear Differential Equation</h3> <hr/> <h3 id="kink-equation">kink Equation</h3> <hr/> <h3 id="conventions">Conventions</h3> <p>The conventions are chose so be the same as that used by Mathematica.</p> <p>Given a function $f(t):\mathbb{R} \to \mathbb{R}$, the Fourier transform in the symmetrical form is</p> <p>\(\begin{align} \tilde{f} (\omega) &amp;= \frac{1}{\sqrt{2\pi}}\int_ {-\infty}^\infty f(t) e^{i\omega t} dt, \\ f(t) &amp;= \frac{1}{\sqrt{2\pi}}\int_ {-\infty}^\infty \tilde{f}(\omega) e^{-i\omega t} dt \end{align}\) where $\tilde{f}(\omega) \equiv \mathcal{F}\left{ f \right}(\omega)$. Note the factor of $\frac{1}{\sqrt{2\pi}}$ and the signs in the exponent.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="error-function-in-the-complex-plane">Error function in the complex plane</h3> <p>The error function in the complex plane is defined to be \be \(\operatorname* {erf}{z} = \frac{2}{\sqrt{\pi}} \int_ {\Gamma} d\zeta \, e^{-\zeta^2}\) where $\Gamma$ is any path going from $0$ to $z$. The real and imaginary part of an error function can be estimated by Abramowitz and Stegun.</p> <p>The error function $\text{erf}(z),\, z \in \mathbb{C}$ satisfy symmetry relations \(\begin{align} \text{erf}(z) &amp;= - \text{erf}(-z), \\ \text{erf}(\overline{z}) &amp;= \overline{\text{erf}(z)}. \end{align}\)</p> <p>A possibly useful series expression for numerical calculation is \(\begin{multline} \operatorname* {erf}(x+i y) = \operatorname* {erf}{x} + \frac{e^{-x^2}}{2 \pi x} [(1-\cos{2 x y})+i \sin{2 x y}]\\ + \frac{2}{\pi} e^{-x^2} \sum_ {k=1}^{\infty} \frac{e^{-k^2/4}}{k^2+4 x^2}[f_ k(x,y)+i g_ k(x,y)] + \epsilon(x,y) \end{multline}\) where \(\begin{align*} f_ k(x,y) &amp;= 2 x [1-\cos(2 x y) \cosh(k y)] + k\sin(2 x y) \sinh(k y), \\ g_ k(x,y) &amp;= 2 x \sin(2 x y) \cosh(k y) + k\cos(2 x y) \sinh(k y). \end{align*}\)</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="Math"/><category term="Renormalization"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Abstract]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Note on The Moral Foundations of Politics</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Note-on-The-Moral-Foundations-of-Politics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Note on The Moral Foundations of Politics"/><published>2023-12-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Note-on-The-Moral-Foundations-of-Politics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Note-on-The-Moral-Foundations-of-Politics/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="enlightenment-politics">Enlightenment Politics</h1> <blockquote> <p>f there is a single overarching idea shared in common by adherents to different strands of Enlightenment thinking, it is faith in the power of human reason to understand the true nature of our circumstances and ourselves. Human improvement is measured by the yardstick of <strong>individual rights</strong> that embody, and protect, <strong>human freedom</strong>.</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p>Descartes announced that he was in search of propositions that are impossible to doubt. His famous example, known as the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cogito</code>, was ‘‘I think, therefore I am.’’</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p>Immanuel Kant defined in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">The Critique of Pure Reason</code> (1781), of placing knowledge ‘‘on the secure path of a science.’’</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p>These developments in philosophy reflected and reinforced the emergence of modern scientific consciousness.</p> </blockquote> <p>Such ideas, as necessary conditions for the development of natural science (not merely technology), seems to never had appeared in China. Year 1781 is the year 乾隆四十六年 in China, one of the most closed, ignorant, and autocratic era in history.</p> <blockquote> <p>During the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries, when the hallmark of scientific knowledge was indubitable certainty, ethics, political philosophy, and the human sciences were regarded as superior to the natural sciences. This view seems strange from the vantage point of the twenty-first century, when fields like physics, chemistry, astronomy, geology, and biology have all advanced with astonishing speed to discoveries that would have been unimaginable in the eighteenth century.</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="the-workmanship-ideal-of-knowledge">The Workmanship Ideal of Knowledge</h2> <blockquote> <p>The first distinctive feature of the early Enlightenment concerns the range of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">a priori knowledge</code>, the kind of knowledge that either follows from definitions or is otherwise deduced from covering principals. This is the kind of knowledge Descartes had in mind when he formulated his cogito and that Kant located in the realm of ‘‘analytic judgments.’</p> </blockquote> <p><strong>Epistemology</strong> is a branch of philosophy that studies the nature, origin, and limits of human knowledge. The term comes from the Greek words “episteme,” meaning knowledge or understanding, and “logos,” meaning study or discourse. Epistemology addresses questions such as:</p> <ul> <li>What is knowledge?</li> <li>How is knowledge acquired?</li> <li>What do people know?</li> <li>How do we know what we know?</li> <li>What are the limits of human knowledge?</li> <li>What makes beliefs justified or rational?</li> </ul> <p>In exploring these questions, epistemology deals with the definition of knowledge and its scope and limits. It often involves debating between different theories of knowledge, such as empiricism (the idea that knowledge comes primarily from sensory experience), rationalism (the idea that reason is the main source of knowledge), and constructivism (the idea that knowledge is constructed by individuals through their interactions with the world).</p> <p>Immanuel Kant distinguished between two types of judgments: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">analytic</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">synthetic</code>. These distinctions are central to his philosophy, especially in his work “Critique of Pure Reason.”</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Analytic Judgments</strong>: An analytic judgment is one where the predicate (the part of the sentence that says something about the subject) is contained within the subject itself. The truth of an analytic judgment is derived from the meanings of the words involved and logical reasoning. They are tautological in nature and do not add any new information about the world. For example, the statement “All bachelors are unmarried” is analytic because the predicate “unmarried” is part of the definition of the subject “bachelor.”</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Synthetic Judgments</strong>: A synthetic judgment, on the other hand, is one where the predicate adds something to the subject that is not contained within it. The truth of a synthetic judgment is determined through how our concepts relate to the world and cannot be known just by understanding the meanings of the words. They require empirical investigation or intuition. For instance, “The cat is on the mat” is a synthetic judgment because the concept of “the cat” does not inherently include the concept of “being on the mat.”</p> </li> </ol> <p>Kant’s distinction between analytic and synthetic judgments is fundamental to his epistemology, particularly in addressing the question of how human beings can have knowledge about the world. He further introduced the concept of “synthetic a priori” judgments, which are synthetic judgments that are known independently of experience (a priori), like mathematical truths.</p> <hr/> <p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">creationist</code> or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">workmanship</code> theory in political science, often associated with the work of John Locke, is a theory of political obligation. It suggests that political authority and legitimacy derive from the consent of the governed, likening the role of the government or ruler to that of a craftsman or creator who constructs a system with the consent and for the benefit of the people.</p> <p>This theory is rooted in the idea that political and social structures are artificial constructs, made by human beings, unlike natural phenomena. The “creationist” aspect implies that political structures are deliberately created or constructed, rather than organically evolved. The “workmanship” aspect emphasizes the idea that the creators or rulers of these structures have a responsibility to the people they govern, similar to how a craftsman is responsible for the quality and function of their creation.</p> <p>Locke’s theory was revolutionary at its time because it challenged the prevailing notion of the divine right of kings, suggesting instead that political authority is justified only when it serves the interests of the governed and respects their rights. This theory laid the groundwork for modern concepts of democracy, individual rights, and the social contract.</p> <hr/> <p>Thomas Hobbes and John Locke, two prominent philosophers, had distinct views on natural law, reflecting their differing perspectives on human nature and the ideal structure of society.</p> <p>Hobbes, in his work “Leviathan,” presented a rather pessimistic view of human nature. He believed that in the state of nature (a hypothetical condition without government or laws), humans are driven by self-interest and a desire for self-preservation, leading to a “war of all against all” (bellum omnium contra omnes). In this state, life would be “solitary, poor, nasty, brutish, and short.”</p> <p>For Hobbes, natural law is a set of precepts or general rules, <em>discovered by reason</em>, which prohibit anything destructive to one’s own life. <em>It’s based on the right of every individual to preserve their own life</em>, leading to the conclusion that humans should seek peace. This is where his famous concept of the social contract comes into play: individuals surrender some of their freedoms and submit to the authority of a ruler (or a ruling assembly) to ensure their own safety and peace. Thus, Hobbes’s natural law is fundamentally about self-preservation and the avoidance of harm to others as a means of securing one’s own safety.</p> <p>Locke’s view, as articulated in “Two Treatises of Government,” is more optimistic about human nature. He believed that in the state of nature, humans live in a state of equality and freedom, not inherently prone to violence or war. For Locke, the <em>law of nature is a moral guide based on the belief that God has given the world to all people in common</em>. It teaches that, since all are equal and independent, no one ought to harm another in their life, health, liberty, or possessions.</p> <p>Locke’s natural law is grounded in the rights to life, liberty, and property. It includes the idea that people have the obligation to respect the rights of others. His social contract theory suggests that people form governments to protect these natural rights. If a government fails to do so, citizens have the right to overthrow it. This view laid the groundwork for modern democracy and significantly influenced the development of political philosophy in the Western world.</p> <p>So, Hobbes saw natural law as a means of avoiding the brutal state of nature through self-preservation and peace, whereas Locke viewed natural law as a moral guide ensuring equality and the inherent rights of life, liberty, and property.</p> <hr/> <blockquote> <p>A basic issue for Locke and many of his contemporaries was the ontological status of natural law and in particular its relation to God’s will.</p> </blockquote> <p>In this sentence, “ontological status” refers to the fundamental nature or essence of natural law, especially in relation to its existence and its relationship to God’s will. Ontology, in philosophy, is the study of being or existence, and it deals with questions concerning what entities exist or can be said to exist, and how such entities can be grouped, related within a hierarchy, and subdivided according to similarities and differences.</p> <p>So, when discussing the “ontological status of natural law” in the context of John Locke and his contemporaries, the focus is on understanding the very essence of natural law: whether it exists as an objective reality independent of human beings, how it relates to or derives from God’s will, and what its fundamental characteristics are. This was a central topic in the philosophical and theological debates of that era, particularly in the context of determining the basis and legitimacy of moral and legal principles. Locke and many others were engaged in trying to understand whether natural laws were inherent aspects of the universe, ordained by God, or whether they were constructs of human reason and society.</p> <p>“Will-centered” refers to the philosophical position known as voluntarism. This is a theory that emphasizes the role of the will, either divine or human, in various philosophical contexts. In the context of Locke’s moral and political writings, being “will-centered” or a voluntarist means that Locke ultimately leaned towards the view that natural law and moral principles are determined by the will, particularly the will of God, rather than being inherent or objective truths that exist independently of any will.</p> <p>In Locke’s time, the debate about the nature of natural law often centered around whether natural laws were intrinsic to the universe (a position known as intellectualism or rationalism) or whether they were decrees of God’s will (voluntarism). A will-centered or voluntarist approach suggests that moral and legal norms derive their authority from an act of will, particularly the divine will, rather than from reason alone or from the inherent nature of reality. In this view, what is right or wrong, just or unjust, is so because God wills it to be that way, and human beings understand and follow these laws through revelation, religious teachings, or other means of discerning God’s will.</p> <blockquote> <p>Locke distinguished “ectype”’ from “archetype” ideas: ectypes are general ideas of substances, and archetypes are ideas constructed by man.</p> </blockquote> <p>John Locke’s distinction between “ectype” and “archetype” ideas is a crucial aspect of his epistemological theory, which he discusses in his work “An Essay Concerning Human Understanding.” This distinction is part of his broader inquiry into the nature of human knowledge and understanding.</p> <p>In Locke’s philosophy, archetypes are the original models or patterns from which copies are made. They are the fundamental, primary ideas that exist in the mind of God or, in a more secular interpretation, the perfect, abstract forms of things. When Locke refers to archetypes as ideas constructed by man, he means that these are the ideal standards or criteria we hold in our minds for categorizing and understanding the world. They represent our understanding of what the essential characteristics of a particular thing are.</p> <p>For instance, the archetype of a tree would be the idealized concept or mental representation of what a tree is supposed to be. This archetype is not derived from any particular tree but is a kind of composite or abstracted idea of “treeness” that we use to recognize and categorize individual trees.</p> <p>Ectypes, on the other hand, are derivative or secondary ideas. They are the imperfect copies or generalizations that we derive from our experience with individual instances in the world. Ectype ideas are more about the general ideas of substances we form based on our sensory experiences and observations. When we see many individual trees, for example, we form a general idea of what a tree is - this is an ectype. It’s a more practical, experiential idea based on the aggregation of real-world instances.</p> <p>In summary, Locke’s distinction between archetype and ectype ideas can be understood as a differentiation between the idealized, abstract concepts we hold in our minds as standards (archetypes) and the more practical, general ideas we form based on our sensory experience of the world (ectypes). Archetypes are about the essence or ideal form of things, while ectypes are about the general, often imperfect, concepts we derive from actual experiences.</p> <h2 id="the-preoccupation-with-certainty">The Preoccupation with Certainty</h2> <blockquote> <p>The post-Humean Enlightenment tradition has been marked by a fallibilist view of knowledge. All knowledge claims are fallible on this account, and science advances not by making knowledge more certain but by producing more knowledge. Recognizing the corrigibility of all knowledge claims and the possibility that one might always be wrong exemplifies the modern scientific attitude. As Karl Popper (1902-1994) noted, the most that we can say, when hypotheses survive empirical tests, is that they have not been falsified so that we can accept them provisionally.</p> </blockquote> <p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Value judgments</code> are statements or opinions that express an evaluation, typically of something’s worth, beauty, goodness, or morality. Examples include statements like “Lying is wrong,” or “This painting is beautiful.” A.J. Ayer was a key figure in the logical positivist movement, which held that for a statement to be meaningful, it must be either empirically verifiable (i.e., testable by observation or experiment) or analytically true (true by definition, like mathematical or logical statements). In logical positivism, a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">proposition</code> is a statement that can be either true or false. It’s a claim about the world that can, <em>at least in principle</em>, be tested and verified or falsified.</p> <p>The Logical Positivist movement, also known as Logical Empiricism, was a philosophical movement that emerged in the early 20th century. It primarily revolved around a group of philosophers associated with the Vienna Circle (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Moritz Schlick</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Hans Hahn</code>, ), along with others like A.J. Ayer in Britain. This movement sought to apply the rigor of scientific methodology to philosophy, with a significant focus on the analysis of language and the verification of statements.</p> <p>Key Features of Logical Positivism include</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Verification Principle</strong>: The central tenet of Logical Positivism is the verification principle. This principle asserts that a statement is only meaningful if it can be empirically verified or is analytically true (true by virtue of its meaning, like “All bachelors are unmarried”). The idea was to eliminate metaphysical and abstract discussions that couldn’t be supported by empirical evidence or logical reasoning.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Empiricism and Science</strong>: Logical Positivists emphasized the importance of empirical evidence and scientific methods in acquiring knowledge. They viewed science as the model for all true knowledge.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Rejection of Metaphysics</strong>: They were critical of metaphysics and other traditional philosophical endeavors, which they saw as meaningless since such statements couldn’t be empirically verified. They believed that many philosophical problems arose from misunderstandings of language and could be resolved by clarifying the language used.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Language and Meaning</strong>: A significant focus was placed on the analysis of language, particularly the language of science. They aimed to clarify how language is used in scientific theories and to distinguish between meaningful and meaningless statements.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Influence of Wittgenstein</strong>: Although not officially part of the Vienna Circle, Ludwig Wittgenstein’s early work, especially his “Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus,” significantly influenced Logical Positivism. Wittgenstein argued that <em>much of philosophy consists of nonsensical propositions and that the role of philosophy should be to clarify thought and language</em>.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Ethical and Aesthetic Statements</strong>: Logical Positivists generally considered ethical and aesthetic statements to be expressions of emotions or subjective preferences, rather than statements that could be true or false.</p> </li> </ol> <p>The “positivism” component is linked to the movement’s commitment to a scientific and empirical approach to knowledge. Positivism, as a philosophical stance, argues that knowledge should be based on positive, observable facts and their logical and mathematical treatment. It rejects introspection and intuition as sources of knowledge and instead emphasizes empirical evidence obtained through observation and experimentation. Logical Positivists extended this approach by asserting that statements must be empirically verifiable (or analytically true) to be meaningful.</p> <hr/> <p>Somewhat to my surprise, Karl Popper is not a member of the Vienna circle even though they shared many intellectual engagements. Furthermore, Karl Popper is even critically oppositional. The Vienna Circle advocated for the verification principle, which held that a statement is meaningful only if it can be empirically <em>verified</em>. Popper challenged this view, proposing <em>falsificationism</em> instead. According to Popper, scientific theories cannot be conclusively verified but can be falsified. He argued that a theory is scientific if it is testable and can potentially be refuted by evidence. This approach places a greater emphasis on the role of empirical refutation rather than verification.</p> <p>Also, Popper was critical of what he called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">historicism</code> – the belief that <em>history unfolds according to deterministic laws or principles</em>. He argued that such theories, which <em>were often used to justify authoritarian regimes</em>, are fundamentally flawed. He believed that historicism led to totalitarianism because it promoted the idea that certain individuals or groups had access to inevitable truths about societal development, thus justifying their absolute rule. Popper advocated for what he termed an <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">open society</code>. An open society, in his view, is characterized by a democratic government, individual freedoms, and a critical attitude towards tradition and authority. It allows for change and improvement through rational and critical discourse, as opposed to the unquestioning acceptance of dogmatic principles.</p> <p>Just as Popper applied the <em>principle of falsifiability</em> to scientific theories, he suggested that political policies should also be subjected to critical scrutiny and should be alterable in the face of new evidence or arguments. He was wary of any political theory or system that claimed to have absolute or final answers.</p> <hr/> <p>According to Ayer, the expression of a value judgment is not a proposition since it can not be judged by right and wrong, the question of truth or falsehood does not here arise.</p> <p>Regarding ethics, Ayer points out that many theorists in ethics tend to treat statements about the causes and characteristics of our ethical feelings as if these statements were definitions of ethical concepts. For example, a theory might claim that an action is good if it promotes happiness. Here, the cause of the ethical feeling (happiness) is used to define the ethical concept (good). Ayer argues that ethical concepts are <em>pseudo-concepts</em>, since ethical concepts, in his view, is neither empirically verifiable or analytically correct.</p> <p>Ayer’s stance is closely associated with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">emotivism</code>, a meta-ethical view that suggests <em>ethical statements do not assert propositions but express emotional attitudes</em>. According to emotivism, saying “Stealing is wrong” is akin to expressing one’s disapproval of stealing, rather than making an objective claim about the nature of stealing.</p> <h2 id="the-centrality-of-individual-rights">The Centrality of Individual Rights</h2> <blockquote> <p>In addition to faith in science, the Enlightenment’s central focus on individual rights differentiates its political philosophy from the ancient and medieval commitments to order and hierarchy. This focus brings the freedom of the individual to the center of arguments about politics. This move was signaled in the natural law tradition by a shift in emphasis from the logic of law to the idea of natural right.</p> </blockquote> <p>Hobbes contended that it was customary to conflate “Jus and Lex, law and right”. Yet he made the distinction that right, consisted in liberty to do, or to forbeare, whereas law, determines and binds to one of them. Similarly by Locke.</p> <p>John Locke’s oppinion on natural law is as the following. In his work <em>Essays on the Law of Nature</em>, Locke argues a moral law inherent in the world and discoverable through reason.</p> <p>Key points of Locke’s argument include:</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Natural Law and Reason:</strong> Locke posits that natural law is an aspect of the natural world, similar to physical laws. According to him, this <em>moral law can be discovered through the use of reason, without the need for divine revelation</em>.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Moral Obligations:</strong> He argues that <em>natural law imposes moral obligations on individuals</em>. These moral principles are universal and apply to all people, regardless of their culture or society.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Rights and Duties:</strong> Locke’s view of natural law is closely tied to his ideas about individual rights and duties. He believes that natural law forms the basis for understanding human rights, especially the right to life, liberty, and property.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Foundation for Political Theory:</strong> These essays lay the groundwork for Locke’s later political theories, particularly those presented in his famous works, “Two Treatises of Government.” He uses the concept of natural law to argue for the rights of individuals and the limitations of governmental power.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Human Equality:</strong> Locke emphasizes the inherent equality of all human beings, derived from their natural state. This idea is a critical aspect of his argument against absolute monarchy and for the formation of governments based on the consent of the governed.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Religious Tolerance:</strong> Although not as explicitly developed in these essays as in his later works, Locke’s concept of natural law also leads to his advocacy for religious tolerance, seeing religious belief as a matter of individual conscience.</p> </li> </ol> <p>In summary, Locke’s “Essays on the Law of Nature” propose that there is a moral law inherent in the natural world, understandable through human reason, and that this law underpins human rights and forms the basis for just and ethical governance.</p> <hr/> <p>John Locke’s <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">voluntarist theology</code> reflects his views on the nature of God and the relationship between divine will and moral law. The emphasis is on <em>the will will (voluntas in Latin, hence the name) of God of God as the primary or sole source of moral law</em>. Locke’s voluntarism posits that <em>moral laws are decrees of God’s will</em>. In this view, what is morally right or wrong is so because God wills it, and not necessarily because it aligns with any intrinsic moral truths or rational principles independent of God’s will. Locke emphasizes the <em>absolute freedom</em> and <em>omnipotence</em> of God. He argues that God’s will is not bound by any external standards or principles. Therefore, moral laws are a product of God’s free choice.</p> <p>While Locke is a proponent of reason and believes that human beings can discover moral truths through rational inquiry, he also upholds the importance of divine revelation. In his voluntarist theology, revelation plays a crucial role in imparting knowledge of God’s will, which might not be entirely accessible through reason alone. Locke’s voluntarism is tied to his rejection of innate ideas, a concept he famously critiques in his “Essay Concerning Human Understanding.” He argues against the notion that <em>moral principles are innately known</em>, instead positing that our understanding of moral laws comes from experience, reason, and revelation. Locke’s voluntarist approach suggests that moral obligations are ultimately grounded in obedience to God’s will. This perspective can lead to a form of ethical subjectivism, where moral truths depend on the decrees of a divine authority.</p> <hr/> <blockquote> <p>In Locke’s formulation, natural law dictates that man is subject to divine imperatives to live in certain ways, but, within the limits set by the law of nature, men can act in a godlike fashion. Man as maker has a maker’s knowledge of his intentional actions, and a natural right to dominion over man’s products. … Provided we do not violate natural law, we stand in the same relation to the objects we create as God stands to us; we own them just as he owns us.</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="tensions-between-science-and-individual-rights">Tensions Between Science and Individual Rights</h2> <p>The two enlightenment values, the preoccupation of science and the commitment to individual rights, seem to be in contradiction with each other. Science is deterministic, concerned with discovering the laws that govern the universe, with human being included. This has potential for conflict with an ethic that emphasizes individual freedom, for now the freedom has to be subjugated to the laws (of nature, of God).</p> <p>In Locke’s theory, the freedom to comprehend natural law by one’s own lights supplied the basis of Locke’s right to resist, which could be invoked against the sovereign. No one is in a higher position to monopolize the right to interpret the scripture.</p> <blockquote> <p>We will see this tension surface repeatedly in the utilitarian, Marxist, and social contract traditions, without ever being fully resolved.</p> </blockquote> <h1 id="classical-utilitarianism">Classical Utilitarianism</h1> <p>Jeremy Bentham famously wrote that</p> <blockquote> <p>Nature has placed mankind under the governance of two sovereign masters, <em>pain</em> and <em>pleasure</em>. It is for them alone to point out what we ought to do, as well as to determine what we shall do. On the one hand the standard of right and wrong, on the other the chain of causes and effects, are fastened to their throne. They govern us in all we do, in all we say, in all we think: every effort we can make to throw off our subjection, will serve but to demonstrate and confirm it. In words a man may pretend to abjure their empire: but in reality he will remain subject to it all the while. The principle of utility recognizes this subjection, and assumes it for the foundation of that system, the object of which is to rear the fabric of felicity by the hands of reason and law. Systems which attempt to question it, deal in sounds instead of senses, in caprice instead of reason, in darkness instead of light.</p> </blockquote> <p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">principle of utility</code>, as Bentham explains, ‘‘approves or disapproves of every action whatsoever, according to the tendency which it appears to have to augment or diminish the happiness of the party whose interest is in question: or, what is the same thing in other words, to promote or to oppose that happiness.’’</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Enlightenment Politics]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introduction to Higher Form Symmetry</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Higher-Form-Symmetry-Lecture-3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction to Higher Form Symmetry"/><published>2023-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Higher-Form-Symmetry%20Lecture%203</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Higher-Form-Symmetry-Lecture-3/"><![CDATA[<p>For conventions used in this note, see my other blog <a href="https://www.mathlimbo.net/blog/2022/Conventions-and-Formula/">here</a>.</p> <p>In lecture 2 we talked about classic symmetry and their re-interpretation in the language of differential (exterior) form. We have made the connection between the so-called symmetry defect operator (SDO) and a charged, point (0-dimensional) operator. In this note we try to generalized this concept to charged operators defined on manifolds of dimension more than zero, such as a line or a surface, etc.</p> <p>Let’s start with the ordinary symmetry once again on a $D$-dimensional manifold. We first upgraded the global symmetry parametrized by $\epsilon$ to a local symmetry parametrized by $\epsilon(x)$, and write the action variation as \(\delta S = \int d^{D}x \, J^{\mu}\partial_ {\mu}\epsilon(x) \tag{1}\) under $e^{ iQ_ {\Sigma} }$ the charged operators with non-trivial linking $\text{Link}(\Sigma,x)$ transform as \(\phi(x) \to \epsilon(x) \Delta \phi(x).\) In our convention, $\Delta$ stands for a small but finite change while $\epsilon(x)$ stands for an infinitesimal parameter. Eq. (1) can be regarded as the definition of the Noether current $J^{\mu}$, which tells us how much the action changed under the transformation in question. But, being a symmetry of the system, of course the action must remains unchanged under the transformation, thus we have the Noether current \(\partial_ {\mu}J^{\mu} = 0 \Longleftrightarrow d\star J=0.\)</p> <p>In terms of differential forms, function $\epsilon(x)$ is a $0$-form and constant function $\epsilon$ is a closed form. The variation of action reads \(\delta S = \int_ {M^{(D)}} (\star J)\wedge d\epsilon, \tag{2}\) where $\star J$ is a $(D-1)$-form, $d \epsilon$ is a $1$-form (since $\epsilon$ is a zero form), hence their wedge product is a $D$-form, something can be integrated over $D$-dimensional manifold $M$ (whose boundary is $\Sigma$).</p> <hr/> <p>The advantage of Eq. (2) is that it can be generalized to higher forms. Assume now the symmetry is parametrized by a $1$-form $\xi = \xi_ {\mu}dx^{\mu}$. Then $d \xi$ is a 2-form, as a result $\star J$ is a $(D-2)$-form thus $J$ is a $2$-form. The conservation law becomes \(d \star J = 0 \to \partial_ {\mu} J^{\mu \nu}=0.\) Since $(D-2)$-form can be integrated over a $(D-2)$ manifold, we can define the charge operator as \(Q(\Sigma_ {D-2}):= \int_ {\Sigma} \, \star J.\)</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="PureMath"/><category term="Notes"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For conventions used in this note, see my other blog here.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introduction to Resurgence and Transseries 4</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Resurgence-and-Transseries-Lecture-4/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction to Resurgence and Transseries 4"/><published>2023-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Resurgence-and-Transseries-Lecture-4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Resurgence-and-Transseries-Lecture-4/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="introduction">Introduction</h3> <p>This part follows from a lecture by Maxim Kontsevich.</p> <p>There are roughly speaking three perspectives of resurgence,</p> <ul> <li>Borel plane,</li> <li>Exponential integrals,</li> <li>Ray-crossing in the complex plane.</li> </ul> <p><strong>Simple resurgence package.</strong> Consists of</p> <ol> <li>A discrete subset of complex plane, $\left{ z_ {\alpha} \right}\in\mathbb{C}$, finite countable.</li> <li>Formal power series,</li> <li>A collection of integers $n_ {\alpha \beta}\in\mathbb{Z}$, called Stokes integers, usually anti-symmetric, $n_ {\alpha \beta}=-n_ {\beta \alpha}$.</li> </ol> <p>There is an axiom. Consider function $\phi_ {\alpha}(\zeta)$, \(\phi_ {\alpha}(\zeta) := \sum_ {k\geq 0} \frac{c_ {\alpha,k}}{k!} (\zeta-z_ {\alpha})^{k}.\) It is analytic germ at $z_ {\alpha}$, Meaning it converges at some small disk centered at $z_ {\alpha}$. This extends analytically to star-shaped domain \(\mathbb{C} - \bigcup_ {\alpha \neq \beta} (z_ {\beta} + \mathbb{R}_ {+}(z_ {\beta}-z_ {\alpha})).\) This is hard to explain it with words but I am too lazy to draw a picture and include it to my note. The best way to describe it is to regard $z_ {\alpha}$ as the sun, radiating heat and light, and consider $z_ {\beta}$ as planets, all lying on the complex plane, then the star-shaped manifold is the area where the light from $z_ {\alpha}$ reaches. And we want to describe how the functions jumps at the ray of shades.</p> <p>The jumps are controlled by the numbers $n_ {\alpha \beta}$, in the following fashion. The function of interested $\phi_ {\alpha}$ is not holomorphic at $z_ {\beta}$’s, but it can be separated into holomorphic and singular part, roughly as \(\phi_ {\alpha}(\zeta){\Large\mid}_ {z_ {\beta}} = \text{holomorphic part} + \frac{n_ {\alpha \beta}}{2\pi i} \log(\zeta-z_ {\beta})\times \text{something}.\)</p> <hr/> <p>A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">formal series</code> is an infinite formal sum that is considered independently from any notion of <em>convergence</em>, and can be manipulated with the usual algebraic operations on series, such as addition, multiplication, division, partial sum, etc.</p> <p>A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">formal power series</code> is a special case of formal series, whose terms are of form $ax^{n}$ where $n\in\mathbb{Z}^{+}$ is the power of the variable $x$. $a$ is the coefficient of that term. They can be viewed as a generalization of polynomials, where the number of terms is allowed to be finite, with no requirement of convergence. One of the biggest difference between <em>formal</em> power series and power series is that the operation <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">evaluation</code> is not defined for formal power series but is for regular power series, which can thus be identified as a function, at least within the radius of convergence. In formal power series, in a term such as $a x^{5}$, $x^{5}$ is merely a position holder, used to tell the position of $a$ is a tuple of coefficients.</p> <p>It is the fact that we don’t need to bother about convergence that made the ring of formal power series so useful in our discussion. Doing arithmetic is actually simpler with formal power series, since you can just pretend it is a power series without worrying about <em>absolute, conditional</em> and <em>uniform convergence</em>.</p> <p>In the previous notes we have introduced the (complex) formal power series of $z^{-1}$ without constant term, denoted \(z^{-1}\mathbb{C}[[ z^{-1} ]].\)</p> <p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">formal Borel transformation</code> is defined to be a linear map from $z^{-1}\mathbb{C}[[ z^{-1} ]]$ to $\mathbb{C}[[\zeta]]$ as \(\mathcal{B}: \tilde{\phi} = \sum_ {0}^{\infty} a_ {n} z^{-n-1} \mapsto \hat{\phi} = \sum_ {0}^{\infty } \frac{a_ {n}}{n!} \zeta^{n}\)</p> <p>The reason for this definition is that we hope the introduction of extra $1 / n!$ factor in the coefficients can turn the original formal power series into a convergent power series, which we can then identify to a function. The change of variable from $z^{-1}$ to $\zeta$ seems out of nowhere, like, where does this $\xi$ came from? One way to explain it, without mathematical rigor but quite intuitive, is to say that it comes from writing the power of $z$ to the integral form, \(x^{n+1} = \frac{1}{n!} \int_{0}^{\infty} d\xi \, \xi^{n} e^{ -\xi / x } , \quad x=\frac{1}{z},\) which is a generalized form of the Euler integral. Substitute it to $\tilde{\phi}$ and re-arrange the order of integral and summation (which is not allowed! But we do it anyway) we find the mysterious $\xi$.</p> <p>For the formal power series in $\mathbb{C}[[z^{-1}]]$ (note that we have put constant terms back in to make the case most general) which are actually convergent at infinity ($z\to \infty$) with positive radius of convergence, we denote the collection of them \(\mathbb{C}\left\{ z^{-1} \right\}\) and the ones without constant terms are again denoted \(z^{-1}\mathbb{C}\left\{ z^{-1} \right\} .\)</p> <p><strong>Lemma 1.</strong> Let \(\tilde{\phi}\in z^{-1}\mathbb{C}[[z^{-1}]],\) then \(\tilde{\phi}\in z^{-1}\mathbb{C}\left\{ z^{-1} \right\}\) iff its formal Borel transform \(\hat{\phi}=\mathcal{B}\tilde{\phi}\) has infinite radius of convergence and defines an entire function (functions that are finite except at infinite points) of bounded exponential type, i.e. there exists $A,c&gt;0$ such that \(\left\lvert \hat{\phi}(\zeta) \right\rvert \leq A e^{ c\left\lvert \zeta \right\rvert } \text{ for all } \zeta.\) <strong>Proof.</strong> Let \(\tilde{\phi}=\sum_ {n\geq 0}a_ {n}z^{-n-1}.\) It is convergent iff there exists $A,c&gt;0$ such that $\left\lvert a_ {n} \right\rvert\leq Ac^{n}$ for all $n\in\mathbb{N}$. If it is so, then \(a_ {n}\zeta^{n} / n! \leq \frac{A}{n!} \left\lvert c\zeta\right\rvert^{n}\) and the conclusion follows.</p> <p>The converse can be proofed with the help of Cauchy inequality, which we will not list here.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="PureMath"/><category term="CategoryTheory"/><category term="Notes"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Note on Quantum Kink Mass in 3D</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Note-on-Quantum-Kink-Mass-in-3D/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Note on Quantum Kink Mass in 3D"/><published>2023-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Note-on-Quantum-Kink-Mass-in-3D</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Note-on-Quantum-Kink-Mass-in-3D/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="background">Background</h3> <h3 id="the-symplectic-manifold">The symplectic manifold</h3> <p>The finite-dimensional covariant Hamiltonian approach to field theory is vigorously developed from the seventies in its multisymplectic and polysymplectic variants. The final purpose is to covariant Hamiltonian quantization of field theory. For classical field theory, the Hamiltonian formalism provides an alternative to the Lagrangian formalism for deriving the equations of motion. Furthermore, the Hamiltonian approach offers a geometrical interpretation of the field theory, in a sense combines geometry and algebra together. To fully appreciate it, we need to know what is a symplectic manifold first.</p> <p>A symplectic manifold is a type of smooth manifold equipped with a special kind of geometric structure known as a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">symplectic form</code>. As we all know, a manifold is a <em>topological space</em> that <strong>locally resembles Euclidean space</strong>. In the case of a smooth manifold, this means that around every point, the manifold can be approximated by a patch of Euclidean space in such a way that the transition maps between these patches are smooth (infinitely differentiable). A symplectic form on a manifold is a specific kind of differential form that is <strong>closed</strong> and <strong>non-degenerate</strong>. In more concrete terms, a symplectic form is a $2$-form, and non-degeneracy means that the form pairs vectors in a way that is <strong>invertible</strong> – no non-zero vector is mapped to zero – ensuring that the form provides a kind of generalized volume element on the manifold.</p> <p>To be more mathematically rigorous, let $M$ be a topological space that is Hausdorff (any two distinct points have disjoint neighborhoods) and second-countable (has a countable basis for its topology). Additionally, $M$ is locally homeomorphic to $\mathbb{R}^n$, meaning every point in $M$ has a neighborhood that is topologically the same as an open subset of Euclidean space (this practically says that $M$ is a manifold). A smooth manifold is a manifold equipped with an atlas of charts such that the transition maps between overlapping charts are smooth. On $M$, a symplectic form $\omega$ is a closed, non-degenerate differential $2$-form. Mathematically, this means</p> <ul> <li><strong>Closed</strong>: The exterior derivative $d\omega$ is zero, $d\omega = 0$. This implies that $\omega$ is <strong>locally exact</strong>.</li> <li><strong>Non-degenerate</strong>: For any vector $v\in T_ {p}M$ where $p \in M$, if $\omega(v, w) = 0$ for all vectors $w$ at that point, then $v$ must be the zero vector. This ensures that the form $\omega$ pairs vectors in a fully invertible way.</li> </ul> <p>Note that a symplectic manifold is necessarily even-dimensional. If $M$ is a symplectic manifold with symplectic form $\omega$, and the dimension of $M$ is $2n$, then $\omega^n$ (the $n$-th wedge power of $\omega$) is a volume form on $M$, providing a natural orientation.</p> <p><strong>Darboux’s theorem.</strong> Locally, all symplectic manifolds of the same dimension are isomorphic. This means that around any point in a symplectic manifold, one can find local coordinates (often called “canonical coordinates” or “Darboux coordinates”) $(q_1, \ldots, q_n, p_1, \ldots, p_n)$) in which the symplectic form has the standard expression $\omega = \sum_{i=1}^{n} dq_i \wedge dp_i$.</p> <p>In classical mechanics, symplectic manifolds serve as the stage for Hamiltonian dynamics. The <em>phase space of a classical mechanical system</em>, which includes both its positions and momenta, <em>can be treated as a symplectic manifold</em>. The symplectic form encodes the fundamental <em>Poisson brackets</em> of the system, which are central to Hamiltonian mechanics. It provides the geometric framework within which the evolution of the system can be elegantly expressed using Hamilton’s equations. The structure of symplectic manifolds imposes several interesting properties. For instance, in <strong>even-dimensional</strong> spaces, they allow for the formulation of Hamiltonian vector fields and symplectic transformations. These concepts have far-reaching applications not only in physics but also in areas like symplectic topology, geometric quantization, and more.</p> <h3 id="hamiltonian-equations">Hamiltonian equations</h3> <p>Most readers are much more comfortable with the Lagrangian formalism of field theory than the Hamiltonian formalism, so let’s start with the former. The transition from Lagrangian to Hamiltonian is achieved by <strong>Legendre transformation</strong>. We first define the canonical momenta $\pi_i$ conjugate to each field $\phi_i$ by \(\pi_i = \frac{\partial \mathcal{L}}{\partial (\partial_t \phi_i)},\) where $\mathcal{L}$ is the Lagrangian density and $\partial_t \phi_i$ is the time derivative of the field.</p> <p>The Hamiltonian density $\mathcal{H}$ is then given by \(\mathcal{H} = \sum_i \pi_i \partial_t \phi_i - \mathcal{L},\) where the sum runs over all fields in the theory.</p> <p>The equations of motion in the Hamiltonian formalism for field theory are then given by Hamilton’s equations, analogous to the Hamiltonian formalism in classical mechanics. These equations are</p> <p>\(\frac{\delta \mathcal{H}}{\delta \phi_i}=-\dot{\pi}(x),\) \(\frac{\delta \mathcal{H}}{\delta \pi_i} = \dot{\phi}_i,\) where $\delta / \delta \phi_i$ and $\delta / \delta \pi_i$ represent functional derivatives with respect to the field $\phi_i$ and its conjugate momentum $\pi_i$, respectively.</p> <p>From now on let’s assume there are only one type of field and canonical momentum, so we can neglect the subscript $i$. Note here the functional derivative $\delta / \delta \phi$ is not equivalent to the partial derivative $\partial / \partial \phi$. To see this, recall how $\delta \mathcal{H}$ and $\delta \mathcal{H} / \delta \phi$ is defined, \(\delta H =: \int d^{d-1}x \, \delta \mathcal{H} = \int d^{d-1}x \, \delta \phi \frac{\delta \mathcal{H}}{\delta \phi},\) thus all we need to do is to perform a variation of the field $\phi$ and leaving the canonical momentum $\pi$ untouched, then massage the variation of the Hamiltonian in the form given above. For a generic Hamiltonian $\mathcal{H}(\pi,\phi,\partial_ {x}\phi)$ where $x$ denotes all the spatial coordinates, under the field variation $\phi\to\phi+\delta \phi$ we have \(\begin{align*} H\to H' &amp;= \int d^{d-1}x \, \mathcal{H}(\phi+\delta \phi,\partial_ {x}\phi+\partial_ {x}\delta\phi, \cdots) \\ &amp;= \int d^{d-1}x \, \left[ \frac{\partial\mathcal{H}}{\partial \phi }\delta \phi + \frac{\partial \mathcal{H}}{\partial(\partial_ {x}\phi)}\delta(\partial_ {x}\phi) \right] \\ &amp;= \int d^{d-1}x \, \left[ \frac{\partial\mathcal{H}}{\partial \phi }\delta \phi + \frac{\partial \mathcal{H}}{\partial(\partial_ {x}\phi)}(\partial_ {x}\delta\phi) \right] \\ \\ &amp;= \int d^{d-1}x \, \left[ \frac{\partial\mathcal{H}}{\partial \phi }\delta \phi - \left( \partial_ x\frac{\partial \mathcal{H}}{\partial(\partial_ {x}\phi)} \right) \delta\phi \right] \\ \\ &amp;= \int d^{d-1}x \, \delta\phi \left[ \frac{\partial\mathcal{H}}{\partial \phi } - \left( \partial_ x\frac{\partial \mathcal{H}}{\partial(\partial_ {x}\phi)} \right) \right] \\ &amp;= : \int d^{d-1}x \, \delta \phi \frac{\delta \mathcal{H}}{\delta \phi} \end{align*}\) thus, \(\frac{\delta \mathcal{H}}{\delta \phi} = \frac{\partial\mathcal{H}}{\partial \phi } - \left( \partial_ x\frac{\partial \mathcal{H}}{\partial(\partial_ {x}\phi)} \right).\) Taking this back to the Hamiltonian equations we recover the familiar Euler-Lagrange equation.</p> <p>These equations describe how the fields and their conjugate momenta evolve over time, analogous to how the position and momentum of a particle evolve in classical mechanics. They provide a complete description of the dynamics of the field system within the Hamiltonian framework.</p> <h3 id="basics-of-qft">Basics of QFT</h3> <p>The starting point of defining a quantum field theory is the choice of a manifold $M$ of dimension $d$. We mostly (but not always) regard the manifold as a Riemannian manifold with a <strong>smooth</strong> metric on it. The manifold may or may not have boundaries, if it does then some additional information is needed at the boundaries to define the theory.</p> <p>Having defined the manifold $M$, the next ingredient is the choice of objects to consider over $M$, the so-called “degree of freedoms”, or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">fields</code>. Now it is helpful to adopt a statistical viewpoint toward QFT, in order to extract the information about physical observables we need “just” to know the partition function, which is obtain via a so-called path-integral. That is, we integrate all the possible field configurations with a weight, which is essentially given by the exponent of the action. For example, we may consider a principal bundle with a connection over $M$. In physics terminology the choice of the connection is the same as picking a gauge field. We may also be considering the section of a vector bundle over $M$, these fields are sometimes called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">matter field</code>.</p> <p>As another example of QFT we may consider the space of maps \(X: M\to N\) where $N$ is the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">target</code> manifold. The field theories associated with integrating over the space of such maps are called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sigma models</code>.</p> <p>In quantum field theories we are typically interested in integrating over infinite-dimensional spaces. It turns out that the greater the dimension $d$ of $M$, the more complicated the integrations over these spaces. In fact (ignoring gravitational theories), the only non-trivial quantum field theories that are believed to exist (i.e., for which some kind of integration over the infinite-dimensional space exists) have $d \leq 6$ and most of the standard ones have $d \leq 4$.</p> <p>Quantum field theories in different dimensions can be related to each other by an operation known as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Kaluza–Klein reduction</code>. Roughly speaking this means considering the situation where \(M = N \times K,\quad K \ll N\) The action may be very large for field configurations that are <strong>not</strong> constant over $K$, so the path-integral, which is weighted by $e^{ -S_ {E} }$, localizes to field configurations that are constant along $K$. This gives rise to an <strong>effective</strong> path integral over field configurations that have only constant modes along $K$.</p> <h2 id="the-model">The model</h2> <h2 id="hamiltonian-truncation">Hamiltonian Truncation</h2> <p>In our case, we consider the phi-fourth theory defined on \(M = \mathbb{T}^{2} \times \mathbb{R},\) where $\mathbb{T}^{2}$ is the flat torus space of size $L \times L$, and the time direction $\mathbb{R}$ is left uncompactified. Since the space manifold is compact, the spectrum of the free theory is discrete and free of IR divergence. Following the procedure of canonical quantization, we first expand the scalar field in terms of ladder operators (in discrete form) as \(\phi(\vec{x}) = \sum_ {k_ {1},k_ {2}} c_ {k} a_ {k}e^{ +i \vec{k}\cdot \vec{x} } + \text{h.c.} \tag{1}\) where $\vec{k}$ is the two-dimensional momentum vector $\vec{k}=(k_ {1},k_ {2})$. Since the space is a torus of size $L \times L$, the momentum can only take values \(k_ {i} = \frac{2\pi n_ {i} }{L},\quad n_ {i} \in \mathbb{Z}.\) The coefficient $c_ {k}$ is defined to be \(c_ {k} = \frac{1}{L\sqrt{ 2\omega_ {k} }},\quad \omega _ {k} = \sqrt{ k^{2}+m^{2} }.\) The canonical quantization in terms of the ladder operator is rather simple, \([a_ {k} , a_ {k'}^{^{\dagger}}] = \delta_ {k,k'},\quad \text{zero otherwise.}\) The free Hamiltonian is \(\mathcal{H}_ {0} = \frac{1}{2} \pi^{2} + \frac{1}{2 } (\nabla \phi)^{2} + \frac{m^{2}}{2} \phi^{2},\) where $\pi$ is the canonical momentum. So far we have assumed that the field configuration is static so there is no contribution from the canonical momentum. Taking Eq. (1) to $\mathcal{H}_ {0}$ we have \(H_ {0} = \int _ {L^{2}} d^{2}x \, \mathcal{H}_ {0} = \sum_ {k} \omega_ {k} a_ {k} ^{\dagger} a_ {k} + \text{Const},\) where the constant term is the zero point energy.</p> <p>The free vacuum is defined by $H_ {0} \left\lvert{0}\right\rangle=0$.</p> <p>The interacting Hamiltonian is defined as \(\mathcal{H} (E_ {T}) = \mathcal{H}_ {0} + \mathcal{V}, \quad \mathcal{V}=g_ {2} \mathcal{V}_ {2} + g_ {4} \mathcal{V} _ {4}+ C(E_ {T}),\) where \(\mathcal{V}_ {n} = \frac{1}{n!} :\phi^{n}:\) and $:\bullet:$ denotes the normal ordering. $E_ {T}$ is the truncation energy and $C(E_ {T})$ is a counter terms which will be needed later.</p> <hr/> <p>The Hilbert space is spanned by the eigenstates of the <strong>free</strong> Hamiltonian, $\left\lvert{E_ {i}}\right\rangle$. In the Hamiltonian truncation approach, we only consider the the states with $E_ {i} &lt; E_ {T}=: \Lambda$. In this case, the <strong>full</strong> Hamiltonian can be considered as a finite-dimensional matrix \(H_ {ij} := \left\langle{E_ {i}}\right\rvert H \left\lvert{E_ {j} }\right\rangle .\) At weak coupling, the spectrum of the truncated Hamiltonian can be computed using Hamiltonian Perturbation Theory (HPT).</p> <h3 id="hamiltonian-perturbation-theory">Hamiltonian Perturbation Theory</h3> <p>In quantum field theory, Lagrangian perturbation theory has been dominant, especially in the study of scattering processes and elementary particle physics. This approach’s explicit covariance has been crucial in implementing the renormalization program.</p> <p>The total Hamiltonian $H$ of a system is divided into two parts, 1) the unperturbed Hamiltonian $H_0$, which is solvable and represents the system in the absence of the interaction or perturbation, and 2) the perturbation Hamiltonian $H’$, which represents the interaction or perturbation that is considered small compared to $H_0$.</p> <p>The idea is to treat the perturbation $H’$ as a small correction to $H_0$ and expand the observables of interest (like the energy levels or scattering amplitudes) in a power series of $H’$.</p> <p>In the absence of the perturbation, the eigenstates and eigenvalues of $H_0$ are assumed to be known. <em>These serve as the basis for exploring the effects of the perturbation.</em> The corrections to the eigenvalues and eigenstates of the system due to $H’$ can be calculated iteratively. In practical calculations, Feynman diagrams (or similar diagrams) are used to visually and systematically represent the terms in the perturbation series. Each diagram corresponds to a mathematical term in the expansion and simplifies the computation of complex interactions.</p> <h3 id="hamiltonian-truncation-with-uv-divergence">Hamiltonian truncation with UV divergence</h3> <p>In the paper “Exploring Hamiltonian Truncation in $d = 2 + 1$”, the $\phi^{2}$ theory is analysed using different methods, including analytical, perturbative, and HT solutions, to establish the reliability of the HT method.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Background]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes on Coleman-Weinberg Potential</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Coleman-Weinberg-Potential/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes on Coleman-Weinberg Potential"/><published>2023-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Coleman-Weinberg-Potential</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Coleman-Weinberg-Potential/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="quantum-effective-action">Quantum Effective Action</h3> <p>The goal of this chapter is to introduce the quantum action and quantum potential. There are usually two kinds of quantum actions, one is the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Wilsonian quantum action</code>, where the higher momentum modes are integrated out to focus on the low-energy, long-distance behavior of a system. The Wilsonian effective potential is a way to understand the behavior of a physical system at different scales. Take a scalar field theory $\phi$ for example. The “integrating out” procedure is done using the path integral approach, it involves <em>separating the field into high and low energy parts</em>. We split the scalar field into $\phi = \phi_ {\text{low}} + \phi_ {\text{high}}$, where $\phi_ {\text{low}}$ contains modes below a certain energy scale $\Lambda$ and $\phi_ {\text{high}}$ contains modes above $\Lambda$. Then, the path integral over the full field is then re-written as a path integral over these two components. The crucial step is to integrate out the high-energy modes $\phi_ {\text{high}}$. This can be done perturbatively by treating $\phi_ {\text{high}}$ as a different field as $\phi_ {\text{low}}$, using Feynman diagram techniques. The resulting effective action should only depends on the low-energy modes. Then, the Wilsonian effective action captures the dynamics of the field <em>at energies below</em> $\Lambda$. It will typically have a form different from the original action, often with new interactions generated as a result of integrating out the high-energy modes.</p> <p>The other kind of effective action is the so-called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">quantum effective actions</code> which is the Legendre transformation of the generating functional of connected diagrams, this is quite a mouthful and we will talk more about it in the next section. When the original action is replaced by the quantum effective action, the tree-level diagrams generated by it will contain <em>all the quantum corrections</em> of the full theory (i.e. the original theory). The quantum effective action has a useful property that it can give us the vacuum expectation value (VEV) of the field operator with quantum correction. As we will see, the Coleman-Weinberg potential is a special case of the effective action.</p> <hr/> <p>There are in general three ways to calculate the effective action as listed in the following.</p> <ul> <li>By matching, we require</li> </ul> \[\int \mathcal{D}\{\text{original dof}\} e^{iS} = \int \mathcal{D}\{\text{effective dof}\} e^{i\Gamma}\] <p>where dof stands for the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">degree of freedom</code>, the LHS is the original theory while the RHS is the effective theory, with different degree of freedom, $\Gamma$ is the quantum action.</p> <ul> <li> <p>by Legendre transformation, as will be shown in the next section.</p> </li> <li> <p>by background field method, that is to separate the field into a static non-propagating background field $\phi_ b$ and a dynamic propagating field $\tilde{\phi}$, the dynamic fields are the fluctuations around the background field. Integrating out the fluctuations (usually done perturbatively) leaves us the effective potential $\Gamma[\phi_ b]$,</p> </li> </ul> \[\int \mathcal{D} \phi e^{i S[\phi_ b + \tilde{\phi}]} = e^{i\Gamma[\phi_ b]}.\] <p>Another approach to deriving an effective theory is through an educated guess. Given that the effective action must possess the same symmetries as the original action, one can propose various <em>local terms</em> that fulfill this requirement. The coefficients of these terms are then adjusted based on experimental data. This method relies on symmetry considerations to guide the formulation of potential terms in the effective action.</p> <p>For the rest of the note, we will confine our discussion to $\phi^4$ model with real scalar fields.</p> <h3 id="quantum-action">Quantum Action</h3> <p>The partition function (with source) reads \(Z[J] = \int \mathcal{D} \phi e^{iS[\phi] + i\int \phi J}\) where $S$ is the action, $J$ is the source, $\int \phi J$ is short for $\int dx^4 \phi(x) J(x)$. $\phi$ field is integrated out hence $Z$ is a functional of $J$ only.</p> <p>From it we can define the generating function $W[J]$ by \(Z[J] = e^{iW[J]} \implies W[J] = -i \ln Z[J],\) $W[J]$ is the summation of connected diagrams with source, refer to Mark Srednicki’s text book on quantum field theory. It generate <em>connected diagrams</em>, due to the exponential form of the path integral representation.</p> <p>The expectation value of $\phi$ in the presence of a source $J$ is given by</p> \[\left\langle {\phi}_ J \right\rangle=\frac{1}{Z} \int \mathcal{D} \phi e^{iS[\phi] + i\int \phi J} \phi = \frac{\delta W[J]}{\delta J(x)}\equiv \varphi,\] <p>Note the difference between $\phi$ and the so-called “varphi” $\varphi$, the former is a operator while the latter is a classical field. When compared to the classical mechanics of point particles, $W$ is similar to the Lagrangian $L$, $J$ to $\dot{q}$, and $\delta W / \delta J$ to $\partial L / \partial \dot{q}$ which define a new variable.</p> <p>The generating functional $W[J]$ is a functional of $J$, we can perform Legendre transformation to define a new functional in terms of $\delta W / \delta J =: \varphi$. Behold, the quantum action:</p> \[\boxed{ \Gamma[\varphi] = W[J] - \int J\varphi , }\] <p>which is indeed a functional of $\varphi$, and we have omitted the measure under the integral sign. We have</p> <p>\(\frac{\delta\Gamma}{\delta\varphi} = -J.\) <strong>Summary.</strong></p> <ul> <li>$\Gamma[\varphi]$ generates the 1-particle irreducible (1PI) diagrams;</li> <li>$W[J]$ generates connected diagrams;</li> <li>$Z[J]$ generates all kinds of diagrams.</li> </ul> <hr/> <p>There are superficially two different ways to define the quantum effective action, 1) by requiring that the tree diagrams of the effective action reproduce the quantum effects of the original action, and 2) by Legendre transformation. It is not meant to be obvious, but they are equivalent to each other. To see it, we can first <strong>define</strong> $\Gamma[\phi]$ to be whose tree diagrams gives us all the quantum effects, then since $iW[J]$ also gives all the quantum effects with loops, we have</p> \[e^{iW[J]} = \lim_ {\hbar\to 0} \int \mathcal{D}\phi e^{i\Gamma[\phi]/\hbar}\] <p>where the limiting process isolates out the tree contribution, then use the fastest descent approximation we find $\Gamma$ can be written as the Legendre transformation of $W[J]$.</p> <p>To see that $\Gamma$ generates only the 1PI diagrams, recall that quantum effective action has the property that the tree-level graphs generated by it gives the complete scattering amplitude. Putting $\Gamma[\varphi]$ at the position of action $S$, we will have a new path integral \(Z_ \Gamma[J] = \int \mathcal{D}\phi e^{i\Gamma +i\int \phi J}.\) It will generate Feynman diagrams with sources, just like the original action $S$ does, only this time the tree diagrams alone is enough to give the complete information of the original theory. Thus $\Gamma$ must gives us exact propagators and exact n-point vertices, while the original action $S$ gives us the ordinary propagator and ordinary vertex. Also in order to calculate the exact n-point vertex, we need not consider the 1-particle reducible diagrams since any contribution from connected diagram can be written as a tree diagram comprised of two or more sub 1 particle IRREDUCIBLE diagrams.</p> <p><strong>Remark.</strong> The generating functionals such as $W[J]$ and $\Gamma[\varphi]$ are classical. In fact the language of path integral has a feeling of classical field theory, in the sense that each path we take into consideration is a c-field in space-time, instead of q-field.</p> <h4 id="tree-level-example">Tree-level Example</h4> <p>In the classical limit, taking the limit $\hbar \to 0$, the partition function become \(Z = \int \mathcal{D}\phi e^{iS + i\int \phi J}\) which receives dominant contribution from the stationary configuration, given by \(\frac{\delta}{\delta\phi}\left( S + \int \phi J \right) = 0 \implies \frac{\delta S}{\delta\phi} = - J\) which has a solution $\varphi$. Thus the partition function is \(Z = e^{iS+i\int \varphi J}\) up to a normalization factor. Since \(W[J] = -i \ln Z = S + \int \varphi J,\) we have \(\varphi = \frac{\delta W}{\delta J} = \left\langle {\phi}_ J \right\rangle\) thus \(\Gamma[\varphi] = W - \int \varphi J = S[\varphi].\) At the tree-level, the quantum effective action and the original action are the same.</p> <h3 id="effective-potential">Effective Potential</h3> <p>In the classical dynamics, the vacuum (lowest energy state) configuration of the system is given by the minimum of the potential. In the quantum theory, we are sometimes interested in the vacuum expectation value (VEV) of the field operator $\phi$. In a quantum field theory, there is also have a potential term whose minimum gives the classical vacuum field configuration, however that’s not the full story, since in a quantum theory the field always fluctuates around the vacuum, giving rise to a correction to $\left\langle \phi \right\rangle$.</p> <p>We want a quantum effective potential which works like the classical potential, in the sense that its minimum corresponds to the field configuration of the vacuum, quantum corrections included. Luckily we already have something like that, i.e. the quantum effective action.</p> <p>Recall that the quantum effective action</p> <ul> <li>is a functional of $\varphi$, and $\varphi = \left\langle {\phi}_ J \right\rangle$, meaning $\varphi$ is the expectation value of $\phi$ in the presence of a source term $J$, and</li> <li>satisfies ${\delta \Gamma}/{\delta \varphi} = J$ thus</li> <li>when $J=0$, the solution to ${\delta \Gamma}/{\delta \varphi} = J$ is the vev of $\phi$.</li> </ul> <p>Furthermore, assume that the vacuum has translation symmetry, meaning $\left\langle \phi \right\rangle$ is a constant in space and time, then we just need one number to denote the field configuration, we can define a function $\mathcal{V} _ {\text{eff}}$ whose minimum is the vev of $\phi$, \(\Gamma[\varphi]|_ {\varphi = \text{const}} = -VT \mathcal{V}_ {\text{eff}}(\varphi)\) where $V$ is the volume of the space and $T$ the extension of time, $\mathcal{V} _ {\text{eff}}(\varphi)$ is the quantum effective potential. We can see that $\mathcal{V} _ {\text{eff}}$ is a intensive quantity while $\Gamma$ is a extensive quantity, and ${\partial\mathcal{V}}/{\partial\phi} = 0$ reproduces ${\delta \Gamma}/{\delta \varphi} = 0$.</p> <h2 id="coleman-weinberg-potential">Coleman-Weinberg Potential</h2> <h3 id="background-fields">Background Fields</h3> <p>The method of background method is very useful for calculating beta functions and effective action. For a real scalar field $\phi$, the general idea is as following</p> <ul> <li>separate the field into the static background field $\phi_ b$ and dynamic field $\phi$, $\phi \to \phi_ b + \phi$. By static we mean it is not path-integrated, thus don’t propagate. It will simplify the calculation a lot.</li> <li>Define the corresponding action with background field $S_ b[\phi_ b;\phi]$, and resulting generating functional $W_ b[\phi_ b;\phi]$, and the effective action $\Gamma_ b[\phi_ b;\varphi]$, where $\varphi$ is defined to be the vev of $\phi$ in the presence of the background field $\phi_ b$.</li> <li>$\Gamma_ b[\phi_ b;\varphi]$ has the useful property that \(\Gamma_ b[\phi_ b=\phi;0] = \Gamma_ b[\phi_ b=0;\varphi] = \Gamma[\varphi].\)</li> </ul> <p>The first term means that the effective action with background field $\phi_ b = \phi$ and zero dynamic field $\varphi = 0$. Since the dynamic field will be set to zero at last, if a diagram has dynamic field external legs, it is also zero. It is similar to the Feynman diagrams with sources, when we set $J=0$ in the end then all the diagrams with a un-canceled source vanish.</p> <p>The reason why $\phi_ b$ does not propagate can be seen in two ways, namely in the context of canonical quantization and path integral.</p> <p><strong>Canonical:</strong> the background field $\phi_ b$ is regarded as a classical field, it is not quantized thus there is no such thing as $\phi_ b$ propagator, <strong>Path integral:</strong> $\phi_ b$ don’t fluctuate, means it is left out of the path integral, recall how we came to the propagator in the first place, it means $\phi_ b$ don’t propagate.</p> <p>The action with a background field is defined as \(S_ b[\phi_ b;\phi] = \int d^4x\mathcal{L}(\phi_ b+\phi),\) the partition function with source is \(\mathcal{Z}[\phi_ b;J] = \int \mathcal{D}\phi \exp\{ i S_ b[\phi_ b;\phi]+i\int J\phi \} = \mathcal{Z}[J] e^{-i\int J\phi_ b},\) note that the source only couples to the dynamic field. Since $\phi$ is integrated over, $\mathcal{Z}$ can only be a functional of $\phi_ b, J$. Define the generating function as \(W_ b[\phi_ b;J] \equiv -i \ln \mathcal{Z}_ b[\phi_ b;J] \implies W_b[\phi_ b;J] = W[J] - \int J\phi.\) Define \(\varphi_ b(x) = \frac{\delta W_ b[J]}{\delta J(x)}\) we have \(\varphi_ b = \varphi - \phi_ b\) which means that in the presence of a background field, $\left\langle \phi \right\rangle$ will be shifted by $\phi_ b$, which is kind of natural.</p> <p>Now we need to define the effective action in the presence of a background field, by the means of Legendre transformation again. \(\Gamma_ b [\phi_ b;\varphi_ b] = W_ b - \int \frac{\delta W_ b[J]}{\delta J}J = W_ b - \int \varphi_ b J\) you can check that \(\frac{\delta \Gamma_ b[\phi_ b;\varphi_ b]}{\delta\varphi_ b}= J .\) Replace $W_ b[J]$ with its expression in terms of $W[J]$, we can check that \(\Gamma_ b[\phi_ b;\varphi_ b] = W[J] - \int J (\varphi_ b+\phi_ b) = \Gamma[\phi_ b + \varphi_ b]\) so for example if we want to calculate $\Gamma[\eta(x)]$, we can set $\phi_ b = \eta,\,\varphi = 0$ and use that to simplify calculations.</p> <h3 id="coleman-weinberg-potential-1">Coleman-Weinberg Potential</h3> <p>Consider the real scalar Lagrangian \(\mathcal{L} = -\frac{1}{2} \phi \partial^2\phi - \frac{1}{2} m^2\phi^2-\frac{1}{4!}\phi^4\) the question is, when $m = 0$, will the quantum effects modify the shape of the potential?</p> <p>Introduce a background field $\phi \to \phi_ b +\phi$, take it into the action and expand, keep in mind that the path integral is over field $\phi$ only, we have \(\begin{align} e^{i\Gamma[\phi_ b]} &amp;= e^{i\int d^4 x (-\frac{1}{2} \phi_ b \partial^2 \phi_ b-V(\phi_ b))} \\ \\ &amp;\times\int \mathcal{D}\phi e^{i \int d^4 x (-\frac{1}{2} \phi \partial^2 \phi -V(\phi_ b) - \phi V'(\phi_ b)-\frac{1}{2}V''[\phi_ b]\phi^2-\frac{1}{3!}V'''[\phi_ b]\phi^3-\cdots)}. \end{align}\) In the path integral, one of the terms in the Lagrangian, i.e. $\int \mathcal{D} \phi e^{i\phi V’}$ can be thrown away because we only need to consider 1PI diagrams in the calculation of $\Gamma$, while the Feynman diagram given by $\phi V’(\phi_ b)$ will never contribute to the 1PI diagrams. For the same reason we can also discard $\phi^3$ term in the Lagrangian. At one loop, there will be no contributions from $\phi^4$ and higher terms either. Hence we are left with \(e^{i\Gamma[\phi_ b]} = e^{i\int d^4 x (-\frac{1}{2} \phi_ b \partial^2 \phi_ b-V(\phi_ b))} \int \mathcal{D} e^{i \int d^4 x (-\frac{1}{2} \phi \partial^2 \phi -\frac{1}{2}V''[\phi_ b]\phi^2)}.\) use the master formulae in QFT \(\int\mathcal{D}\phi\exp\left\{ i \int d^4x (\phi M \phi) \right\} = \mathcal{N}\frac{1}{\text{det}^{M}}\) we have \(e^{i\Gamma[\phi_ b]} = \mathcal{N}e^{i\int d^4 x (-\frac{1}{2} \phi_ b \partial^2 \phi_ b-V(\phi_ b))} \text{det}^{-1/2}(\partial^2 + V''(\phi_ b))\) In order to calculate the functional determinant, we need to put it in a specific representation, such as the position representation or the momentum representation, to turn $\partial^2 + V’’(\phi_ b)$ into a matrix, then calculate the determinant of that infinite dimensional matrix. Writing \(\Gamma[\phi_ b] = \int d^4 x (-\frac{1}{2} \phi_ b \partial^2 \phi_ b-V(\phi_ b)) + \Delta \Gamma[\phi_ b],\) where \(i\Delta \Gamma[\phi_ b] = -\frac{1}{2}\ln \det (\partial^2 +V''(\phi_ b)) + \text{const}.\) With the help of identity \(\ln \det M = \ln \prod_ i \lambda_ i = \sum_ i \ln \lambda_ i = \text{tr } {\ln M}\) where $\lambda_ i$ are the eigenvalues of $M$, we have \(i\Delta \Gamma[\phi_ b] = -\frac{1}{2} \text{tr } {\ln (\partial^2 +V''(\phi_ b))} + \text{const}.\) Next we assume that $\phi_ b$ is a const in space-time, and define \(m_ {\text{eff}}^2(\phi_ b) \equiv V''(\phi_ b),\) calculate the functional determinant in the representation of $x$, with the help of \(\mathbb{1}= \int \frac{dp^4}{(2\pi)^4} \left\lvert k \right\rangle \left\langle{k}\right\rvert\) we have \(\begin{align} i\Delta \Gamma[\phi_ b] &amp;= -\frac{1}{2}\int d^4 x \left\langle{x}\right\rvert \ln\left( 1+\frac{V''}{\partial^2} \right) \left\lvert{x}\right\rangle +\text{const}\\ &amp;= -\frac{1}{2}\int d^4 x \int\frac{d^4 k}{(2\pi)^4}\ln\left( 1-\frac{m_ {\text{eff}}^2}{k^2} \right)+\text{const} \end{align}\) where $\int d^4 x = VT$ is the space-time volume of the system.</p> <p>The integral over momentum is divergent, we will render it finite by a hard cut-off, that is to Wick rotate the system into Euclidean space and insert the momentum cut-off $\Lambda$, yielding \(\begin{align} \Delta\Gamma[\phi_ b] &amp;= -VT \frac{2\pi^2}{2(2\pi)^4} \int_ 0^\Lambda dk_ E k_ E^3 \ln(1+\frac{m_ {\text{eff}}^2}{k_ E3^2}) +\text{const}\\ &amp;= - \frac{VT}{128\pi^2} \left( 2 m_ {\text{eff}}^2 \Lambda^2 + 2m_ {\text{eff}}^4 \ln\frac{m_ {\text{eff}}^2}{\Lambda^2}+\text{const}\right) \end{align}\) where $k_ E$ is the Wick-rotated momentum and we have used the relation $\Lambda \gg m_ {\text{eff}}$. The effective potential accordingly is \(V_ {\text{eff}} = V(\phi_ b) + c_ 1 + c_ 2 m_ {\text{eff}}^2 + \frac{1}{64\pi^2} m_ {\text{eff}}^4 \ln\frac{m_ {\text{eff}}^2}{c_ 3}\) where $c_ 1,c_ 2,c_ 3$ are some $\Lambda$-dependent constants. They are independent of $\phi_ b$ thus in general are not of interests to us. For example, $c_ 2 = \Lambda^2 / 64\pi^2$.</p> <p>Next we need to add the counter terms to the potential \(V(\phi) = \frac{1}{2}m_ R^2(1+\delta_ m)\phi^2 +\frac{\lambda_ R}{4!}(1+\delta_ \lambda)\phi^4 +\Lambda_ R (1+\delta_ \Lambda),\) with all the counter terms starting at 1-loop level, that is of $\mathcal{O}(\lambda_ R)$. $m_ {\text{eff}}^2$ is still defined as $V’’$.</p> <p>What about the renormalization conditions?</p> <ul> <li>The question we want to ask is how the quantum corrections change the shape of the potential, when the mass term is zero, thus we require $\lambda_ R^2 = 0$</li> <li>$V(0) = 0 \implies \Lambda_ R = 0$</li> <li>$\lambda_ R = V’’’’(\phi_ R)$ for some arbitrary fixed scale $\phi_ R$</li> </ul> <p>They will fix the counter terms, plugging them in gives \(\boxed{ V_ {\text{eff}}(\phi) = \frac{1}{4!}\phi^4\left\{ \lambda_ R + \frac{3 \lambda_ R^2}{32\pi^2}\left[ \ln \left( \frac{\phi^2}{\phi_ R^2}-\frac{25}{6} \right) \right] \right\} }\) which is known as Coleman-Weinberg potential.</p> <p>Now having the effective potential at hand, we can answer the question: does the quantum correction change the vacuum expectation value of $\phi$? Originally, without the quantum correction, the minimum of the potential is at $\phi = 0$ since there is no quadratic term and only a quartic term. With quantum correction, the vev of $\phi$ is given by the minimum of the effective potential, which is the Coleman-Weinberg potential, which is minimized when \(\lambda_ R \ln \frac{\left\langle \phi^{2} \right\rangle}{\phi_ R^2} = \frac{11}{3} \lambda_ R - \frac{32}{3}\pi^2.\) which gives a nonzero $\left\langle \phi \right\rangle$. It means now we have a double-well potential, instead of the original single-well potential, due to the quantum correction.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="ColemanWeinbergPotential"/><category term="EffectiveTheory"/><category term="Coleman"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Quantum Effective Action]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">罗伯特议事规则</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/%E7%BD%97%E4%BC%AF%E7%89%B9%E8%AE%AE%E4%BA%8B%E8%A7%84%E5%88%99/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="罗伯特议事规则"/><published>2023-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/%E7%BD%97%E4%BC%AF%E7%89%B9%E8%AE%AE%E4%BA%8B%E8%A7%84%E5%88%99</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/%E7%BD%97%E4%BC%AF%E7%89%B9%E8%AE%AE%E4%BA%8B%E8%A7%84%E5%88%99/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="当会议主持人的讲究">当会议主持人的讲究</h2> <p>协商会议的进行至少需要两名会议官员，一是主持人（或主席），负责主持会议、秉持规则；二是记录员，负责会议的书面记录。<em>这二人都该计入法定人数</em>。主持人要保证<em>能看到整个会场，所有与会者都能看到他</em>。</p> <p>在指定的开会时间，主持人需要判断出席人数是否满足法定人数，如果满足，主持人当等待会场肃静，或者示意会场肃静，然后大声宣布“会议现在开始／开幕”或“现在进入会议程序”。</p> <h2 id="动议motion">动议(motion)</h2> <p>动议是指在会议中由一名参与者提出的一个<em>正式提议</em>，用以建议采取某项行动或决策。指与会者在 会议之上提出的、需要会议给予处理的正式建议。例如，在一个组织的会议上，有一名成员想提出一个新的议题，要求增加会议预算。</p> <p>成员提出动议，必须向主持人处取得<em>发言权</em>，这要求他从自己的位置上起立，向主持人申请（主持人可以点头示意）。如果数人同时起立申请发言，那么最先起立并称呼主持人的那位将取得发言权。</p> <p>对动议的处理，可分六个步骤</p> <ol> <li>一位成员提出动议。例如，成员A说：“要求增加会议预算。”</li> <li>另（至少）一位成员表示附议，即支持该动议。例如，成员 B 说：“我支持这个动议。”</li> <li>主持人宣布议题。例如，主持人说：“已经有动议提出并得到支持，现在开始讨论增加年度会议预算10%的动议。”</li> <li>与会成员就议题展开辩论。例如，成员们轮流发表意见，有的支持增加预算以改善会议质量，有的则担心预算增加可能会给组织带来财务压力。</li> <li>主持人将议题提请表决。可通过举手等方式进行。</li> <li>主持人宣布表决结果。例如，主持人宣布：“增加年度会议预算10%的动议已通过/未通过。”</li> </ol> <hr/> <p>动议主要分为三大类：主动议（Main Motions）、辅动议（Subsidiary Motions）、和再议类动议（Incidental Motions）。</p> <p><strong>主动议（Main Motions）</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong>定义</strong>：主动议是提出新议题的动议。它旨在引入一个待会议考虑的主题，并在通过后成为会议的正式决定。</li> <li><strong>例子</strong>：比如，在社区会议上，一名成员提出主动议：“我提议社区购买新的游乐设施。”这个动议旨在引入一个全新的议题，即购买游乐设施的议题。</li> </ul> <p><strong>辅动议（Subsidiary Motions）</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong>定义</strong>：辅动议用于修改、延迟或以其他方式影响主动议的处理方式。<em>辅动议通常优先于主动议进行考虑</em>。</li> <li><strong>例子</strong>：假设有人提出主动议：“我提议增加今年的社区保安预算。”接着，另一名成员提出辅动议：“我提议将这个动议提交给财务委员会进行详细评估。”这个辅动议旨在修改处理主动议的方式。</li> </ul> <p><strong>再议类动议（Incidental Motions）</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong>定义</strong>：再议类动议通常与<em>会议的程序</em>有关，它们出现在对会议流程、议程、或成员权利和特权的问题上。<em>这类动议通常在出现时立即处理</em>。</li> <li><strong>例子</strong>：在讨论一项议题时，一名成员可能会提出再议类动议：“我请求对议程进行修改，以便先讨论另一个更紧急的议题。”这个动议直接涉及到会议的议程安排，需要立即处理。</li> </ul> <p>具而言之，主动议可以进一步细分为<strong>实质主动议</strong>（Substantive Main Motion）和<strong>程序主动议</strong>（Procedural Main Motion）。<em>实质主动议是提出一个新的议题或建议，通常与组织的实质性活动或决策有关</em>。例如，在一个社区会议上，一名成员可能提出这样的实质主动议：“我提议社区为公园购置新的儿童游乐设施。”这个动议提出了一个具体的行动建议，即购买新的游乐设施，这是一个实质性的议题。而<em>程序主动议涉及会议的程序或组织运作方式的改变</em>。这类动议通常关注于会议的流程或规则。例如，在一个公司董事会会议上，成员可能提出这样的程序主动议：“我提议修改会议议程，将财务报告的讨论提前到今天的第一项议程。”这个动议关注的是会议的议程安排，是一个程序性的议题。</p> <p>实质主动议和程序主动议的区别在于，前者关注于组织的具体决策或行动，而后者则关注于会议的流程、规则或组织的运作方式。这两种主动议都是会议决策过程中不可或缺的部分。</p> <hr/> <p>辅动议（Subsidiary Motions）可以进一步细分为<strong>附属动议</strong>（Subsidiary Motions）、<strong>优先动议</strong>（Privileged Motions）和<strong>偶发动议</strong>（Incidental Motions）。这三类辅动议都用于影响或处理主动议，但它们的功能和使用场合有所不同。</p> <p><em>附属动议用于直接影响或处理在讨论中的主动议</em>。这些动议可以修改、延迟或以其他方式影响主动议。例如，在会议中，当有成员提出主动议：“我提议增加年度社区活动预算。”随后，另一名成员可能提出附属动议：“我提议将这个动议推迟到下次会议再讨论。”附属动议共计七种：搁置、修改、委托、改期、调整辩论限制、结束辩论、暂停。</p> <p><em>优先动议与会议的主题无关，但由于它们的重要性或紧迫性，优先于其他所有动议处理</em>。这类动议通常涉及会议的基本需求或成员的权利。例如，在长时间的会议中，一名成员可能感到疲劳，因此提出优先动议：“我提议现在休息15分钟。”这个动议由于涉及会议成员的即时需求，因此优先于正在讨论的主动议处理。优先动议共计五种：要求遵守议程、提出权益问题、休息、休会、指定后续会议时间。</p> <p><em>偶发动议通常与会议的程序、议程或成员权利和特权有关</em>，它们出现在对会议流程、议程的问题上。这类动议通常在提出时立即处理。例如，在一次讨论中，如果一名成员认为另一名成员的发言与议题不相关，他可能提出偶发动议：“我要求点名表决，以决定是否继续讨论这个子议题。”这个动议直接影响会议的进行方式和讨论内容。这些辅动议通过提供对主动议的处理方式、会议流程的调整和即时需求的解决，确保了会议的高效和有序进行。偶发动议主要包括程序问题、申诉、暂缓规则、反对考虑、拆分议题、逐段或逐条讨论、起立重新表决、关于表决方式的动议、关于提名的动议、请求免责、请求和咨询等。</p> <hr/> <p><em>再议类动议</em>，所谓再议，即对已经处理的动议再次进行考虑。它分作四种：恢复、取消（或修改）、收回委托、重议。</p> <h3 id="各动议之间的优先关系">各动议之间的优先关系</h3> <p>与名目相反，<em>辅动议优先于主动议</em>；这类似于重要的事情可以在解决了当前次要问题之后从容解决。三大辅动议中：</p> \[\text{偶发动议} \geq \text{优先动议} &gt; \text{附属动议}\] <p>比如说，会议正在讨论交党费的问题，这是主议题。之后讨论最多能延期几天的问题，这是辅动议里的附属动议。这时有人提出来说我家里着火了，提议推迟会议，这是优先动议，需要马上解决。但是同时又有人提出，家里着火这人压根就不是党员，不应该有开会的资格，会议应该在此人缺席的情况下继续进行，这就是偶发动议，也应当立即解决。这些都解决了之后再回到一开始的附属动议。</p> <h2 id="场与次休息与休会一些术语">场与次、休息与休会，一些术语</h2> <p><strong>“场”与“次”的区别</strong></p> <p>严格说来，“次”的内涵更大，包含了“场”，一次会议可以包含五场、十场会议。所谓一场会议，指组织成员在同一个场合正式集会以处理事务，会议需要连续进行，<em>除了短暂休息，成员不可解散离场</em>。所谓一次会议，指组织成员围绕既定的会议程序、议事日程、时间表或公开宣称的目标而开展的一场、或者连续若干场会议。</p> <p><strong>休息与休会</strong></p> <p>它们的区别在于效果：<em>休息结束后的会议直接从断点继续，如同没有休息一样</em>，没有任何开幕的步骤；<em>休会结束后的会议，一般先有开幕的程序，并且要宣读上一场会议纪要，然后从断点继续</em>。</p> <p><strong>关于会议类型的一些术语</strong></p> <p>会议类型包括例行会议、临时会议、后续会议、年度会议、闭门会 议、公开会议、电子会议等。以下详细解释。</p> <p>以下是关于不同类型会议的解释和示例：</p> <ul> <li>例行会议（Regular Meeting）。按照既定的时间表定期召开的会议，通常有固定的议程。例如，一个公司每月第一周的星期三举行的董事会议，讨论公司运营和财务情况。</li> <li>临时会议（Special Meeting）。为了讨论特定事项而特别召开的会议，通常不在常规会议时间表内。例如，公司因应突发市场变化，紧急召集董事会进行特别讨论。</li> <li>后续会议（Adjourned Meeting）。为了完成之前会议上未完成的议程，而在之后的某个时间继续举行的会议。例如，上周的社区会议因时间限制未能讨论完所有议题，所以本周召开后续会议继续讨论。</li> <li>年度会议（Annual Meeting）。通常每年举行一次的正式会议，用于回顾过去一年的工作并规划未来。例如，一家公司的年度股东大会，总结去年的业绩并讨论未来的战略。</li> <li>闭门会议（Executive Session）。仅限特定成员参加的私密会议，通常用于讨论敏感或保密的议题。例如，董事会就高级管理层的任命进行闭门讨论。</li> <li>公开会议（Open Meeting）。对公众开放的会议，任何人都可以参加旁听。例如，市政府就城市规划举行的公开会议，邀请市民参与讨论和提供反馈。</li> <li>电子会议（Electronic Meeting）。通过电话、视频会议或其他电子方式远程召开的会议。例如，一家跨国公司使用视频会议软件，召集位于不同国家的团队成员进行月度会议。</li> </ul> <h2 id="主动议言简意赅无歧义">主动议：言简意赅无歧义</h2> <p>主动议一旦得到通过，便将作为<em>会议的决定</em>被记录下来。因此，主动议的措辞应该言简意赅且无歧义。不应当包含有争议性，例如歧视类用语。用语要风格明确，与其说“动议不赞成公开发售基金”，不如直接说“动议反对公开发售基金”。</p> <p>一般而言，不要在动议当中说明动议的理由。有人可能赞成动议的行动，但是并不同意所陈述的理由，说得太多反而自找麻烦。如果确实需要说明动议的背景或缘由，可采用决议的形式，在“决定项”前加上“前言”，前言以“鉴于……”开头。比如：鉴于协会所指派的专家在调查后发现河边地带的低层写字楼普遍存在严重火灾隐患。因此决定，成立一个七人委员会，其中四位是……，另外三位由主持人指派，以起草本协会关于贯彻城市防火安全条例的措施，以及对该条例的修改建议。</p> <p>有些主动议不合规则，属于无效动议，应尽量避免。主动议不可与国家法律相冲突自不必言，而同一次会议当中，不应提出本质上与此前已经被否决的主动议内容相同的主动议；无论是不是在同一次会议当中，都不可提出与此前的决议冲突的主动议（若符合重议条件，则可例外）。对于“得到暂时处理”的主动议，只要还在会议处理的时限之内，则不可提出跟它们相似或相反的主动议，以免引起会议混乱。</p> <h2 id="七种附属动议的实操范例">七种附属动议的实操范例</h2> <p><strong>搁置</strong></p> <p>指会议根本不想对主动议做出决定，因为无论它得到通行，还是被 明确否决，都将造成不良后果，当搁置的动议通过，主动议即被忽略、 丢弃，就是说，不再处理，没有结论，而且在<em>本次会议期间不可重提</em>。</p> <p>例如，一家全州规模的专业协会的基层组织会议，面对一个主动议：“决定，本分部支持州协会主席杰姆斯·桑顿先生竞选国会参议员”，但是辩论陷入了棘手的境地，一方面成员尊敬自己的主席，另一方面认为他竞选参议员并不可取。如果直接否决该决议，则可能构成对主席的诋毁，而且无论表决结果如何，都会导致内部的分裂。于是出现了搁置：</p> <p>成员A（取得发言权）：我动议搁置（该决议）。（成员B，C附议）</p> <p>主持人：有人动议有人附议，搁置关于“支持桑顿主席竞选国会参议员”的决议。主持人请A先生发言……</p> <p>如果搁置最终没有通过，主持人宣布结果（不同意搁置）之后，还得继续讨论原决议。</p> <p><strong>修改</strong></p> <p>指在动议得到处理之前，修改它的措辞，甚至在一定程度上修改其含义，修改的内容称作“<em>修正案</em>”。这是所有附属动议当中使用<em>最广泛、最频繁</em>的一种。</p> <p>有些修正案不合规则，需要注意避免，如修正案必须切题，即必须与被修改的动议紧密相关，不能引入任何新议题，只能对原议题进行修改。如果修改后的动议等于在事实上否决了原来的动议，也属违规；如果修正案改变了动议的种类，如原来的动议是“将待决问题改期到下午两点”，修正案为“搁置该问题”，那么这个修正应当无效。</p> <p>举个例子。假设在一个学校董事会的会议上，一名成员提出了一个主动议：“我提议从下个学期开始，将每周的体育课程从两节增加到三节。”在讨论这个动议时，另一名成员可能认为增加的数量过多，因此提出修改动议：“我提议修改这个动议，将体育课程的增加量修改为每周增加一节，而不是两节。”这个修改动议需要得到至少一名其他成员的支持（second）。假设有另一名成员说：“我支持这个修改动议。”一旦修改动议得到支持，它就成为讨论的焦点。成员们会讨论这个修改动议，而不是原始的主动议。在充分讨论之后，会议主持人将指导成员对修改动议进行表决。如果修改动议通过，原始的主动议就被更改为：“我提议从下个学期开始，将每周的体育课程从两节增加到三节。”变为：“我提议从下个学期开始，将每周的体育课程从两节增加到两节半。”如果修改动议未通过，会议将继续讨论原始的未修改的主动议。无论修改动议是否通过，主动议都需要继续进行讨论，并最终进行表决。</p> <p><strong>委托</strong></p> <p>指把一个待决的动议交给专业小组（委员会）讨论，以便使问题得到更充分、详尽的考虑和研究，待讨论结果出炉，再交还会议，回归议事程序。主要有三种引申形式：进入全体委员会（Committee of the Whole）、进入准全体委员会（Quasi Committee of the Whole）、和非正式讨论（Informal Consideration）。下面是这三种形式的详细说明和例子：</p> <ol> <li>进入全体委员会（Committee of the Whole）。这是一种让整个会议以一种更自由的格式讨论某个议题的方式。在这种模式下，会议的正式主持人暂时退位，一般<em>由另一位成员担任全体委员会的主席</em>，以促进讨论的自由氛围，让前主持人不再有特殊的地位，以便会议从新的角度讨论问题。例如，在一次城市议会的会议中，议员们需要深入讨论一个复杂的城市规划项目。为了使讨论更加深入和灵活，议会决定进入全体委员会，此时主持人暂时退位，由另一名议员担任全体委员会主席，以便进行更自由的讨论。实际上，具体做法可以根据组织的实际情况和需求有所调整。在某些情况下，如果会议规模较小或原主持人被认为能够有效促进自由讨论，也可能不更换主持人。</li> <li>进入准全体委员会（Quasi Committee of the Whole）。与全体委员会类似，但主要区别在于主持人不改变。这种方式允许较为自由的讨论，同时保持一定的正式程度。例如，在一家公司的年度董事会议中，董事们决定对一项重大投资进行深入讨论。他们选择进入准全体委员会，由原会议主持人继续主持，但放宽了对发言次数和时长的限制，使讨论更加灵活。</li> <li>非正式讨论（Informal Consideration）。这是一种更加非正式的讨论方式，常用于较小的会议或组织。在这种模式下，放宽了对讨论的正式议事规则的限制，例如对发言次数的限制。例如，在一个社区协会的月度会议中，成员们希望就如何改善社区安全进行深入讨论。他们决定采用非正式讨论的方式，允许成员自由地表达观点，没有严格的发言次数限制。</li> </ol> <p><strong>改期</strong></p> <p>即推迟对当前待决议题的讨论。<em>必须指定什么时间可继续讨论</em>。改期不同于搁置，搁置的意图不在推迟，而是阻挠（kill）动议。</p> <p>例如，在一个非营利组织的董事会会议上，成员们正在讨论一个主动议，比如：“我提议在下个季度为社区中心购买新的电脑设备。”在讨论过程中，可能出现需要更多时间来收集有关电脑设备的信息，或者有关键成员缺席无法立即做出决策的情况。这时，一名成员可能会提出改期动议：“我提议将这个动议改期到下次会议上再讨论，以便我们有时间获取更多的报价信息。”这个改期动议需要得到至少一名其他成员的支持。得到支持后，会议将对该改期动议进行讨论。<em>讨论集中在改期的必要性和可行性上，而不是原始动议的内容</em>。讨论结束后，会议主持人将引导成员对改期动议进行表决。如果改期动议通过，原始关于购买电脑设备的动议将被推迟到下次会议或指定的未来时间；如果改期动议未通过，会议将继续讨论原始的未改期的主动议。</p> <p>无论改期动议是否通过，主动议都将根据改期动议的结果被相应处理，要么继续讨论，要么推迟到后续会议。</p> <p><strong>调整辩论限制</strong></p> <p>包括两种 方式，一是减少发言次数或缩短每次发言的时间，但不限制什么时候结束辩论；二是要求在未来某一时刻结束辩论，或者要求在指定的一段时间之后结束辩论，以提请表决。鉴于该方法会限制讨论的充分性，对决策不利，因此需要“三分之二表决”，且不可在委员会中使用。</p> <p>例如，如果要调整<em>发言的次数</em>或<em>每次发言的时间长度</em>，那么调整辩论限制的格式为：“我动议每次发言控制在5分钟之内”，或“我动议延长李先生的发言时间3分钟”。如果<em>要限制辩论的时间长度</em>，那么调整辩论限制的格式为：“我动议对这个修正案的辩论控制在20分钟之内。” 如果要指定结束辩论并开始表决的时刻，那么调整辩论限制的格式为：“我动议9点结束辩论并开始表决。</p> <p><strong>结束辩论（Move the Previous Question 或 Call for the Question）</strong></p> <p>调整辩论限制只能指定在未来某一时刻结束辩论，结束辩论则可立即结束辩论，此外不接受除暂停以外的任何附属动议。与调整辩论限制一样，结束辩论需要“三分之二表决”，且不可在委员会中使用。</p> <p>这个动议的目的是防止会议过度拖延，尤其是在讨论开始变得重复或偏离主题时。</p> <p>假设在一个社区委员会的会议上，成员们正在讨论一个关于是否在公园安装新的安全照明的主动议。在经过一段时间的讨论后，一些成员可能开始觉得讨论已经足够充分，或者讨论开始偏离主题。这时，一名成员可能会提出结束辩论的动议：“我提议结束辩论，并对当前关于公园安全照明的动议进行表决。”结束辩论的动议同样需要得到二次动议（second），即至少一名其他成员的支持。然后，不同于大多数其他动议，结束辩论的动议不进行讨论（毕竟提出该动议的原因一开始就是因为觉得辩论失去了意义），而是立即进行表决。如果结束辩论动议获得通过（通常需要超过三分之二的成员同意，有些情况下可能需要更高比例的支持），则立即结束当前动议的讨论，并进行表决。如果结束辩论动议未通过，讨论将继续进行。</p> <p>结束辩论动议在以下情况下特别重要：</p> <ul> <li>当讨论开始变得重复无新意时。</li> <li>当讨论偏离了主题或不再产生有价值的信息时。</li> <li>当时间有限且需要迅速做出决策时。</li> </ul> <p><strong>暂停（Recess）</strong></p> <p>指中断待决议题，以便立即响应其他事务。这是多数方的一种<em>隐形权力</em>，能够不经辩论便立即中断对一个动议的讨论，它可能会侵犯少数方与个体的权利，容易被滥用。鉴于此，议事规则规定，暂停只能用于应对突然出现的紧急事务，或者为了提前处理另一件更需要先处理的事务。</p> <p>“暂停动议”作为一种辅动议，可用于休息、处理紧急事务或进行非正式讨论。这种动议通常是针对会议当天内的短暂休息或中断，而非推迟会议到另一天。</p> <p>例如，假设在一个学校董事会的长时间会议中，成员们已经连续工作了数小时，正在讨论一个关于校园设施升级的复杂议题。随着会议进行，成员们可能开始感到疲劳，需要休息或处理个人事务。这时，一名成员可能会提出暂停动议：“我提议我们暂停会议10分钟，以便大家可以休息一下。”得到二次动议（second），即至少一名其他成员的支持后，会议主持人通常会立即对该动议进行表冠决。如果暂停动议获得通过，则会议将暂时中断，成员们可以休息或处理其他事务。如果暂停动议未通过，会议将继续进行，不进行休息。</p> <h3 id="动议的重要性">动议的重要性</h3> <p>暂停动议在以下情况下特别重要：</p> <ul> <li>当成员需要休息或恢复精力，以保持会议效率和成员注意力时。</li> <li>当需要处理突发事件或紧急情况，这些情况需要会议成员立即注意时。</li> <li>当会议进行了长时间而成员需要短暂的休息或餐点时。</li> </ul> <p>这个动议有助于保持会议成员的精神饱满和高效参与，确保会议能在良好的状态下进行。</p> <h2 id="五种优先动议">五种优先动议</h2> <p><strong>要求遵守议程（Call for the Orders of the Day）</strong></p> <p>成员可以要求会议遵守既定的日程、时间表或会议程序，或者要求立即处理指定在此时此刻的普通议程或特别议程。“要求遵守议程”是作为辅动议的一种，用于确保会议按照预定的议程顺序进行。当会议偏离了原定议程，或当某些成员希望会议返回到预定议程上时，可以使用这个动议。</p> <p>设想在一个公司的董事会议上，会议原定有一个详细的议程安排，包括多个关键议题按特定顺序讨论。假设在会议进行中，讨论开始偏离预定议程，或者某些成员试图引入不在议程上的新议题，导致原定的重要议题被忽视。这时，一名成员可能会提出“要求遵守议程”动议：“我要求遵守议程，返回到今天会议安排的第三项议题”。“要求遵守议程”动议一般<em>不需要二次动议</em>（second），并且不进行讨论。会议主持人应立即对此动议进行表决。如果动议通过，则会议必须立即返回到预定的议程上讨论对应的议题。如果动议未通过，会议可以继续当前的讨论或处理其他议题。</p> <p>“要求遵守议程”动议在以下情况下特别重要：</p> <ul> <li>当会议开始偏离预定议程，而这可能导致重要议题未能得到及时或适当的讨论时。</li> <li>当会议时间有限，需要确保所有预定议题都能被讨论到时。</li> <li>当某些议题具有优先级或法律要求必须遵守特定顺序时。</li> </ul> <p>这个动议有助于确保会议的有序性和效率，确保所有计划的议题都能按顺序得到妥善处理。</p> <p><strong>提出权益问题（Raise a Point of Order）</strong></p> <p>指会议组织及其成员出现了一些特殊情况，这些情况涉及会议或成员的基本权益，或者重要，或者紧急，急需给予考虑和解决。权益问题由成员提出，主持人裁定，无须表决，除非主持人的裁定遭到申诉。这也体现了主持人的权力。”提出权益问题”用于指出会议进行过程中的程序错误或违反议事规则的情况。当会议成员认为会议的某个方面违反了会议规则或常规议事程序时，他们可以提出权益问题，以纠正这种情况。</p> <p>权益问题分作两类：</p> <ol> <li>关系到会议<em>整体的</em>基本权益，如涉及组织的安全和保密问题，或者会场环境如取暖、通风、光线出现问题，或者官员、雇员或嘉宾出现了有损会议利益的行为；</li> <li>关系到<em>个人</em>基本权益，如在某位成员未出席的情况之下通过了一份会议纪要，然而这份会议纪要对上次会议该成员出席情况记录有误，或者出现了对某位成员的不当指控等。如果这两类问题发生冲突，<em>会议的权益问题优先于个人的权益问题</em>。</li> </ol> <p>假设在一个社团的会员大会上，成员们正在讨论一项有争议的议题。在讨论过程中，如果会议主持人未能正确执行会议规则（如<em>允许某成员超时发言</em>或未遵守发言顺序），一名会议成员可能会提出权益问题：“我提出权益问题，会议规则规定每位成员的发言时间不得超过两分钟。”提出权益问题<em>不需要二次动议</em>（second），并且应该立即被会议主持人处理。主持人需要就提出的问题做出判断，确定是否确实存在程序上的错误或违规。如果主持人认为提出的权益问题成立，他们将采取措施纠正程序错误，比如重新调整发言顺序或限制发言时间。如果主持人判断权益问题不成立，可以解释为什么当前的做法是合规的。成员如果对主持人的判断不满意，可以提出<em>上诉动议（Appeal）</em>，由全体成员表决是否接受主持人的判断。</p> <p>“提出权益问题”动议在以下情况下特别重要：</p> <ul> <li>确保会议遵循既定的议事规则和程序。</li> <li>保障会议成员的权利和议事的公平性。</li> <li>促进会议的有效和有序进行。</li> </ul> <p>这个动议是一个关键的工具，用于确保会议遵守规则和程序，维护会议的正当性和效率。</p> <p><strong>休息（Recess）</strong></p> <p>“休息”动议用于临时中断会议的进行。它允许参与者在会议期间进行短暂的休息，这通常用于长时间的会议中，以便成员休息、私下讨论或处理紧急事务。如果会议日程或时间表中安排了休息时间，待时间一到，无须动议，主持人即可直接宣布会议休息；如果主持人没有这么做，任何成员都可要求遵守议程。</p> <p>比如，在一次持续了几个小时的组织年会上，参与者可能需要休息、用餐或处理个人事务。在会议进行一段时间后，任何成员都可以提出”休息”动议。例如，一名成员可能会说：”我提议我们现在休息十分钟”。”休息”动议通常需要得到至少一名其他成员的支持（second）。一旦得到支持，会议主持人会对该动议进行表决。如果表决通过，会议将暂时休息，成员们可以离开会议室。如果动议未通过，会议将继续进行。</p> <p>休息动议的主要作用有：</p> <ul> <li>提高效率：定期休息有助于保持会议参与者的精神集中和效率。</li> <li>处理紧急事务：允许参与者处理会议期间可能出现的紧急事务。</li> <li>促进非正式讨论：休息期间，成员们可以进行非正式的交流和讨论，有助于促进思维碰撞和共识形成。</li> </ul> <p><strong>休会（Adjourn）</strong></p> <p>指在<em>已知下次会议何时召开的前提之下</em>，立刻结束本次会议。”休会”动议是一种常见的辅动议，用于结束当前会议的所有正式议程，将会议正式关闭。与”休息”动议（Recess）不同，”休会”动议标志着会议的完全结束，而不是暂时中断。</p> <p>例如，在一个社团的月度会议上，所有的议程项目已经讨论完毕。任何成员都可以在合适的时候提出”休会”动议。比如，一名成员可能会说：”我提议休会。”得到支持后，会议主持人会立即对该动议进行表决，无需讨论。如果表决通过，会议立即结束。如果动议未通过，会议将继续处理剩余的议程或讨论。</p> <p>休会可以保证会议按照正式程序结束，所有议程得到妥善处理；可以帮助控制会议的总体时间，避免无休止的讨论；也为会议参与者提供一个清晰的结束信号，确保所有人都知道会议已经结束。</p> <p><strong>指定后续会议的时间（Fix the Time to Which to Adjourn）</strong></p> <p>用于确定下一次会议的具体时间和日期，尤其是在当前会议即将结束，但下次会议的时间尚未确定的情况下。</p> <p>假设在一个志愿者组织的会议中，成员们正在讨论完接下来的活动计划，但意识到当前会议时间不足以完成所有的议程。在会议接近尾声但仍有重要议题未决时，一名成员可以提出”制定下次会议时间”动议。例如，该成员可能会说：”我提议我们将下一次会议定在下周三下午三点。”“制定下次会议时间”动议通常需要得到至少一名其他成员的支持（second）。得到支持后，会议主持人会对该动议进行表冠决。如果表决通过，下一次会议的时间和日期就按动议中提出的时间确定。如果动议未通过，可能需要重新提议一个不同的时间，或者在会议后通过其他方式确定下次会议时间。</p> <h2 id="偶发动议">偶发动议</h2> <p><strong>程序问题（Point of Order）</strong></p> <p>任何成员，只要认为有违反规则的现象发生，都可提出程序问题，要求主持人裁定并纠正，无须主持人</p> <p>成员A：我要提出程序问题。（或者直接说“程序问题！”） <em>正在发言的成员就座</em>。主持人则请成员A指出哪道程序出现了问 题，或者发言人哪些话违规。准许而发言。</p> <p>又例如，在一个社团的年会上，成员们正在讨论重要的决策事项。如果在讨论过程中，会议主持人未正确遵循议事规则（例如允许某个成员连续发言而不给其他人机会），任何成员都可以提出程序问题动议。例如，该成员可能会说：”我提出程序问题，我们的议事规则规定每位成员在同一议题上只能发言一次。”提出程序问题动议不需要二次动议（second），并且应由会议主持人立即处理。主持人需要判断提出的问题是否成立，并相应地采取措施。如果主持人认为程序问题成立，他们将采取措施纠正程序错误。如果主持人认为程序问题不成立，他们将解释为什么当前的做法是适当的。</p> <p><strong>申诉</strong></p> <p>申诉主要针对主持人而发。通过选举，成员把自己的部分权力与责任，特别是根据议事规则进行裁定的权力与责任，委托给主持人，同时，<em>成员必须保留收回这种授权的手段</em>，这个手段就是申诉。任何两个成员，一个动议，一个附议，便可以把裁定权从主持人手中收回，交还整个会议。</p> <p>只要是主持人做出的裁定，成员都可提出申诉。然后由主持人准确描述当前争议的问题，必要的话还可以阐述自己裁定的理由，宣布议题，提请表决。</p> <p><strong>暂缓规则（Suspend the Rules）</strong></p> <p>暂缓规则用于临时搁置或修改会议的一些特定<em>规则</em>，以便处理特殊情况或加快议程的进程。这种动议通常用于暂时放弃那些阻碍会议进行的正规程序规则，但它<em>不能用来暂停那些受到组织宪章、法律、或其他不可变规定所保护的规则</em>。</p> <p>例如，在一个俱乐部的例会中，成员们想要快速通过一个常规但非争议性的议题，以便有更多时间讨论另一个紧急且重要的议题。一个成员可能会提出”暂缓规则”动议：“我提议暂缓关于每项议题至少讨论10分钟的规则，以便我们可以快速通过当前的议题。<em>暂缓规则动议通常需要得到较高比例的支持</em>，如二分之三多数同意。这个动议不需要二次动议（second），并且应由会议主持人立即对其进行表决。如果表决通过，会议中的特定规则将暂时被搁置，以适应当前的特殊需求。如果动议未通过，会议将继续按照原有规则进行。</p> <p>暂缓规则动议提供了在特殊情况下调整会议流程的灵活性。有助于会议在必要时快速处理某些议题，特别是在时间紧迫或议题简单明了的情况下。同时也允许会议在不常见的或紧急情况下适当调整规则，以更好地满足会议目的。</p> <p><strong>反对考虑（Objection to the Consideration of a Question）</strong></p> <p>如果会议认为根本不应该或不值得对某个实质主动议进行讨论，则可提出反对考虑，直接阻挠。这个动议通常在议题刚被提出时使用，用于表达对讨论该议题的强烈反对，通常是因为议题被认为是不适当、冒犯性或与会议目的无关。</p> <p>比如，在一个组织的会议上，一个成员提出了一个可能引起争议或被认为不适当的议题。另一个成员可能立即提出“反对考虑”动议，例如说：“我反对考虑这个问题。”这个动议不需要二次动议（second），并且应立即进行表决。此类动议通常不进行讨论。如果大多数成员投票支持“反对考虑”，则该议题将不会被讨论或表决。如果大多数成员投票反对或动议未获得足够支持，则会议将继续讨论该议题。</p> <p>“反对考虑”动议是一种有效的工具，用于确保会议的顺利进行，防止不必要或不适当的讨论，保护会议的有效性和专业性。</p> <p><strong>拆分议题（Division of a Question）</strong></p> <p>如果一个动议，虽然关于同一主题，却包含若干部分，而且每一部分都可作为一个动议，那么可以将它们分开考虑并分别表决。拆分议题用于将复杂或多部分组成的主动议拆分为几个独立的议题，以便分别进行讨论和表决。这种动议适用于当原始动议包含多个相互独立且需要单独决策的部分时。</p> <p>例如，在一个组织的会议上，一个成员提出了一个包含多个部分的复杂动议，如“我提议我们增加预算用于购买新的办公设备，并且调整工作时间。”另一个成员可能觉得这些议题应该分别讨论和决定，因此提出“拆分议题”动议：“我提议将这个动议拆分为两部分：一部分关于增加预算购买办公设备，另一部分关于调整工作时间”。”拆分议题”动议通常需要得到至少一名其他成员的支持（second）。得到支持后，会议主持人会对该动议进行表决。如果表决通过，原始动议就被拆分成几部分，每部分将分别进行讨论和表决。如果动议未通过，原始的复合动议将作为一个整体继续进行讨论和表决。</p> <p>动议有助于使会议对复杂议题的讨论更加清晰和专注，保证会议能够对每个部分的议题进行充分和细致的审查，同时使会议成员能够对每个独立的议题作出更明确的决策，增加决策的透明度和成员的参与度。</p> <p><strong>逐段或逐条讨论（Consider by Paragraph or Seriatim）</strong></p> <p>一个篇幅较长的动议，可能会包含系列决议、段落或章节，它们事关一个主题，不可拆分，但是可以逐一对每个部分展开辩论与修改，如果主持人没有主动采取这样的处理方式，成员则可提出逐段讨论或逐条讨论。不过，如果一份文件所包含的主动议分别涉及不同主题，那么只要有一位成员反对，便不能逐段或逐条讨论，只能拆分议题。</p> <p>比如，在一个组织的年度大会上，需要审议和修改该组织的章程或一份长期规划文件。主持人或会议成员可以提议按照章程或文件的结构逐段（或逐条、逐项）进行讨论。通常，这不需要正式的动议，但可以通过动议来建议这种讨论方式。在逐段讨论的过程中，会议将集中于文本的一个特定段落或条款。对每个部分的讨论完成后，再移至下一个部分，直至整个文本讨论完毕。每个部分可以分别进行修改和表决，或在整个文本讨论完后，对所有提出的修改进行统一表决。</p> <p>逐段或逐条讨论有助于使对复杂文档的审查更有组织和系统性，确保每个部分都得到适当的注意和考虑，避免遗漏或忽视重要细节，同时使会议成员能够对文档的每个部分发表意见，增加整个过程的透明度和参与性。</p> <p><strong>起立重新表决（Division of the Assembly）</strong></p> <p>如果刚刚完成的表决采用的是口头表决，或是未予计数的举手表 决，那么任何成员都有权质疑表决结果，提出起立重新表决。重要的是，当一个成员要求进行起立表决时，这个请求<em>不需要二次动议（second）</em>。一旦提出，会议主持人应立即采取行动来进行起立表决，除非显然是为了延误会议而提出的无效请求。起立表决可以清楚地展示支持和反对的比例，因为它要求成员通过站立的方式来表示他们的投票意向。</p> <p><strong>关于表决方式的动议（Motion Regarding Voting Method）</strong></p> <p>关于表决方式的动议用于确定或改变某个具体议题的表决方式。这种动议允许会议成员提议采用特定的表决方法，如无记名投票、计数投票、举手投票或口头投票等，来替代或修改会议默认的表决方式。</p> <p>例如，在一个社团的年会上，成员们需要决定是否接受一项关于财务支出的提案。如果某个成员希望确保表决结果的准确性和透明性，他们可能会提出关于表决方式的动议：“我提议我们对这个财务支出提案进行无记名投票。”这种动议通常需要得到至少一名其他成员的支持（second）。得到支持后，会议主持人会对该动议进行表决。如果表决通过，那么接下来对提案的表决将采用提议的表决方法。如果动议未通过，会议将继续使用默认或之前决定的表决方式。</p> <p><strong>关于提名的动议</strong></p> <p>这种动议通常出现在需要选举官员或委员会成员时，可以用来开启、关闭提名过程，或修改提名程序。</p> <p>比如，在一个组织的年度选举会议上，成员们需要选举新的董事会成员。成员可能提出与提名过程相关的不同动议，例如：</p> <ul> <li>开始提名：一名成员可能提出动议：“我提议开始对董事会成员职位的提名。”</li> <li>关闭提名：在一定时间或所有意愿成员都被提名后，成员可能提出：“我提议关闭董事会成员的提名。”</li> <li>修改提名程序：有时也可能提出修改提名过程的动议，如提议采用无记名提名方式或提议提名时需有特定的支持者数量。</li> </ul> <p>这些动议通常需要得到至少一名其他成员的支持（second）。得到支持后，会议主持人会对该动议进行表冠决。如果表决通过，提名过程将按照提议的方式进行。如果动议未通过，则继续使用原有的提名方式或过程。</p> <p><strong>请求免责（Request for Excuse）</strong></p> <p>请求免责通常指的是会议成员就某项职责、任务或会议出席要求提出的正式请求，以获得免除或推迟履行这些职责的许可。这种请求可能是由于各种原因，如个人紧急事务、健康问题或其他无法控制的情况。</p> <p>例如，在一个董事会会议上，一名成员可能因为个人健康问题或紧急家庭情况，无法履行其作为董事的职责。该成员或另一名代表他的成员可以在会议上提出请求免责：“由于个人健康原因，我请求被免除下月的董事会职责。”这种请求通常会被会议主持人带到会议上进行讨论，可能需要进行表决决定是否批准该请求。如果会议成员同意该请求，该成员将被免除相关职责，直至他们能够恢复履行职责；如果请求未被批准，该成员仍需尽力履行其职责。</p> <p>请求免责提供了一种机制，允许成员在特殊情况下获得必要的灵活性，同时确保组织的工作不会因个别成员的特殊情况而受到不必要的干扰。通过在会议上公开讨论这些请求，增加了组织运作的透明度。请求免责有助于在<em>尊重个人情况</em>和<em>维护组织整体利益</em>之间找到平衡。</p> <p><strong>请求和咨询（Request and Inquiry）</strong></p> <p>通常指的是会议成员提出的关于会议程序、议事规则、议题内容或与会议相关的其他问题的正式请求或询问。这些请求和咨询旨在帮助成员更好地理解和参与会议过程，确保会议的顺利进行。成员可能不确定会议的某个程序如何操作，比如如何提出动议或动议的具体含义。成员可能问：“我可以在这个时候提出修改动议吗？”或“这个程序动议是指什么？”</p> <p>例如，成员可能对正在讨论的议题内容或背景需要更多的信息。成员可能问：“我们讨论的预算提案包括哪些主要项目？”或“此前的决议对当前讨论有何影响？”</p> <p>在会议中，这些请求和咨询通常由会议主持人或有相关知识的成员回答。主持人可能需要参考会议的规则手册、先前的决议或其他文档来提供准确的回答。对于复杂或特殊的问题，主持人可能建议暂停会议，以便进行更深入的研究或咨询。</p> <h2 id="再议类动议incidental-motions">再议类动议（Incidental Motions）</h2> <p>这一类动议可以让动议原地复活，死而复生。</p> <p><strong>恢复（reconsider）</strong></p> <p>其意图在于把暂停的动议或绑定在一起的系列动议重新提交给会议，作为待决动议来讨论。被暂停的动议始终处于暂停状态，可以在本次会议期间恢复；如果与下一次例行会议的时间间隔没有超过三个月，除了在本次会议期间，还可在下一次会议期间恢复。如果在上述时间范围之内都没有被恢复，那么暂停的动议自动失效，不再处于暂停状态，不过可以作为新动议重提。</p> <p>恢复动议允许会议成员提出重新考虑之前已经做出的决定。通常，”恢复”动议用于重新审议一个已经投票决定的议题，特别是如果有新信息出现，或者有人认为先前的决定需要重新评估。</p> <p>例如，在一个董事会的会议中，成员们可能已经对一个重要议题进行了投票，比如批准一项新的投资计划。如果在投票后出现了新的信息，或者有成员认为需要重新考虑之前的决定，他们可以提出”恢复”动议：“我提议重新考虑我们关于新投资计划的决定”。”恢复”动议通常需要由在原始表决中投了赞成票的成员提出，并且需要得到至少一名其他成员的支持（second）。之后，会议主持人会将该动议带到会议上进行表决。如果表决通过，原来的决定将被暂停，会议将重新对该议题进行讨论和表决。如果动议未通过，原先的决定将继续有效。</p> <p><strong>取消或修改已经通过的决议（Rescind or Amend Something Previously Adopted）</strong></p> <p>该动议用于改变或撤销之前会议上已经作出的决策，允许一个组织回过头来改变或取消先前做出的正式决定，这通常是基于情况的变化、新的信息或成员对原决定的重新考虑。</p> <p>例如，一个社团在几个月前的会议上通过了一项关于增加会费的决议。随着时间的推移，如果一些成员认为增加会费是不必要或不合适的，他们可以提出一个取消或修改该决议的动议：“我提议取消我们之前关于增加会费的决议。”或者“我提议修改我们关于增加会费的决议，将增幅调整为更低。”这类动议<em>通常需要得到较高比例的支持</em>，比如二分之三多数的同意。它需要得到至少一名其他成员的支持（second），然后在会议上进行表决。如果表决通过，原先的决议将被取消或按照新的提议进行修改。如果动议未通过，原先的决议将继续保持有效。</p> <p>总的来说，“取消或修改已经通过的决议”动议是一种重要的议事工具，用于确保组织的决策能够及时反映最新的情况和成员的共识。</p> <p><strong>收回动议（Withdraw a Motion）</strong></p> <p>收回委托指的是提议者<em>在动议还未被会议正式采纳或拒绝之前</em>，请求撤回他们所提出的动议。这通常发生在动议被正式讨论之前，但也可以在讨论过程中提出，只要尚未进行最终表决。</p> <p>比如，在一个组织的会议中，一名成员提出了关于更改会议时间的动议。在动议被讨论之前或讨论过程中，如果提议者发现了新信息，或者认为他们的动议不再合适或有争议，他们可以提出要收回他们的动议：“我请求撤回我关于更改会议时间的动议。”在动议被讨论之前，提议者可以单方面撤回动议。如果动议已经被讨论，通常需要得到会议的同意才能撤回。如果动议被允许撤回，那么该动议就好像从未提出过一样，会议将继续处理其他议题。</p> <p><strong>重议（Reconsider）</strong></p> <p>即把一个已经表决过的动议拿回来重新展开辩论和表决。其意图在于及时纠正那些草率的、被误导的或者本质上错误的决定。因为重议容易造成会议效率低下，所以有极严格的限制。一是重议的主体，必须是参与表决的多数方；二是重议的时间：如果是长度只有一天的一次会议，那么重议只能在被重议的动议表决当天提出；如果是长度超过一天的一次会议，那么提出重议的时间可以延长到下一个会议日。</p> <p>例如，在一个董事会会议中，成员们可能已经对一项重要的投资提案进行了表决。如果在表决后出现了新的信息，或者有成员认为需要重新考虑之前的决定，他们可以提出“重议”动议：“我提议重新考虑我们关于投资提案的决定。”重议”动议通常需要由原始表决中投了赞成票的成员提出，并且需要得到至少一名其他成员的支持（second）。之后，会议主持人会将该动议带到会议上进行表决。如果表决通过，原来的决定将被暂停，会议将重新对该议题进行讨论和表冠决。如果动议未通过，原先的决定将继续保持有效。</p> <p>总的来说，“重议”动议是一种重要的议事工具，用于确保会议决策能够在必要时进行适时的修正或重新评估。</p> <h2 id="一事一议原则">一事一议原则</h2> <p>一事一议原则（One Subject at a Time Rule）要求<em>在任何时候，会议只能讨论一个议题</em>，直到处理完毕后才能转移到下一个议题。这有助于确保会议的有序和高效，防止议题间的混淆和不必要的混乱。</p> <p>具体来说，一事一议原则意味着：</p> <ol> <li> <p>议题专注性：当一个动议（motion）被提出并处于讨论阶段时，所有的讨论必须仅限于这个动议的内容。不允许引入与当前动议无关的新议题或其他动议。</p> </li> <li> <p>动议处理完整性：在当前动议得到充分讨论并最终表决（通过或否决）之前，不得开始讨论另一个动议或议题。</p> </li> <li> <p>排他性：如果某个动议需要时间来决定或需要进一步信息，可以将其搁置，但在处理这个动议的过程中，不能同时讨论其他动议。</p> </li> </ol> <p>例如，假设在一个组织的会议上，有成员提出了关于增加年度预算的动议。根据一事一议原则，讨论必须集中在这个预算增加的议题上，直到决定是否接受或拒绝这个动议。在此期间，不可以将讨论转移到其他议题，如更改会议时间或引入新的活动计划，除非当前议题被正式解决或搁置。</p> <p>这个原则有助于保持会议的焦点，确保每个议题都得到适当的关注和处理。</p> <h2 id="动议的重提和不良动议">动议的重提和不良动议</h2> <p>一般而言，同一次会议之上，相同的或者本质上相同的动议，不得重复出现，除非使用再议类动议，如取消或修改已经通过的决定，或重 议。但是，按照前述规则本来不可重提的动议，如果措辞经过相当程度的修改，或者影响动议的环境条件发生了显著的变化，以至这个动议变成了一个新问题，则可重提。对于动议的重提，还得补充两点：第一，已经收回的动议，等于从未被提出，则不存在重提的限制，或者说随时可以重提；第二，如果一个主动议在本次会议提出之后未能得到通过，那么可以在此后任何一次会议重提。关于不良动议，我们已经谈过无效动议，这里再说故意拖延的情 形。所谓故意拖延性质的动议，指那些妨碍、阻挠会议整体意志的动议。任何在本质上不严肃、无意义、没有提出任何实质建议、荒谬的动议，都属于故意拖延，不应被引入。举例来讲，如不断对主持人的裁定提出申诉；在所有人都参与表决且结果明显的情况之下，要求起立重新表决，皆属故意拖延。</p> <h2 id="法定人数quorum">法定人数（Quorum）</h2> <p>所谓法定人数，指按照议事规则，<em>会议召开所必须满足的成员出席人数</em>（出席并在场的人数，而非表决之时参与投票的人数）。对此，一般在<em>组织章程</em>之中都该有所规定。若无规定，那么根据通用议事规则，对法定人数有默认：对于公众集会，出席人数即法定人数；对于代表大会，法定人数则是实际报到人数的过半数。</p> <p>法定人数确保了会议和所作决策的合法性。如果会议没有达到法定人数，那么会议所作的任何决定都可能是无效的。通过确保有足够的成员出席，法定人数帮助避免少数人做出可能影响整个组织的重要决策。在任何正式会议开始之前，通常会有一个确定是否达到法定人数的过程，以确保会议可以有效且合法地进行。若不满足法定人数条件，主持人可以适当等待；若等待一段时间之后依然没有希望满足法定人数，那么主持人仍可宣布会议开始，并立即宣布法定人数不足，然后建议成员采取一定行动，或者受理一个<em>休会动议</em>。</p> <p>在诸如立法机构这样有权强制成员出席会议的组织当中，有一种叫作<em>强制出席</em>的动议，可以用来实现法定人数的满足。请注意，<em>强制出席只适用于像立法机构这样的组织，而不适用于自愿性组织</em>。</p> <h2 id="会议程序">会议程序</h2> <p>标准会议程序分作基本程序与<em>可选标题</em>。所谓基本程序一般包括六项：宣读并批准会议纪要，官员报告、 董事会报告、常设委员会报告，临时委员会报告，特别议程，未完事务和普通议程，新事务。可选标题包括：开幕仪式或典礼，点名，快速处理列表，自由评论，声明，节目等。</p> <p>《罗伯特议事规则》提供了一套详细的会议程序指南，旨在使正式会议有序、高效地进行。以下是按照这些规则进行的典型会议流程：</p> <ol> <li>开会（Call to Order）。主持人宣布会议开始，确保会议在预定时间正式启动。</li> <li>确定法定人数（Determine a Quorum）。在会议开始之前，确认是否有足够的成员出席以满足法定人数的要求，从而确保会议的决策有效。</li> <li>审阅并批准议程（Review and Approve the Agenda）。主持人或秘书宣读会议议程，成员们可以提议对议程进行修改或补充，然后对最终议程进行表决批准。</li> <li>审阅并批准上次会议记录（Reading and Approval of Minutes）。秘书宣读上一次会议的记录，成员们有机会提出更正或修改，然后记录被正式批准。</li> <li>报告（Reports）。包括（1） 官员报告：董事长、财务官员等官员可能会提供更新或报告。（2）委员会报告：各委员会负责人报告他们的工作进展或成果等。</li> <li>未完成的业务（Unfinished Business）。处理上次会议遗留下来的或未完成的事务。</li> <li>新业务（New Business）。成员提出新的议题或动议进行讨论和表决。这些议题通常在会议开始前列入议程，但也可能在会议中提出。</li> <li>宣布（Announcements）。通知成员即将到来的活动、会议或重要日期。</li> <li>公开论坛（Open Forum）。在某些会议中，可能会有一个时间段供成员自由讨论或提出关切。</li> <li>休会（Adjournment）。会议主持人提出休会动议，一旦获得批准，会议正式结束。</li> </ol> <p>例如，在一个社区协会的月度会议中，主持人会按照上述步骤组织会议，确保所有的行政事务（如审批记录和报告）得到处理，并且提供一个平台供成员讨论新的提案或计划，并对它们进行表决。公开论坛可能被用来讨论社区的关切或即将发生的事件。</p> <h2 id="发言与辩论如何有效率有礼貌地争吵">发言与辩论：如何有效率有礼貌地争吵</h2> <p>在哪种情形之下，可以打断他人的发言？一般而言，在成员取得发言权并且开始发言之后，任何人，包括主持人，都不得随意打断他的发言，除非发言人的言行出现程序问题，如发言时间超出规定等。而一些特殊情况下，则可以如此，这些情形包括：提出要求遵守议程（因为出现了未遵守议程的情况），提出权益问题，提出程序问题，提出拆分议题，提出请求或咨询，提出申诉，提出反对考虑，提出起立重新表决等。</p> <p>再说辩论。辩论之时，常常出现发言人滔滔不绝、罗里吧嗦，甚至不知所云的情况。议事规则之为规则，要义之一，即在于对这些弊病的防范。如果会议组织没有制定特别议事规则，那么依通用议事规则，每次辩论发言的最长时间则为10分钟；<em>同一天内，对同一问题，同一成员的发言不能超过两次</em>。当然，可以有所变通，如主持人认为，假如宽延一分钟，发言人结束发言能够更加体面，那则不妨延长。</p> <p>辩论之时，要求切题、严禁攻击其他成员的动机、<em>所有辩论必须通过主持人</em>、避免称呼成员的姓名、禁止对已经做出的决定发表反面意见、<em>禁止对自己提出的动议发表反面意见</em>、<em>朗读文件需要会议批准</em>、<em>成员被主持人打断后就座</em>、禁止扰乱会场等。</p> <p>关于辩论，还有一点要补充：主持人作为组织成员，同样享有辩论权，不过，基于主持人角色的中立性，<em>他在会议期间则不得行使辩论权</em>，尤其在一些大型会议之上，主持人不能对待决议题的是非利弊发表任何意见，以免左右他人；必要之时，他的确可以参加辩论，只是在此之前，他得让出主持人之位，等到当前待决议题得到处理之后，才能恢复他的主持人职务</p> <h2 id="表决">表决</h2> <p>第一个要点是<em>表决额度</em>（Voting Thresholds），即“决定表决结果的底线”。除 了“过半数表决”和“三分之二表决”，还有<em>相对多数表决</em>，一般发生在有三个或三个以上竞争者的情况之下。此外，一般而言主持人也有表决权，如果采用的表决方式是“书面不记名表决”，那么主持人跟其他成员一样参与投票；如果采用其他表决方式，主持人这一票可能影响最终结局，他可以选择参与表决，也可以放弃。</p> <p>关于表决额度的种类主要有以下几种。</p> <ol> <li> <p>简单多数（Simple Majority）。即超过半数的投票。这是最常见的表决额度。用于大多数标准决策，如常规动议的通过。例如，在年会上，成员对是否增加年度活动预算进行表决。如果赞成票超过<em>出席成员的一半</em>，该提案通过。</p> </li> <li> <p>绝对多数（Absolute Majority）。即超过所有成员总数一半的投票。较少使用，适用于更重要或敏感的决策。例如组织修改章程时可能要求绝对多数表决，即赞成票需要超过<em>所有成员总数的一半</em>。</p> </li> <li> <p>三分之二多数（Two-thirds Majority）。要求至少三分之二的赞成票。多用于更重要的决策，特别是那些可能限制成员权利或需要更大共识的决定。例如，要取消或修改已通过的决议，或在会议中暂缓执行某项规则，通常需要三分之二多数的赞成票。</p> </li> <li> <p>固定数字或比例（Fixed Number or Proportion）。即规定了具体的数字或比例，而不是基于出席成员的比例。适用于特定情况，可能是由法律或组织的章程特别规定的。例如，某些组织可能规定，更改组织的主要政策或结构至少需要80%的赞成票。</p> </li> <li> <p>一致同意（Unanimous Consent）。要求所有出席成员的一致赞成。适用于那些需要完全一致同意的决策。例如，在非常敏感或重大的决策，如特殊荣誉的授予，可能要求一致同意。</p> </li> </ol> <hr/> <p>第二个要点是表决方式。主要有以下几种常见的表决方式。</p> <ol> <li> <p>口头表决（Voice Vote）。成员通过说“赞成”（aye）或“反对”（no）来表达他们的投票意见。例如，在社区会议上，主持人提出：“所有支持建设新公园的，请说‘赞成’；反对的，请说‘反对’。”会议成员随后大声表达他们的选择。</p> </li> <li> <p>举手表决（Show of Hands）。成员通过举手表示赞成或反对。如，董事会讨论是否批准新的预算案时，主持人说：“支持这个预算案的，请举手。”成员们随后举手表示支持或反对。</p> </li> <li> <p>站立表决（Standing Vote）。类似于举手表决，但要求成员站立以表示赞成或反对。例如，在一个年会上，为了更清楚地计数，主持人可能要求：“所有赞成新会员政策的，请站立。”</p> </li> <li> <p>无记名投票（Secret Ballot）。要求成员在选票上私下标记他们的选择，然后进行计数。例如，选举组织领导时，可能采用无记名投票以确保投票的隐私和客观性。</p> </li> <li> <p>逐点表决（Roll Call Vote）。即按照名单顺序呼叫每个成员的名字，成员在被叫到时公开表达他们的投票意见。例如，在一项重要且可能有争议的决议上，为了确保记录每个人的投票，会进行逐点表决。</p> </li> <li> <p>通行表决（General Consent）。对于没有争议的议题，主持人会提议如果没有反对意见，就认为议题通过。例如，主持人可能说：“如果没有人反对，我们就认为关于会议时间变更的提案通过了。”</p> </li> </ol> <p>每种表决方式都有其适用场景，选择合适的表决方式取决于议题的性质、所需的投票隐私程度和会议的具体要求。</p> <hr/> <p><strong>表决的权利和义务</strong></p> <p>对于拖欠会费的成员，只要未予除名、未被处分而暂停表决权，他便可以参与表决；表决适用一人一票原则，成员可以弃权；表决适用<em>回避原则</em>，如成员与待决议题有直接利害关系，他应该回避，不过这一点并不具备强制性。</p> <h2 id="提名与选举">提名与选举</h2> <p>提名和选举是选举官员或委员会成员的正式过程。</p> <p><strong>提名过程</strong></p> <ol> <li> <p>开放提名：会议可以允许会议上的任何成员提出提名。通常，主持人会询问是否有提名。例如，在社区协会的年度选举中，主持人询问：“是否有人要提名今年的协会主席？”成员们可以自由提出候选人的名字。</p> </li> <li> <p>提名委员会：某些情况下，可能有一个专门的提名委员会负责提出候选人的提名。例如，在公司董事会选举中，提名委员会提前准备了一份候选人名单，并在会议上宣布。</p> </li> <li> <p>自我提名：成员有时也可以自我提名。例如，在一个俱乐部的选举中，一名成员站起来说：“我想自我提名参加秘书的角色。”</p> </li> </ol> <p><strong>选举过程</strong></p> <ol> <li> <p>表决方式：选举通常通过无记名投票进行，尤其是在竞争性选举中。也可以通过举手或口头表决，如果没有反对。例如，在社区协会选举中，如果只有一个候选人，主持人可能会建议：“如果没有反对，我们将通过一致同意来选举这位候选人。”</p> </li> <li> <p>多轮投票：如果在首轮投票中没有候选人获得必要的多数票，可能需要进行多轮投票。例如，在董事会选举中，如果第一轮投票没有候选人获得超过一半的票数，就需要进行第二轮投票。</p> </li> <li> <p>选举结果：选举的结果根据获得多数票的候选人来确定。如果规定了特定的多数额度（如绝对多数），则必须达到该额度。例如，在学校董事会的选举中，候选人必须获得所有投票的三分之二才能当选。</p> </li> </ol> <h2 id="官员会议纪要和官员报告切不可有官架子">官员、会议纪要和官员报告：切不可有“官架子“</h2> <p>会议官员与官僚体制中的官员迥然不同，前者必须避免后者的种种习气与陋规。一般而言，组织都是从内部选择官员，不过，除非是秘密组织，否则章程并不一定排斥从成员之外选择官员，如许多立法机构的主持人并不是该机构的成员。</p> <p>官员可分作两块，一是选举产生的官员，包括主持人（临时主持人）、当选总裁／会长、副总裁／会长、秘书、联络秘书、财务官和财务秘书、其他官员（董事或理事、史记官、图书管理员、物管员、牧 、警卫员、门卫等）、荣誉官员或荣誉成员；二是指派产生的官员和顾问，包括执行秘书、议事规则专家（这里简单介绍一下：议事规则专家以顾问和专家的身份，向主持人、其他官员、委员会和所有其他成员提供议事规则方面的咨询和建议。</p> <p>官员当中，地位最高、责任最大、工作最忙的无疑是主持人。其职责包括在指定时间开始会议；依据既定的会议程序、日程、时间表以及议程宣布会议即将处理的下一项事务；判断并分配发言权；对所有正当、合乎规则的动议宣布议题、提请表决、宣布表决结果；对于明显具有扰乱、拖延性质的或荒诞的动议，直接拒绝受理或者裁定为不合规则；贯彻辩论规则，维护会议的秩序和礼节；在保障所有成员权利的前提之下提高会议的运行效率；对所有程序问题进行裁定，接受申诉；在成员咨询议事规则之时给予回应；在必要的时候，签署所有法案、命令、记录等文件；宣布休会等。由此可知，会议主持人除了要承担一般主持人的功能之外，还要扮演裁判的角色。</p> <p>秘书的一大职责是负责记录、整理并保管会议纪要。会议纪要的内容包括会议的类型、组织名称、日期、时间、地点；如果主持人和秘书出席，记下这个事实，如果缺席，记下替代者的姓名；所有主动议与未被否决、收回的辅动议、委员会报告、所有事先告知、所有程序问题和申诉（无论成立还是无效，同时记录主持人裁定的理由）；休会时间等。其中主动议这一块，可谓会议纪要的主体，必须详之又详，慎之又慎。注意，动议人的姓名应该记录；除非会议要求，否则不必记录附议人的名字。秘书要在会议纪要之上签字。如果会议要求，主持人也应签字。</p> <h2 id="纪律惩戒程序">纪律惩戒程序</h2> <p>如果只是轻微违纪，如辩论之时没有面对主持人而是面对另一位成员发言，或者发言脱离了当前议题，主持人只需轻击法槌，指出错误并警告其不要再犯；对于更严重的错误，如成员不断指名道姓攻击其他成员的动机，主持人<em>或其他任何成员</em>都可以立即请此人遵守秩序；对于屡加警告而无效的严重违纪行为，主持人可以点名批评；最坏的情况，则只能勒令其退场直至会议结束，或者勒令其退场直至公开道歉，或者要求暂停其会籍，或者要求开除。开除会员一般需要“三分之二表决”。具体而言，惩戒程序包括（但不限于）以下几种。</p> <ol> <li> <p>警告。对轻微或初次违规行为通常首先通过口头警告来处理。主持人可以直接提醒成员遵守会议规则。例如，如果一个成员在会议中反复打断他人，主持人可能首先给予口头警告，提醒该成员遵守会议的发言规则。</p> </li> <li> <p>禁言。对于持续的不当行为，会议可以投票决定暂时禁止该成员发言。例如，如果警告后成员继续打断会议，会议可以决定在剩余的会议时间内禁止该成员发言。</p> </li> <li> <p>请离会场。对于严重或不受控制的行为，会议可以投票决定要求成员离开会议场所。例如，如果一个成员表现出侮辱性行为或威胁他人安全，会议可以决定让该成员离开会场。</p> </li> <li> <p>弹劾或撤销职务。对于严重违反职责或不端行为的官员，组织可以通过正式程序进行弹劾或撤销其职务。例如，如果一名董事被发现滥用职权或严重违反组织规章，可以通过正式的弹劾程序撤销其职务。</p> </li> <li> <p>会员资格的暂停或终止。在极端情况下，组织可能决定暂停或终止某人的会员资格。例如，如果一个成员持续进行破坏活动或严重违反组织的原则，组织可能决定暂停或终止其会员资格。</p> </li> <li> <p>正式听证和调查。对于复杂或严重的案件，可能需要进行正式的听证或调查过程。例如，在处理严重的财务不当行为指控时，组织可能成立一个特别委员会来调查事实并进行听证。</p> </li> </ol> <p>这些程序旨在保持会议的秩序和尊重，同时确保对违规行为的处理既公正又适当。重要的是，这些程序应当在尊重成员的权利和保证程序公正的前提下进行。</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[当会议主持人的讲究]]></summary></entry></feed>