<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-12-07T08:47:52+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Baiyang Zhang</title><subtitle>A place dedicated to sharing insights and reflections on mathematics, physics, and social sciences. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Analytic Structure</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Analytic-Structure/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Analytic Structure"/><published>2023-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Analytic-Structure</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Analytic-Structure/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="holomorphic-and-meromorphic-functions">Holomorphic and Meromorphic Functions</h3> <p>Let $X$ be a Riemann surface and $(U_ {p},\phi_ {p})$ an coordinate patch of $X$ containing a point $p$ in it. A coordinate system of $X$ is a map $X\to \mathbb{C}$, a map $\mathbb{C} \to X$ would be called a parametrization. A coordinate system is a function on $X$.</p> <p>Let $Y\subset X$ be a open subset of $X$. Denote the set of all holomorphic function on $Y$ by $\mathcal{O}(Y)$ or $\mathcal{O}_ {Y}$. This notation reminds us of the sheaf theory.</p> <p>Let $Y\subset X$ be an open subset, a function $f$ on $Y$ is called a meromorphic function if $f$ is holomorphic on $Y$ except on a set $A$ of isolated points, $A$ is called the set of poles. Let $p\in A$ be a pole, then \(\lim_{ x \to p } \left\lvert f(x) \right\rvert =\infty.\)</p> <p><em>Note that the poles must be isolated points</em>.</p> <p>We denote the set of meromorphic functions by $\mathcal{M}(Y)$. A meromorphic function is of form \(\text{meromorphic}= \frac{\text{holomorphic function }f}{\text{holomorphic function }g}\) thus the poles are zeros of $g$. This is true because every holomorphic function, which is not identically zero, has only <em>isolated</em> points as zeros.</p> <p>Since the meromorphic functions are quotients of holomorphic functions, we can construct the inverse of it, thus all the meromorphic functions on $Y$, or $X$ for that matter, form a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">field</code>.</p> <p>Given two Riemann surfaces $X$ and $X’$, a holomorphic function $f: X \to X’$ is a functions that is holomorphic on all the coordinate patches. If $f$ is a bijection with an inverse $f^{-1}$ which is also holomorphic, then we call $f$ an <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">analytic holomorphic</code> function. <strong>Analytic is to holomorphism what continuous is to open sets</strong>.</p> <p>One of the most important topic is the classification of Riemann surfaces up to analytic holomorphism.</p> <p>Let $X$ be a compact Riemann surface and $f$ a global holomorphic function, then $f$ can only be a constant function. In other words, \(\mathcal{O}(X) = \mathbb{C}.\)</p> <hr/> <p>The Riemann sphere is a geometric model that extends the complex plane to include a point at infinity. Imagine the complex plane as a horizontal sheet. The Riemann sphere is then a sphere sitting on this plane, touching it at the origin. Every point on the complex plane is projected onto the sphere (except the point at infinity, which is represented by the top point of the sphere, or the “north pole”). This projection is typically done using stereographic projection, where each point on the complex plane is connected by a line to the north pole of the sphere, and the point of intersection on the sphere is the corresponding point.</p> <p>The one-dimensional complex projective space $\mathbb{C}\mathbb{P}^1$, or just $\mathbb{P}^{1}$ in this note, is formed by considering lines through the origin in a two-dimensional complex vector space $\mathbb{C}^2$. Essentially, you take all possible complex lines (one-dimensional subspaces) in $\mathbb{C}^2$, and each line is considered a point in $\mathbb{P}^1$. This space includes all the points of the complex plane, along with an additional “point at infinity” to account for limits along each possible direction in the complex plane.</p> <p>The equivalence between these two comes from how they treat points at infinity. In the Riemann sphere, there is a single point at infinity (the north pole of the sphere), which is the limit point for all directions in the complex plane. In $\mathbb{P}^1$, each line through the origin in $\mathbb{C}^2$ corresponds to a point in projective space. Lines parallel to the complex plane (but not within it) converge to a single “point at infinity,” similar to the north pole of the Riemann sphere.</p> <p>Both the Riemann sphere and $\mathbb{P}^1$ provide a way to compactify the complex plane by adding a point at infinity, thus allowing for a seamless handling of limits and behaviors that would otherwise be “infinite” or “undefined” in the regular complex plane. They are different representations of the same conceptual space, with the Riemann sphere providing a more geometric and intuitive picture, while $\mathbb{P}^1$ offers a more algebraic and abstract framework.</p> <hr/> <p>The principal part of a meromorphic function $f(z)$ at a pole $a$ refers to the portion of the function’s Laurent series that contains the terms with negative powers of $(z - a)$. Recall that a function is meromorphic on a domain if it is holomorphic throughout the domain <strong>except for isolated poles</strong>. For a meromorphic function near a pole $a$, you can express the function as a Laurent series. This is a series expansion that, unlike the Taylor series, includes terms with negative powers. The Laurent series for $f(z)$ around the pole $a$ can be written as: \(f(z) = \sum_{n=-\infty}^{\infty} c_n (z - a)^n\) where $c_n$ are the coefficients of the series.</p> <p>The principal part of $f(z)$ at the pole $a$ specifically refers to the sum of the terms of the Laurent series with negative powers of $(z - a)$. This part of the Laurent series looks like: \(\sum_{n=1}^{\infty} c_{-n} (z - a)^{-n}\)</p> <p>So, when we talk about the principal part of a meromorphic function $f(z)$ at a pole $a$, we’re focusing on the terms in the function’s Laurent series that capture the behavior of $f(z)$ as $z$ approaches $a$ and the function goes towards infinity.</p> <hr/> <p>Every meromorphic function on the Riemann sphere is a rational function (i.e. the quotient of two polynomials), we write \(\mathcal{M}(\mathbb{P}^{1}) = \text{Quot}(\mathbb{C}[z]).\) To see that, take $f\in\mathcal{M}(\mathbb{P}^{1})$. $f$ has only finite many poles. Around each pole, we can separate the function into the principal part (namely the divergent part) and the holomorphic part. We can subtract the principal parts from $f$ hence obtaining a holomorphic function. But then this new function must be a constant. Then $f$ must be the quotient of two polynomials.</p> <h2 id="divisor">Divisor</h2> <p>A divisor is a formal sum that provides a way to keep track of the zeros and poles of meromorphic functions on a complex manifold (like a Riemann surface). It is especially useful in the study of complex functions, algebraic curves, and algebraic geometry.</p> <p>A divisor on a complex manifold is a formal sum of points on the manifold, with each point $p$ associated with an integer $n_p$. It is typically written as <br/> \(\text{Div} = \sum n_p p\) where $n_p &gt; 0$ for a zero of order $n_p$, $n_p &lt; 0$ for a pole of order $|n_p|$, and $n_p = 0$ means that $p$ is neither a zero nor a pole of the function in question.</p> <p>Divisors are used to study the properties of meromorphic functions and to formulate concepts like the degree of a divisor, the principal divisor (associated with a meromorphic function), and to define line bundles. In the context of Riemann surfaces, divisors play a crucial role in the formulation of the Riemann-Roch theorem, which is fundamental in the intersection of algebraic geometry and complex analysis.</p> <p>In short, given a Riemann surface $X$, the group of divisors $\text{Div}(X)$ is a group freely generated by points of $X$. We will denote the elements of $\text{Div}(X)$ as $D,D’$, etc. Let \(D,D' \in \text{Div}(X), \quad D = \sum_ {a}n_ {a} a,\quad D' = \sum_ {a} m_ {a} a,\) we define \(D + D' = \sum_ {a}(n_ {a}+m_ {a})a.\) We say $D&lt;D’$ iff $n_ {a}&lt;m_ {a}$ for all $a$.</p> <p>For $f\in\mathcal{M}(X)$ a meromorphic function defined on $X$, and a point $a \in X$, recall that the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">order</code> (or multiplicity) of $a$ is defined as \(\text{ord}_ {a}(f) := \begin{cases} 0, &amp; \text{holomorphic at } a \text{ and } f(a)\neq 0 \\ k, &amp; \text{has a zero of multiplicity k at } a \\ -k,&amp; \text{has a pole of multiplicity k at } a \\ \infty, &amp; \text{identically zero.} \end{cases}\)</p> <p>To every meromorphic function $f$ we may assign a divisor \((f) := \sum_ {a} \text{ord}_ {a}(f) \cdot a.\) We call such divisors <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">principal divisors</code>.</p> <p>Principal divisors turn multiplication between functions into addition, similar to the exponent function. To be exact, given two meromorphic functions $f$ and $g$ we have \((f\cdot g) = (f)+(g),\quad (f^{-1} ) = - (f).\)</p> <p>Principal divisors are important because they relate the geometry of the manifold (or variety) to the algebra of its function field. A notable property is that <em>the sum of the orders of zeros and poles of any meromorphic function on a compact manifold is zero</em>, leading to the principal divisor being of degree zero (which we will talk about later).</p> <p>In contrast to principal divisors, a general divisor on a manifold or variety is simply a formal sum of points (in the one-dimensional case) or more generally, of subvarieties of codimension $1$, weighted by integers. These are not necessarily associated with any particular meromorphic function.</p> <p>We say two divisors are <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">linearly equivalent</code> $D \sim D’$ if their difference is a principal divisor \(D - D' = (f) \text{ for some moromorphic function } f.\) We use the name <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">divisor class</code> to denote the linear equivalence class of a divisor.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Holomorphic and Meromorphic Functions]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introduction to Transseries Lecture 2</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Transseries-Lecture-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction to Transseries Lecture 2"/><published>2023-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Transseries-Lecture-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Transseries-Lecture-2/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>In history, formal power series are used extensively for finding the resolution of differential equations. If the resulting power series is convergent, it gives rise to a germ which can be analytically continued to (multi-valued) functions on a Riemann surface. However, very often, the power series we found from solving a differential equation is divergent, then it is not clear <em>a prior</em> how to attach reasonable sums to them.</p> <p>The modern theory of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">resummation</code> was developed systematically by Stieltjes, Borel and Hardy, who invented some resummation methods which <em>are stable under the common operators of analysis</em>. Later, Poincare established the equivalence between computations with formal power series and asymptotic expansions. Newton, Borel and Hardy were all aware of the systematic aspects of their theories and they consciously tried to complete their framework so as to capture as much of analysis as possible. The great unifying theory nevertheless had to wait until the late 20-th century and Ecalle’s work on transseries and Dulac’s conjecture.</p> <hr/> <p>Transseries have found significant applications in various areas of physics, particularly in high-energy physics. They are employed as algebraic tools to investigate self-consistent Dyson–Schwinger equations, which are integral equations that arise in the field of quantum field theory, specifically in Yukawa theory and quantum electrodynamics <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0003491616300793">1</a>. These equations are pivotal in understanding the interactions of particles and fields at a fundamental level.</p> <p>In the realm of general relativity, transseries are applied to asymptotic analysis. General relativity stands as one of the cornerstones of modern physics, governing the laws of gravitation and the dynamics of large-scale structures in the universe . By applying transseries in this domain, researchers can gain insights into the asymptotic behavior of gravitational fields and the dynamics of spacetime.</p> <p>Furthermore, transseries are used in the <em>extraction of non-perturbative physics from perturbation theory through resurgence and alien calculus</em>. Perturbation theory is a fundamental tool in quantum mechanics and quantum field theory, allowing for the approximation of complex systems. The non-perturbative effects are those that cannot be captured by perturbation theory alone, and transseries help to identify and understand these effects <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0003491619301691">2</a>.</p> <p>Additionally, in the context of integrable, asymptotically free field theories, transseries have applications in studying the free energy of such systems when coupled to a conserved charge. These studies are significant in high-energy physics, particularly in understanding the thermodynamics and statistical mechanics of particle systems <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/JHEP08%282022%29279">3</a>.</p> <p>These examples showcase the versatility and importance of transseries in advancing the understanding of fundamental physics, from the microscale of particle interactions to the macroscale of cosmic phenomena.</p> <hr/> <p>Define a ordered group ${\frak G}$ (frak G) of transmonomials. Define a differential field $\mathbb{T}$ of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">transseries</code>. Transmonomials are generalizations of monomials in polynomials, by including exponential and logarithmic. In this note and that follows, we will consider the limit where $x\to \infty$.</p> <p>Let’s start with exponents first.</p> <p><strong>Log-free transmonomials.</strong> They are of form \(x^{b}e^{ L },\quad b\in \mathbb{R},\; L \in \text{large log-free transseries.}\)</p> <p>For example, the following are all log-free transmonomials, \(x^{-1},\; x^{\pi}x^{x^{\sqrt{ 2 }}-3x},\; e^{ \sum_ {i}x^{-1}e^{ x } },etc.\)</p> <p>The multiplication is defined in the obvious way. The group identity is just $1$.</p> <p>We define a binary relation $\gg$, read “far larger than”. Keep in mind that we assumed $x\to \infty$. So how does this “far larger than” work? We compare the exponents $e^{ L }$ first, whichever with the largest exponent $L$ is far larger than others; if they have same exponents, then we compare the power of $x$, namely $x^{b}$, whichever with larger $b$ is far larger then others. To be specific, \(x^{b_ {1}}e^{ L_ {1} } \gg x^{b_ {2}}e^{ L_ {2} }\quad \text{ if } L_ {1} &gt; L_ {2} \;\lor\; (L_ {1}=L_ {2}\;\land\; b_ {1}&gt;b_ {2} ),\) where $\lor$ is logic or. For example, $x^{-5}\gg x^{20}e^{ -x }$ since $x^{-5}=x^{-5}e^{ 0 }$ and $0&gt;-x$.</p> <p><strong>Log-free transseries.</strong> A log-free transseries $T$ is a formal sum of log-free monomials ${\frak g}$, \(T = \sum_ {i} c_ {i} {\frak g}_ {i},\quad c_ {i} \in \mathbb{R} .\) We require the order of transmonomials be such that, each ${\frak g_ {i}}$ is far smaller than all previous terms, namely they appear in descending orders. This is similar to the case of regular polynomials where we usually put the highest powers at first.</p> <p>The transseries $T$ is said to be <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">purely large</code> if all transmonomials ${\frak g}_ {i}$ are far larger than $1$ (not $0$), namely ${\frak g_ {i}}\gg 1 \;\forall i$. $T$ is said to be <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">small</code> if all ${\frak g}_ {i}\ll 1$ (why isn’t it called purely small?). The largest (in the sense of far larger than) transmonomial is called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">dominant term</code>, let’s call it $c_ {0}{\frak g}_ {0}$. If the dominant term has positive coefficients, $c_ {0}&gt;0$, then $T$ is said to be positive. This enables us to compare the size of two transseries $S,T$, we say $S&gt;T$ if $S-T&gt;0$. So we just need to compare their dominant terms.</p> <hr/> <p>We consider only transmonomials and transseries of “finite exponential height”. For example, we don’t want \(e^{ x^{x^{x\dots}} }.\)</p> <p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">differentiation</code> of $T$ with respect to $x$ is defined the usual way.</p> <hr/> <p>Next let’s include logarithmic. $\log$ acting $m$ times is denoted $\log_ {m}x$ or $\log_ {(m)}x$, namely \(\log_ {(m)}x = \log \dots \log x,\quad m\; \log .\)</p> <p>A general transseries is obtained by substitution of some $\log_ {m}x$ for $x$ in a log-free transseries.</p> <p><em>Every nonzero transseries has a multiplicative inverse.</em> This is similar to formal power series.</p> <p><em>A lot of functions can now be regarded as a transseries</em>. For example, e hyperbolic sine is a two-term transseries.</p> <h2 id="formal-constructions">Formal Constructions</h2> <p>In mathematics, the move towards higher levels of formality entails adopting rigorous and precise language, definitions, and proofs, which brings clarity and precision, ensuring that mathematical concepts are universally understood and applied correctly. It allows for the development of solid, gap-free proofs, having a deeper understanding of mathematical structures and providing a robust foundation for complex theories. This precision in communication is critical in a global context, where scientists from different fields rely on universally recognized formalisms to understand each other effectively.</p> <p>However, this precision comes at a cost. It can make the subject less accessible to beginners (like myself), potentially hindering educational and interdisciplinary work. A focus on stringent formalism might even inhibit creative thinking, as the rigidity of formal proofs could constrain the exploratory, intuitive processes that often drive mathematical discovery. Moreover, the lengthy and detailed nature of formal proofs can make mathematical work less efficient, both in terms of personal understanding and communication with others. There’s also the risk of diminishing intuition, which is a crucial aspect of mathematical thought, particularly in the preliminary stages of research. It is definitely crucial to have a balance between concrete examples and general formalism, what is I hope to achieve in this note.</p> <hr/> <p>The set of monomials ${\frak G}$ form a field, which is also a group if we focus on multiplication alone. ${\frak G}$ is <em>not</em> finitely generated, to see this consider the finitely generated group with generator \(\mu_ {1},\mu_ {2},\dots,\mu_ {n},\) the generated group has elements of form \(\left\{ \mu_ {1}^{k_ {1}}\times \mu_ {2}^{k_ {2}}\times \dots \times \mu_ {n}^{k_ {n}} \,\middle\vert\, k_ {1},\dots,k_ {n} \in \mathbb{Z} \right\} .\) Note that the exponents must be integers.</p> <p>Let’s use capital letters to denote a set of indices, for example define \(K := (k_ {1},k_ {2},\dots,k_ {n})\) then \(\mu_ {1}^{k_ {1}}\dots \mu_ {n}^{k_ {n}} =: \mu^{K}.\)</p> <p>This will save some writing. The problem is that $\mu^{K}$ can also be interpreted as $\mu^{k_ {1}k_ {1}\dots k_ {n}}$, but it should be clear from the context.</p> <p>We will assume that all the generator $\mu \ll 1$. We will think of these as “ratios” between one term of a series and the next. A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ratio set</code> is a finite set of small monomials.</p> <p>Let $k \in \mathbb{Z}^{n}$ be an $n$-tuple of integers, it form a group under addition. Let $p$ be another such $n$-tuple, one say \(k \leq p \quad \text{ iff } k_ {i} \leq p _ {i} \;\forall\; i,\) where $k_ {i}$ is the $i$-th component of $k$.</p> <p>$J_ {m}$ is a partially ordered set. To be specific, a partially ordered set (or poset) is a set equipped with a binary relation that captures a certain level of order or precedence among its elements. This binary relation is denoted by $\leq$ and must satisfy the following properties for any elements $a, b$, and $c$ in the set:</p> <ol> <li><em>Reflexivity</em>: For all elements a in the set, $a\leq a$. In other words, every element is related to itself;</li> <li><em>Antisymmetry</em>: If $a \leq b$ and $b \leq a$, then $a = b$. This property ensures that <em>no two distinct elements are related in both directions</em>;</li> <li><em>Transitivity</em>: If $a \leq b$ and $b \leq c$, then $a \leq c$. This property means that if there’s an order relationship between $a$ and $b$, and another between $b$ and $c$, there’s also an order relationship between $a$ and $c$.</li> </ol> <p>A partially ordered set <strong>does not</strong> require every pair of elements to be comparable; that is, it’s possible for $a$ and $b$ to be in the set without $a\leq b$ or $b \leq a$ being true. This distinguishes partially ordered sets from <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">totally ordered sets</code>, where <strong>every pair of elements is comparable</strong>.</p> <p>For $m\in \mathbb{Z}^{n}$, define \(J_ {m} := \left\lbrace k \in \mathbb{Z}^{n} \,\middle\vert\, k\geq m \right\rbrace .\) Apparently $m \in J_ {m}$. The sets $J_ {m}$ will be used to define <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">grids</code> of monomials. For example, if \(\mu_ {1} = \frac{1}{x},\quad \mu_ {2}=e^{ -x }\) comprise the ratio group (recall that each element of a ratio group is required to be small), then we can define a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">grid</code> (about which we will say more later) \(\left\lbrace \mu^{k} \,\middle\vert\, k\in J_ {(-1,2)} \right\rbrace\) which is the same as \(\left\lbrace \mu^{k}=\mu_ {1}^{k_ {1}} \cdot \mu_ {2}^{k_ {2}} \,\middle\vert\, (k_ {1},k_ {2})\geq (-1,2) \right\rbrace .\)</p> <p>In our convention, the set of natural numbers $\mathbb{N}$ include zero.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="dicksons-lemma">Dickson’s lemma</h3> <p>It turns out that the set $J_ {m}$ is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">well-partially-ordered</code>, sometimes called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Noetherian</code>. A partially ordered set (poset) is said to be well-partially-ordered if it satisfies two conditions:</p> <ul> <li>It contains no <em>infinite strictly descending sequences</em>. This means there cannot be an infinite sequence of elements $a_1, a_2, a_3, \ldots$ in the set such that $a_1 &gt; a_2 &gt; a_3 &gt; \ldots$.</li> <li>It contains no <em>infinite antichains</em>. An <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">antichain</code> is a subset of the poset in which no two distinct elements are comparable. In a well-partially-ordered set, there cannot be an infinite set of elements where none are comparable to each other.</li> </ul> <p>On the other hand, a poset is called Noetherian if it satisfies the <strong>descending chain condition</strong> (<strong>DCC</strong>), which states that every descending sequence of elements eventually stabilizes. In other words, there cannot be an infinite strictly descending sequence of elements in the set.</p> <p>The primary difference between the two concepts is that being well-partially-ordered is a stronger condition than being Noetherian. While both require the absence of infinite strictly descending sequences (the Noetherian property), being well-partially-ordered also requires the absence of infinite antichains. Therefore, every well-partially-ordered set is Noetherian, but not every Noetherian set is well-partially-ordered.</p> <p><strong>Proposition.</strong> If $E \subseteq J_ {m}$ and $E \neq \emptyset$, then there is a minimal element $k_ {0} \in E$.</p> <p><strong>Proposition.</strong> Let $E$ from the previous proposition be infinite, then there is an infinite sequence $k_ {i}\subset E$ such that $k_ {0}&lt;k_ {1}&lt;\dots$.</p> <p><strong>Proposition.</strong> For the same $E$, the set of all the minimal elements $\text{min}(E)$ is finite. For every element $k\in E$ there is a $k_ {0} \in \text{min}(E)$ such that $k_ {0} \le k$.</p> <h3 id="convergence-of-sets">Convergence of sets</h3> <p>First let’s introduce the symmetric difference of two sets, which is a mathematical operation that results in a new set containing elements that are in <strong>either</strong> of the two sets, but <strong>not in their intersection</strong>. In other words, it combines the elements of each set that are not shared by both. The symmetric difference is denoted by the symbol $\Delta$.</p> <p>Formally, if you have two sets $A$ and $B$, their symmetric difference $A \Delta B$ is defined as: \(A \Delta B = (A - B) \cup (B - A).\) Here, $A - B$ represents the set of elements in $A$ but not in $B$, and $B - A$ represents the set of elements in $B$ but not in $A$. The union of these two sets ($\cup$) forms the symmetric difference.</p> <p>Another way to express this is using the union and intersection of sets: \(A \Delta B = (A \cup B) - (A \cap B).\) By subtracting the intersection from the union, you’re left with only those elements that are exclusively in either $A$ or $B$, but not in both.</p> <p>The symmetric difference has several interesting properties:</p> <ul> <li>It is commutative: $A \Delta B = B \Delta A$.</li> <li>It is associative: $(A \Delta B) \Delta C = A \Delta (B \Delta C)$.</li> <li>The symmetric difference of a set with itself is the empty set: $A \Delta A = \emptyset$.</li> <li>The symmetric difference of a set with the empty set is the set itself: $A \Delta \emptyset = A$.</li> </ul> <p>Now let’s define the convergence of a sequence of sets $E_ {i}, i\in I$, where $I$ is an infinite index set. For each $i\in I$, let $E_ {i} \in \mathbb{Z}^{n}$. We say the family $E_ {i,\,i\in I}$ is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">point-finite</code> if each $p\in \mathbb{Z}^{n}$ belong to $E_ {i}$ for only finite many $i$ (could be zero).</p> <p>Let $m\in\mathbb{Z}^{n}$ and define $J_ {m}$ as before. If the “limit” of $E_ {i}$ is empty, we write \(E_ {i} \xrightarrow{m}\emptyset,\quad \text{iff } E_ {i} \subset J_ {m} \text{ and } (E_ {i}) \text{ is point-finite.}\) More generally, we write \(E_ {i} \to \emptyset\) if there exist $m\in\mathbb{Z}^{n}$ such that $E_ {i}\xrightarrow{m}\emptyset$.</p> <p>Now we can generalize the situation to other than the empty set. To do that we need the concept of symmetric difference. Intuitively, if the limit of $E_ {i}$ is another set $E$, then there should be infinite sets $E_ {i, \, i&gt;j}$ for some $j$ such that they all “tend to” contain $E$. It implies that $E_ {i}-E$ should tend to be empty, for if there is some element $e$ in the limit of $E_ {i}-E$ then $e$ should be in the limit, too. On the other hand, the limit $E$ shouldn’t contain any more element that is not in $E_ {i}$’s. For example, if for all $i&gt;j$, some element $e’$ is not in $E_ {i,i&gt;j}$ then it should not be contained in the limit $E$ as well. These very hand-waving arguments inspires us to define the limit of $E_ {i}$ as follows.</p> <p>We write \(E_ {i}\xrightarrow{m} E,\quad \text{iff }E_ {i} \subset J_ {m} \text{ and } E_ {i}\Delta E\xrightarrow{m}\emptyset .\) All the properties we want for a limit of $E_ {i}$ are concisely contained in the condition that $E_ {i}\Delta E$ tend to the empty set. Also, we simply write \(E_ {i}\to E\) if there exists some $m$ such that $E_ {i}\xrightarrow{m}E$ and we don’t care about the details of $m$.</p> <p>Equivalently, we could say that $(E_ {i}\Delta E)$ is point finite.</p> <p><strong>Example.</strong> Consider $\mathbb{Z}^{n}=\mathbb{Z}^{1}=\mathbb{Z}$. Let $E_ {i} =\left\lbrace i,i+1,\dots \right\rbrace$ for $i\in \mathbb{N}$. Then the sequence $E_ {i}$ is point-finite. We have \(E_ {i}\to \emptyset .\) But if we let $F_ {i}=\left\lbrace -i \right\rbrace$, then even though $F_ {i}$ is point-finite but $F$ can not be contained in some $J_ {m}$ so it does not converge.</p> <p><strong>Notation.</strong> Let $k = (k_ {1},k_ {2},\dots,k_ {n})$ then define $\left\lvert k \right\rvert:=k_ {1}+k_ {2}+\dots+k_ {n}$.</p> <p>For two pints $p,q$ in $J_ {m}$, we can introduce the concept of distance by defining \(d(p,q):= 2^{-\left\lvert p-q \right\rvert }\) This reminds me of Krull topology.</p> <p>For two sets $E,F\subset J_ {m}$, define \(d(E,F):= \sum_ {k\in E\Delta F} 2^{-\left\lvert k \right\rvert },\) then for any $E_ {i}\subset J_ {m}$, we have $E_ {i}\to E$ iff $d(E_ {i},E)\to 0$. And $d$ is a metric on the grid $J_ {m}$.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hamiltonian Truncation in 3D</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Hamiltonian-Truncation-in-3D/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hamiltonian Truncation in 3D"/><published>2023-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Hamiltonian-Truncation-in-3D</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Hamiltonian-Truncation-in-3D/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="background">Background</h3> <h3 id="the-symplectic-manifold">The symplectic manifold</h3> <p>The finite-dimensional covariant Hamiltonian approach to field theory is vigorously developed from the seventies in its multisymplectic and polysymplectic variants. The final purpose is to covariant Hamiltonian quantization of field theory. For classical field theory, the Hamiltonian formalism provides an alternative to the Lagrangian formalism for deriving the equations of motion. Furthermore, the Hamiltonian approach offers a geometrical interpretation of the field theory, in a sense combines geometry and algebra together. To fully appreciate it, we need to know what is a symplectic manifold first.</p> <p>A symplectic manifold is a type of smooth manifold equipped with a special kind of geometric structure known as a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">symplectic form</code>. As we all know, a manifold is a <em>topological space</em> that <strong>locally resembles Euclidean space</strong>. In the case of a smooth manifold, this means that around every point, the manifold can be approximated by a patch of Euclidean space in such a way that the transition maps between these patches are smooth (infinitely differentiable). A symplectic form on a manifold is a specific kind of differential form that is <strong>closed</strong> and <strong>non-degenerate</strong>. In more concrete terms, a symplectic form is a $2$-form, and non-degeneracy means that the form pairs vectors in a way that is <strong>invertible</strong> – no non-zero vector is mapped to zero – ensuring that the form provides a kind of generalized volume element on the manifold.</p> <p>To be more mathematically rigorous, let $M$ be a topological space that is Hausdorff (any two distinct points have disjoint neighborhoods) and second-countable (has a countable basis for its topology). Additionally, $M$ is locally homeomorphic to $\mathbb{R}^n$, meaning every point in $M$ has a neighborhood that is topologically the same as an open subset of Euclidean space (this practically says that $M$ is a manifold). A smooth manifold is a manifold equipped with an atlas of charts such that the transition maps between overlapping charts are smooth. On $M$, a symplectic form $\omega$ is a closed, non-degenerate differential $2$-form. Mathematically, this means</p> <ul> <li><strong>Closed</strong>: The exterior derivative $d\omega$ is zero, $d\omega = 0$. This implies that $\omega$ is <strong>locally exact</strong>.</li> <li><strong>Non-degenerate</strong>: For any vector $v\in T_ {p}M$ where $p \in M$, if $\omega(v, w) = 0$ for all vectors $w$ at that point, then $v$ must be the zero vector. This ensures that the form $\omega$ pairs vectors in a fully invertible way.</li> </ul> <p>Note that a symplectic manifold is necessarily even-dimensional. If $M$ is a symplectic manifold with symplectic form $\omega$, and the dimension of $M$ is $2n$, then $\omega^n$ (the $n$-th wedge power of $\omega$) is a volume form on $M$, providing a natural orientation.</p> <p><strong>Darboux’s theorem.</strong> Locally, all symplectic manifolds of the same dimension are isomorphic. This means that around any point in a symplectic manifold, one can find local coordinates (often called “canonical coordinates” or “Darboux coordinates”) $(q_1, \ldots, q_n, p_1, \ldots, p_n)$) in which the symplectic form has the standard expression $\omega = \sum_{i=1}^{n} dq_i \wedge dp_i$.</p> <p>In classical mechanics, symplectic manifolds serve as the stage for Hamiltonian dynamics. The <em>phase space of a classical mechanical system</em>, which includes both its positions and momenta, <em>can be treated as a symplectic manifold</em>. The symplectic form encodes the fundamental <em>Poisson brackets</em> of the system, which are central to Hamiltonian mechanics. It provides the geometric framework within which the evolution of the system can be elegantly expressed using Hamilton’s equations. The structure of symplectic manifolds imposes several interesting properties. For instance, in <strong>even-dimensional</strong> spaces, they allow for the formulation of Hamiltonian vector fields and symplectic transformations. These concepts have far-reaching applications not only in physics but also in areas like symplectic topology, geometric quantization, and more.</p> <h3 id="hamiltonian-equations">Hamiltonian equations</h3> <p>Most readers are much more comfortable with the Lagrangian formalism of field theory than the Hamiltonian formalism, so let’s start with the former. The transition from Lagrangian to Hamiltonian is achieved by <strong>Legendre transformation</strong>. We first define the canonical momenta $\pi_i$ conjugate to each field $\phi_i$ by \(\pi_i = \frac{\partial \mathcal{L}}{\partial (\partial_t \phi_i)},\) where $\mathcal{L}$ is the Lagrangian density and $\partial_t \phi_i$ is the time derivative of the field.</p> <p>The Hamiltonian density $\mathcal{H}$ is then given by \(\mathcal{H} = \sum_i \pi_i \partial_t \phi_i - \mathcal{L},\) where the sum runs over all fields in the theory.</p> <p>The equations of motion in the Hamiltonian formalism for field theory are then given by Hamilton’s equations, analogous to the Hamiltonian formalism in classical mechanics. These equations are \(\frac{\partial \phi_i}{\partial t} = \frac{\delta \mathcal{H}}{\delta \pi_i},\) \(\frac{\partial \pi_i}{\partial t} = -\frac{\delta \mathcal{H}}{\delta \phi_i},\) where $\frac{\delta}{\delta \phi_i}$ and $\frac{\delta}{\delta \pi_i}$ represent functional derivatives with respect to the field $\phi_i$ and its conjugate momentum $\pi_i$, respectively.</p> <p>From now on let’s assume there are only one type of field and canonical momentum, so we can neglect the subscript $i$. Note here the functional derivative $\delta / \delta \phi$ is not equivalent to the partial derivative $\partial / \partial \phi$. To see this, recall how $\delta \mathcal{H}$ and $\delta \mathcal{H} / \delta \phi$ is defined, \(\delta H =: \int d^{d-1}x \, \delta \mathcal{H} = \int d^{d-1}x \, \delta \phi \frac{\delta \mathcal{H}}{\delta \phi},\) thus all we need to do is to perform a variation of the field $\phi$ and leaving the canonical momentum $\pi$ untouched, then massage the variation of the Hamiltonian in the form given above. For a generic Hamiltonian $\mathcal{H}(\pi,\phi,\partial_ {x}\phi)$ where $x$ denotes all the spatial coordinates, under the field variation $\phi\to\phi+\delta \phi$ we have \(\begin{align*} H\to H' &amp;= \int d^{d-1}x \, \mathcal{H}(\phi+\delta \phi,\partial_ {x}\phi+\partial_ {x}\delta\phi, \cdots) \\ &amp;= \int d^{d-1}x \, \left[ \frac{\partial\mathcal{H}}{\partial \phi }\delta \phi + \frac{\partial \mathcal{H}}{\partial(\partial_ {x}\phi)}\delta(\partial_ {x}\phi) \right] \\ &amp;= \int d^{d-1}x \, \left[ \frac{\partial\mathcal{H}}{\partial \phi }\delta \phi + \frac{\partial \mathcal{H}}{\partial(\partial_ {x}\phi)}(\partial_ {x}\delta\phi) \right] \\ \\ &amp;= \int d^{d-1}x \, \left[ \frac{\partial\mathcal{H}}{\partial \phi }\delta \phi - \left( \partial_ x\frac{\partial \mathcal{H}}{\partial(\partial_ {x}\phi)} \right) \delta\phi \right] \\ \\ &amp;= \int d^{d-1}x \, \delta\phi \left[ \frac{\partial\mathcal{H}}{\partial \phi } - \left( \partial_ x\frac{\partial \mathcal{H}}{\partial(\partial_ {x}\phi)} \right) \right] \\ &amp;= : \int d^{d-1}x \, \delta \phi \frac{\delta \mathcal{H}}{\delta \phi} \end{align*}\) thus, \(\frac{\delta \mathcal{H}}{\delta \phi} = \frac{\partial\mathcal{H}}{\partial \phi } - \left( \partial_ x\frac{\partial \mathcal{H}}{\partial(\partial_ {x}\phi)} \right).\) Taking this back to the Hamiltonian equations we recover the familiar Euler-Lagrange equation.</p> <p>These equations describe how the fields and their conjugate momenta evolve over time, analogous to how the position and momentum of a particle evolve in classical mechanics. They provide a complete description of the dynamics of the field system within the Hamiltonian framework.</p> <h2 id="hamiltonian-truncation">Hamiltonian Truncation</h2> <p>The starting point of defining a quantum field theory is the choice of a manifold $M$ of dimension $d$. We mostly (but not always) regard the manifold as a Riemannian manifold with a <strong>smooth</strong> metric on it. The manifold may or may not have boundaries, if it does then some additional information is needed at the boundaries to define the theory.</p> <p>Having defined the manifold $M$, the next ingredient is the choice of objects to consider over $M$, the so-called “degree of freedoms”, or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">fields</code>. Now it is helpful to adopt a statistical viewpoint toward QFT, in order to extract the information about physical observables we need “just” to know the partition function, which is obtain via a so-called path-integral. That is, we integrate all the possible field configurations with a weight, which is essentially given by the exponent of the action. For example, we may consider a principal bundle with a connection over $M$. In physics terminology the choice of the connection is the same as picking a gauge field. We may also be considering the section of a vector bundle over $M$, these fields are sometimes called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">matter field</code>.</p> <p>As another example of QFT we may consider the space of maps \(X: M\to N\) where $N$ is the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">target</code> manifold. The field theories associated with integrating over the space of such maps are called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sigma models</code>.</p> <p>In quantum field theories we are typically interested in integrating over infinite-dimensional spaces. It turns out that the greater the dimension $d$ of $M$, the more complicated the integrations over these spaces. In fact (ignoring gravitational theories), the only non-trivial quantum field theories that are believed to exist (i.e., for which some kind of integration over the infinite-dimensional space exists) have $d \leq 6$ and most of the standard ones have $d \leq 4$.</p> <p>Quantum field theories in different dimensions can be related to each other by an operation known as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Kaluza–Klein reduction</code>. Roughly speaking this means considering the situation where \(M = N \times K,\quad K \ll N\) The action may be very large for field configurations that are <strong>not</strong> constant over $K$, so the path-integral, which is weighted by $e^{ -S_ {E} }$, localizes to field configurations that are constant along $K$. This gives rise to an <strong>effective</strong> path integral over field configurations that have only constant modes along $K$.</p> <h3 id="definitions">Definitions</h3> <p>In our case, we consider the phi-fourth theory defined on \(M = \mathbb{T}^{2} \times \mathbb{R},\) where $\mathbb{T}^{2}$ is the flat torus space of size $L \times L$, and the time direction $\mathbb{R}$ is left uncompactified. Since the space manifold is compact, the spectrum of the free theory is discrete and free of IR divergence. Following the procedure of canonical quantization, we first expand the scalar field in terms of ladder operators (in discrete form) as \(\phi(\vec{x}) = \sum_ {k_ {1},k_ {2}} c_ {k} a_ {k}e^{ +i \vec{k}\cdot \vec{x} } + \text{h.c.} \tag{1}\) where $\vec{k}$ is the two-dimensional momentum vector $\vec{k}=(k_ {1},k_ {2})$. Since the space is a torus of size $L \times L$, the momentum can only take values \(k_ {i} = \frac{2\pi n_ {i} }{L},\quad n_ {i} \in \mathbb{Z}.\) The coefficient $c_ {k}$ is defined to be \(c_ {k} = \frac{1}{L\sqrt{ 2\omega_ {k} }},\quad \omega _ {k} = \sqrt{ k^{2}+m^{2} }.\) The canonical quantization in terms of the ladder operator is rather simple, \([a_ {k} , a_ {k'}^{^{\dagger}}] = \delta_ {k,k'},\quad \text{zero otherwise.}\) The free Hamiltonian is \(\mathcal{H}_ {0} = \frac{1}{2} \pi^{2} + \frac{1}{2 } (\nabla \phi)^{2} + \frac{m^{2}}{2} \phi^{2},\) where $\pi$ is the canonical momentum. So far we have assumed that the field configuration is static so there is no contribution from the canonical momentum. Taking Eq. (1) to $\mathcal{H}_ {0}$ we have \(H_ {0} = \int _ {L^{2}} d^{2}x \, \mathcal{H}_ {0} = \sum_ {k} \omega_ {k} a_ {k} ^{\dagger} a_ {k} + \text{Const},\) where the constant term is the zero point energy.</p> <p>The free vacuum is defined by $H_ {0} \left\lvert{0}\right\rangle=0$.</p> <p>The interacting Hamiltonian is defined as \(\mathcal{H} (E_ {T}) = \mathcal{H}_ {0} + \mathcal{V}, \quad \mathcal{V}=g_ {2} \mathcal{V}_ {2} + g_ {4} \mathcal{V} _ {4}+ C(E_ {T}),\) where \(\mathcal{V}_ {n} = \frac{1}{n!} :\phi^{n}:\) and $:\bullet:$ denotes the normal ordering. $E_ {T}$ is the truncation energy and $C(E_ {T})$ is a counter terms which will be needed later.</p> <hr/> <p>The Hilbert space is spanned by the eigenstates of the <strong>free</strong> Hamiltonian, $\left\lvert{E_ {i}}\right\rangle$. In the Hamiltonian truncation approach, we only consider the the states with $E_ {i} &lt; E_ {T}=: \Lambda$. In this case, the <strong>full</strong> Hamiltonian can be considered as a finite-dimensional matrix \(H_ {ij} := \left\langle{E_ {i}}\right\rvert H \left\lvert{E_ {j} }\right\rangle .\) At weak coupling, the spectrum of the truncated Hamiltonian can be computed using Hamiltonian Perturbation Theory (HPT).</p> <h3 id="hamiltonian-perturbation-theory">Hamiltonian Perturbation Theory</h3> <p>In quantum field theory, Lagrangian perturbation theory has been dominant, especially in the study of scattering processes and elementary particle physics. This approach’s explicit covariance has been crucial in implementing the renormalization program. However, it complicates the identification of physical states defined as eigenstates of the Hamiltonian and the Hilbert space they span.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Background]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Homotopy-and-Chern-Forms</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Homotopy-and-Chern-Forms/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Homotopy-and-Chern-Forms"/><published>2023-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Homotopy-and-Chern-Forms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Homotopy-and-Chern-Forms/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="lifting-spheres-from-the-base-to-the-bundle">Lifting spheres from the base to the bundle</h2> <p>Let $E\to M$ be a bundle.</p> <p><strong>Sphere lifting theorem.</strong> Any map of a $k$-sphere into $M^{n}$ (with base point $x_ {0}$) can be covered by a map of a $k$-disk into the bundle space $E$, in which the boundary $(k-1)$-sphere is mapped into the fiber $F=\pi^{-1}(x_ {0})$.</p> <p>Recall that a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">covering space</code> is simply a bundle over $M$ with a <em>discrete</em> fiber. The above theorem implies the below theorem.</p> <p><strong>Theorem.</strong> If $\pi: \overline{M} \to M$is a covering space, then the homomorphism induced by projection \(\pi_ {\ast }: \pi_ {k}(\overline{M}, \overline{\ast }) \to \pi_ {k}(M,\ast )\) is an isomorphism for $k\geq 2$. Furthermore, if $k=1$ \(\pi_ {\star}: \pi_ {1}(\overline{M}, \overline{\ast }) \to \pi_ {1}(M,\ast )\) is an isomorphism.</p> <p>We will neglect the proof here, we just mention that this is a result of the fiber $\pi_ {-1}(x_ {0})$ being discrete. And the reason why $k\geq 2$ is special is that the boundary of $k$-sphere, if $k\geq 2$, is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">continuous</code>, hence the image of it also has to be discrete, however the fiber is discrete, so the image must be a single point.</p> <p>As simple corollaries we have \(\pi_ {k}(\mathbb{R}P^{n}) = \pi_ {k}(\mathbb{S}^{n}),\) \(\pi_ {k}(T^{n}) = \pi_ {k}(\mathbb{R}^{n}),\) all for $k\geq 2$.</p> <hr/> <p>We know that $SU(N)$ are all simply connected, $\pi_ {1}(SU(N))=0$. Now we show that $\pi_ {2}(SU(N))$ also vanish.</p> <p>Recall the $SU(N)$ fibering \(SU(N-1) \rightarrow SU(N) \rightarrow \mathbb{S}^{2N-1},\) where $SU(N-1) \rightarrow SU(N)$ represents the inclusion of $SU(N-1)$ into $SU(N)$. Essentially, $SU(N-1)$ can be thought of as a subgroup of $SU(N)$, where the matrices in $SU(N-1)$ are extended to $N \times N$ matrices by adding 1 as an additional diagonal entry. $SU(N) \rightarrow \mathbb{S}^{2N-1}$ is a bit more complex. $\mathbb{S}^{2N-1}$ represents the $(2N-1)$-dimensional sphere, which can be thought of as a set of points in a complex $N$-dimensional space $\mathbb{C}^N$. The map from $SU(N)$ to $S^{2N-1}$ can be understood as taking a matrix in $SU(N)$ and mapping it to a point on the sphere, typically using the action of $SU(N)$ on a fixed point in $\mathbb{C}^N$. In other words, the $\mathbb{S}^{N-1}$ can be considered as the first column of $SU(N)$ and $SU(N-1)$ can be considered as the subgroup of $SU(N)$.</p> <p>From here we have the exact homotopy sequence \(\cdots \to \pi_ {3}(\mathbb{S}^{2N-1})\to\pi_ {2}(SU(N-1))\to\pi_ {2}(SU(N))\to\pi_ {2}(\mathbb{S}^{2N-1})\cdots\) for $N\geq 3$ this gives \(0 \to \pi_ {2}(SU(N-1))\to\pi_ {2}(SU(N))\to 0.\) To see this, recall that we may assume that $f(\mathbb{S}^{k})$ does not cover all of $\mathbb{S}^{n}$ when $k&lt;n$. Suppose then that the south pole of $\mathbb{S}^{n}$ is not covered. By pushing away from the south pole we may push the entire image to the north pole; we have deformed the map into a constant map. Thus $\pi_ {k}(\mathbb{S}^{n})=0$ if $k&lt;n$.</p> <p>Thus, \(\pi_ {2}(SU(N)) = \pi_ {2}(SU(N-1))\dots=\pi_ {2}(\mathbb{S}^{3}) =0.\)</p> <p>In fact, E. Cartan has shown that every map of a $2$-sphere into any Lie group is contractible to a point, \(\pi_ {2}G=0,\quad G\text{ a Lie group.}\) Also, \(\pi_ {3}(SU(N)) = \pi_ {3}SU(2) = \mathbb{Z} \text{ for } n\geq 2\) thus every element of the shape $\mathbb{S}^{3}$ in $SU(N\geq 3)$ can be deformed to lie in an $SU(2)$ subgroup.</p> <hr/> <p>Heinz Hopf discovered an <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">essential map</code> of $\mathbb{S}^{3}$ onto $\mathbb{S}^{2}$, that is, a map $\pi: \mathbb{S}^{3}\to\mathbb{S}^{2}$ which is not homotopic to a constant map. This cannot happen in the case of a 2-sphere mapped into a 1-sphere. With our machinery we can easily exhibit this map. We know that $SU(2)$ acts on its Lie algebra (with three basis, namely the Pauli matrices) as a double cover of $SO(3)$ rotation, and the stability subgroup of the hermitian matrix $\sigma_ {3}$ is the subgroup \(\begin{pmatrix} e^{ i\theta } &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; e^{ -i\theta } \end{pmatrix} \sim \text{ a circle.}\) Thus we have the fibration \(\mathbb{S}^{1}\to SU(2) \to \mathbb{S}^{2}.\) From the homotopy sequence \(0=\pi_ {3}\mathbb{S}^{1}\to\pi_ {3}SU(2)\to\pi_ {3}\mathbb{S}^{2}\to\pi_ {2}\mathbb{S}^{1}=0\) we see that \(\pi_ {3}SU(2) = \pi_ {3}\mathbb{S}^{2} = \mathbb{Z}.\)</p> <p>We have shown that $\mathbb{S}^{3}=SU(2)$ is a fiber bundle over $\mathbb{S}^{2}$ with (nonintersecting) circles as fibers. This is the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Hopf fibration</code>.</p> <h2 id="chern-forms-as-obstructions">Chern Forms as Obstructions</h2> <p>Consider a $U(1)$ bundle.</p> <p><strong>Theorem.</strong> Let $E\to M$ be a hermitian line bundle (that is, a bundle with hermitian metric, $\left\langle u,v \right\rangle=\overline{\left\langle v,u \right\rangle}$), with pure imaginary connection $\omega$ and curvature $\theta$. Let $V$ be any closed, oriented surface embedded in $M$, then \(\frac{i}{2\pi} \int _ {V} \, \theta = \int _ {V} \, c_ {1}\) is an integer and represents the sum of the indices of any sections $s: V\to E$ of the part of the line bundle over $V$. It is assumed that $s$ has but a finite number of zeros on $V$.</p> <p>It is only when this integer vanishes that one can possibly find a nonvanishing section (that is, a frame over all of $V$).\</p> <p>Next, instantons are associated to $SU(2)$ bundles. The winding number of an instanton is given by \(\frac{1}{24\pi} \int _ {\mathbb{S}^{3}} \, \mathrm{Tr}\,\omega \wedge \omega \wedge \omega = - \int _ {\mathbb{R}^{4}} \, c_ {2}.\) It is only when the winding number is zero then we can construct a global frame on $\mathbb{R}^{4}$.</p> <hr/> <p>We have defined the Chern forms for a complex $U(N)$ bundle $E$, \(\det\left( I+\frac{i\theta}{2\pi} \right) = 1+c_ {1}(E) + c_ {2}(E)+\dots\) and we showed that each $c_ r$ is a closed form, and thus defines a de Rham cohomology class. The factor $i$ is to make each $c’s$ real. This cohomology class, with real coefficients, is independent of the connection used, a change of connection (a gauge transformation) will add to the coefficients an exact form hence does not change the de Rham class. The factor $\frac{1}{2\pi}$ ensures the periods are integers.</p> <p><strong>Obstruction cocycle</strong></p> <p>The existing of nonzero $c_ {2}$ is an obstruction of having a nonzero frame over the manifold. It can be shown by fist triangularize the base $M$, then try to extend the section from the $0$-skeleton to $1$-skeleton and so on.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="Geometry"/><category term="Frankel"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lifting spheres from the base to the bundle]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introduction to Resurgence Lecture 2</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Resurgence-Lecture-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction to Resurgence Lecture 2"/><published>2023-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Resurgence-Lecture-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Resurgence-Lecture-2/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="an-example-by-poincare">An example by Poincare</h3> <p>To get some feeling about resurgence, let’s start with an example first given by Poincare. This example shows <strong>how an divergent series emerges from a function.</strong></p> <p>Fix $w\in \mathbb{C}$ and $\left\lvert w \right\rvert&lt;1$. Consider the series of functions of the complex variable $t$, \(\phi_ {k}(t) := \frac{w^{k}}{1+kt},\quad \phi(t):= \sum_ {k\geq 0} \phi_ {k}(t).\) This series is uniformly convergent on \(U:=C^{\ast } - \left\{ -1,-\frac{1}{2},-\frac{1}{3},\dots \right\} .\) Hence the sum $\phi$ is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">holomorphic</code> in $U$. Actually $\phi$ is meromorphic on $\mathbb{C}^{\ast}$ (not on $\mathbb{C}$ since the origin would be a limiting point of the poles) with simple poles at $1 / \mathbb{N}$.</p> <p>We now show how this function $\phi$ gives rise to a divergent formal series when $t$ approaches $0$. The idea is to expand each $\phi_ {k}$ first in terms of $t$. For each $k \in \mathbb{N}$, we have a <em>convergent</em> Taylor expansion at $t=0$, \(\phi_ {k}(t) = w^{k}\sum_ {n\geq 0}(-1)^{n}(kt)^{n}, \quad \left\lvert t \right\rvert&lt; \frac{1}{k} .\)</p> <p>One might be tempted to recombine the (convergent) Taylor expansion of $\phi_ {k}$ to give $\phi(t)$. It amounts to considering the well-defined <strong>formal series</strong> \(\tilde{\phi}(t) := \sum_ {n\geq 0}(-1)^{n} b_ {n} t^{n}, \quad b_ {n}:= \sum_ {k\geq 0}k^{n} w^{k}.\) We see that $b_ {n}$ is convergent since \(\lim_{ k \to \infty } \frac{(k+1)^{n}w^{k+1}}{k^{n}w^{k}} = w &lt;1 \text{ by construction}.\)</p> <p>However, it turns out that <strong>this formal series is divergent!</strong></p> <p>To see this, make the substitution $w = e^{ s }$. Then, since $\text{Re }w &lt;1$, we have \(b_ {0}=(1-w)^{-1} = (1-e^{ s })^{-1}\) and \(b_ {n} = \left( w \frac{d}{dw} \right)^{n}b_ {0} = \left( \frac{d}{ds} \right)^{n} b_ {0}.\) There is an easy way to tell if a series has non-zero radius of convergence, by some kind of a “dominance criterion”. If the series of study $a_ {n}$ is dominated by $AB^{n}$ where $A,B$ are real and $A,B&gt;0$, namely for all but finite $n$ we have $\left\lvert a_ {n} \right\rvert \leq AB^{n}$. Then the formal series \(F(\xi) := \sum(-1)^{n} a_ {n} \frac{\xi^{n}}{n!}\) would have infinite radius of convergence. <strong>$F$ can be seen as a map of the formal series to a function of $\xi$, note that we have inserted a factor of $1 / n!$ into the sum to make is more convergent</strong>. In our case of $b_ {n}$, we see that \(F(\xi) = \sum(-1)^{n} b_ {n} \frac{\xi^{n}}{n!} = \sum(-1)^{n} \frac{\xi^{n}}{n!}\left( \frac{d}{d s} \right)^{n} b_ {0}(s) = b_ {0}(s-\xi) = \frac{1}{1-e^{ s-\xi }} .\) This functions has finite radius of convergence, since the last expression in the equation above diverges at $\xi=s+2\pi i \mathbb{Z}$. The radius of convergence is not infinite! Thus $\tilde{\phi}$ must have zero radius of convergence.</p> <hr/> <p>Now the question is to understand the relation between $\tilde{\phi}$ and $\phi$. We shall see in this note that the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Borel-Laplace</code> summation is a way of going from the divergent formal series $\tilde{\phi}$ to the finite function $\phi$. $\tilde{\phi}$ is actually the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">asymptotic expansion</code> of $\phi(t)$ at $t=0$. We shall explain what it means next.</p> <p>We can already observe that the moduli of the coefficients $b_ {n}$ satisfy \(\left\lvert b_ {n} \right\rvert &lt;AB^{n} n! ,\quad n \in \mathbb{N}\) for some $A,B&gt;0$. Such inequalities are called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">1-Gevrey estimates</code> for the formal series $\tilde{\phi}(t)=\sum b_ {n}t^{n}$.</p> <p>We remark that, since the original function $\phi(t)$ is not holomorphic (nor meromorphic) in any neighborhood of 0, because of the accumulation at the origin of the sequence of simple poles $- \frac{1}{k}$. Thus it would be very surprising to find a positive radius of convergence for $\tilde{\phi}$.</p> <hr/> <p>Resurgence theory can also be used to study power series of the form \(\sum_ {i} \left( \sum_ {j} a_ {ij}t^{j} \right) e^{ -c_ {j} / t }\) note that the variable $t$ appears at two places, once in the series and once in the exponent. The exponent term is the small correction that is invisible to Taylor expansion at $t=0$, and the formal series in the parenthesis diverges.</p> <p>There are many examples of such series in physics. For example, the series could represent the solution of an ordinary differential equation, or the value of some integral, or the perturbative results. In the below is a list of where you might find series like this:</p> <ul> <li>Normal forms for dynamical systems</li> <li>Gauge theory of singular connections</li> <li>Quantization of symplectic and Poisson manifolds</li> <li>Floer homology and Fukaya categories</li> <li>Knot invariants</li> <li>Wall-crossing and stability conditions in algebraic geometry</li> <li>Spectral networks</li> <li>WKB approximation in quantum mechanics</li> <li>Perturbative expansions in quantum field theory (QFT).</li> </ul> <p>There has been some recent work in the physics literature suggesting the possibility that the divergent series obtained from the perturbative expansion may have more information about the true nature of the QFT that one might naively expect.</p> <p>In the next note we will dive into the details of resurgence theory, beginning with the differential algebra $(\mathbb{C}[[1 / z]],\partial)$.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="PureMath"/><category term="CategoryTheory"/><category term="Notes"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An example by Poincare]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introduction to Resurgence Lecture 3</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Resurgence-Lecture-3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction to Resurgence Lecture 3"/><published>2023-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Resurgence-Lecture-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Resurgence-Lecture-3/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="the-differential-algebra">The differential algebra</h3> <p>It will be convenient for us to set $z = 1/t$ in order to “work at $\infty$” rather than at the origin, since we will often talk about compactified spaces. This means that we shall deal with expansions involving <em>non-positive</em> integer powers of the indeterminate. We denote the set of all the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">formal power series</code>, i.e., polynomials in $1 / z$ by \(\mathbb{C}[\![z^{-1}]\!] = \left\{ \phi=\sum_ {n\geq 0}a_ {n}z^{-n} \,\middle\vert\, a_ {i} \in \mathbb{C} \right\}.\) This is a vector space with basis $1, z^{-1},z^{-2}$, etc. It is also an algebra when we take into account the Cauchy product \(\left( \sum a_ {n}z^{-n} \right) \left( \sum b_ {n} z^{-n} \right) = \sum c_ {n} z^{-n}, \quad c_ {n} = \sum_ {p+q=n} a_ {p} b_ {q}.\)</p> <p>The derivation \(\partial = \frac{d}{d z}\) further makes it a <em>differential algebra</em>, which simply means $\partial$ is a linear map which satisfied the Leibniz rules.</p> <p>This is the derivative in terms of $z$, it is natural to ask what is the derivative in terms of $t$. The answer is straightforward, \(\partial = \frac{d}{d z} = \frac{d}{d t^{-1}} = \frac{d}{-t^{-2}dt} =-t^{2} \frac{d}{d t} .\) Then, in mathematical terminology, there is an isomorphism of differential algebra between $(\mathbb{C}[[z^{-1}]],\partial)$ and $(\mathbb{C}[[t]],\partial)$.</p> <hr/> <p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">standard valuation</code>, or sometimes called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">order</code>, on $\mathbb{C}[[z^{-1}]]$ is the map \(\text{val}: \mathbb{C}[\![z^{-1}]\!] \to \mathbb{N} \cup \infty\) defined by $\text{val }(0)=\infty$ and \(\boxed{ \text{val }(\phi) := \text{min } \left\{ n\in \mathbb{N} \,\middle\vert\, a_ {n}\neq 0 \right\} ,\quad \phi =\sum a_ {n} z^{-n} \neq 0. }\)</p> <p>For $\nu \in\mathbb{N}$, we will use the notation \(z^{-\nu}\mathbb{C}[\![z^{-1}]\!] = \left\{ \sum_ {n\geq \nu} a_ {n}z^{-n} \,\middle\vert\, a_ {\nu},a_ {n+1},\dots \in \mathbb{C} \right\}.\)</p> <p>This is the set of all the complex polynomials in $z^{-1}$ such that the standard valuation is no less than $\nu$.</p> <p>From the viewpoint of the ring structure, ${\frak I} = z^{-1}\mathbb{C}[[z^{-1}]]$ is the maximal ideal of the ring $\mathbb{C}[[z^{-1}]]$. It is often referred to as the <em>formal series without constant term</em>.</p> <p>It is obvious that \(\text{val }(\partial \phi) \geq \text{val }(\phi)+1\) with equality iff there is no constant term.</p> <hr/> <p>With the help of the standard valuation, we can introduce the concept of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">distance</code> into the ring of the formal series. Define \(d(\phi,\psi) := 2^{-\text{val }(\phi-\psi)},\quad \phi,\psi \in \mathbb{C}[\![z^{-1}]\!]\) as the distance between $\phi$ and $\psi$. It can only take discrete values, such as $1, 1 / 2, 1 / 4,$ etc.</p> <p>With the definition of distance, $\mathbb{C}[[z^{-1}]]$ becomes a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">complete metric space</code>. The topology induced by this distance is called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Krull topology</code> or the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">topology of the formal convergence</code> (or the ${\frak I}$-adic topology). It provides a simple way of using the language of topology to describe certain algebraic properties.</p> <p>We mention that a sequence $\phi_ {n}$ of formal series is a Cauchy sequence iff for each $i\in\mathbb{N}$, the $i$-the coefficient is stationary, namely the $i$-th coefficient of $\phi_ {n}$ becomes a constant when $n$ is larger than certain natural number.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="PureMath"/><category term="CategoryTheory"/><category term="Notes"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The differential algebra]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Note-on-Cutoff-Kinks</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Note-on-Cutoff-Kinks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Note-on-Cutoff-Kinks"/><published>2023-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Note-on-Cutoff-Kinks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Note-on-Cutoff-Kinks/"><![CDATA[<p>Let $H’$ be the regularized Hamiltonian in the Kink sector, $H$ be that in the vacuum sector. Then $D_ {f}$ is the Morphism that maps from $H’$ to $H$. It should be invertible since there is no loss of information in the process, namely there should exist another map from $H$ to $H’$. Regard different sectors as objects in a category, this category is defined by a (classical) Lagrangian with a quantization functor (maybe), together with a lattice, or equivalently a momentum cutoff $\Lambda$. The map from $H$ to $H’$ is given by \(\boxed { H' = \mathcal{D}_ {f}^{\dagger} H \mathcal{D}_ {f}, }\) where $\mathcal{D}_ {f}$ is the shift operator defined by a function $f$, which usually corresponds to certain classical solitonic solutions.</p> <p>The</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Let $H’$ be the regularized Hamiltonian in the Kink sector, $H$ be that in the vacuum sector. Then $D_ {f}$ is the Morphism that maps from $H’$ to $H$. It should be invertible since there is no loss of information in the process, namely there should exist another map from $H$ to $H’$. Regard different sectors as objects in a category, this category is defined by a (classical) Lagrangian with a quantization functor (maybe), together with a lattice, or equivalently a momentum cutoff $\Lambda$. The map from $H$ to $H’$ is given by \(\boxed { H' = \mathcal{D}_ {f}^{\dagger} H \mathcal{D}_ {f}, }\) where $\mathcal{D}_ {f}$ is the shift operator defined by a function $f$, which usually corresponds to certain classical solitonic solutions.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introduction to Resurgence Lecture 1</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Resurgence-Lecture-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction to Resurgence Lecture 1"/><published>2023-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Resurgence-Lecture-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Introduction-to-Resurgence-Lecture-1/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="motivation">Motivation</h3> <p>Why do I want to spend time on this subject? Because they are super interesting!</p> <p>But I should maybe say more about it, so that in the future if I were to apply for some research grant, when someone who knows absolutely nothing about resurgence and its application but who decides whether to give me the money, asks me why is this project important, what use does it have and, eventually, why should I give you the money, then I can come back here and just copy the answer. I would say that god knows I have already wasted too much time on grant applications… but thank god I am atheist.</p> <p>The following is an incomplete list of the potential applications of resurgence theory.</p> <ul> <li>Normal forms for dynamical systems</li> <li>Gauge theory of singular connections</li> <li>Quantization of symplectic and Poisson manifolds</li> <li>Floer homology and Fukaya categories</li> <li>Knot invariants</li> <li>Wall-crossing and stability conditions in algebraic geometry</li> <li>Spectral networks</li> <li>WKB approximation in quantum mechanics</li> <li><strong>Perturbative expansions in quantum field theory (QFT)</strong></li> </ul> <p>The most surprising result, at least for me, of resurgence theory in QFT is that one can uncover the non-perturbative results from perturbative expansion alone! Usually to find the non-perturbative results one need to use anything but perturbative results, such as the topology of the vacuum manifold, the homotopy of the solutions to the equation of motion (instanton solutions, etc.), on and on. But resurgence theory lets us to get the non-perturbative results, for instance the contribution of instantons, from analytical continuation of the perturbative results! On the one hand, it is like black magic; on the other hand, I guess I shouldn’t be too surprised since if we know all the perturbative expansions then we know everything about the equation of motion, which eventually contains all the non-perturbative results, so in principal the perturbative expansion should be able to generate the non-perturbative results. But that is only in principal. It is still jaw-dropping to see it actually happen.</p> <p>And I guess it is impossible to make sense out of perturbation theory <strong>without</strong> knowing some of the resurgence theory. After all, is we consider enough terms in perturbative expansion, the power series in coupling actually diverges, so why would it make any sense to just consider the first few terms? Claiming they give the dominant results would also be ridiculous. The answer lies in resurgence theory.</p> <hr/> <p>H. Poincare mentions the so-called “a kind of misunderstanding between geometers and astronomers about the meaning of the word convergence”, He proposed a simple example, the two series \(\sum \frac{1000^{n}}{n!} \text{ and }\sum \frac{n!}{1000^{n}},\) Poincare says that for geometers, namely mathematicians in his time, the first one converges because at large $n$ the terms gets smaller and smaller. But for astronomers the first one is as good as divergent since the next terms doesn’t get smaller until $n$ is larger than $1000$. For them the second series diverges because the first $1000$ terms decreases quickly.</p> <p>He then proposes to reconcile both points of view by clarifying the role that divergent series (in the sense of geometers) can play in the approximation of certain functions. This is the origin of the modern theory of asymptotic expansion.</p> <hr/> <p>In this note we shall focus on <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">formal power series</code>, such as the Stirling series. Thus the previous example should be written as \(\sum \frac{1000^{n}}{n!}t^{n} \text{ and }\sum \frac{n!}{1000^{n}}t^{n}\) where the first one has <strong>infinite</strong> <strong>radius of convergence</strong> while the second one has <strong>zero radius of convergence</strong>. For us, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">divergent series</code> will usually mean a formal power series with zero radius of convergence.</p> <p>First we will speak of the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Borel-Laplace sumamtion</code>, which obtains a function from a divergent formal series. The relation between the obtained function and the original power series is an example of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">asymptotic expansion of Gevrey type</code>. We shall also introduce the phenomenon for which J. Ecalle coined the name <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">resurgence</code> at the beginning of the 1980s.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="analytic-continuation-and-monodromy">Analytic Continuation and Monodromy</h3> <p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Formal power series</code> is a generalization of normal power series, or polynomial, in the sense that we consider a power series of infinite order and don’t care if it is convergent or not. Provided a ring $R$, consider the set of formal power series in $X$, denoted by $R[[X]]$, is another ring, in the same sense that all the polynomials over $R$ forms another ring (for example, multiply one polynomial to another gives as another polynomial). It is called the <strong>ring of formal power series in the variable $X$ over $R$</strong>.</p> <p>We say a complex-valued function $f:\Omega \to \mathbb{C}$ is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">analytic</code> if $f$ is represented by a convergent power series expansion on a neighborhood around every point $a\in\Omega$.</p> <p>We say a complex-valued function $f:\Omega \to \mathbb{C}$ is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">holomorphic</code> iff it satisfied Cauchy-Riemann relation, which is equivalent to $\partial f/\partial \overline{z}=0$ . If we regard $z$ and $\overline{z}$ as independent variables, a holomorphic function $f$ is only a function of $z$ not $\overline{z}$.</p> <p>A differential manifold is a topological space (given by closed sets and all that stuff) with differential structure, which practically means that you can find a way to do derivatives on the manifold. A n-Dimensional real (Complex) manifold is locally homeomorphic to $\mathbb{R}^N (\mathbb{C}^n)$, plus the condition that the transition from one chart (coordinate system) to another is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">homeomorphic (holomorphic)</code> and vice versa.</p> <p>An <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">open disk</code> of radius $r$ around $z_0$ is the set of points $z$ on $\mathbb{C}$ that satisfies \(|z-z_0| &lt; r.\) A <strong>open deleted disk of radius $r$ around $z_0$</strong> is the set of points with \(0 &lt; |z-z_0| &lt; r.\) a deleted disk is also called a punctured disk.</p> <p>A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">complex atlas</code> on a 2-dimensional manifold is a set of holomorphically compatible charts which cover the manifold. Two complex charts $\mathfrak{U}$, $\mathfrak{U}’$ are said to be <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">analytically equivalent</code> if any atlas in $\mathfrak{U}$ is holomorphically compatible with any other atlas in $\mathfrak{U}’$.</p> <p>By a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">complex structure</code> on a manifold, we mean an equivalent class of analytically equivalent complex atlases on the manifold. If we give a manifold a complex atlas, then we have given it a complex structure.</p> <p>A Riemann surface is a pair $(X,\Sigma)$ where $X$ is a connected 2-dimensional manifold and $\Sigma$ is a complex structure on $X$. The simplest Riemann surface is the complex plane itself.</p> <hr/> <ul> <li>$\mathbb{C} P^n$ Model: The (n+1)-tuple $z = (z^0,\cdots,z^n)$ defines a vector in space $\mathbb{C}^{n+1}$. Define a equivalence relation $\sim$ between two vectors, \((u^0,\cdots,u^n) \sim (v^0,\cdots,v^n) \text{ if } \exists \lambda\neq 0 \in \mathbb{C} \text{ so that } \mathbf{u} = \lambda \mathbf{}{v}\) then \(\mathbb{C} P^{n} \equiv (\mathbb{C}^{n+1}-\{0\})/\sim,\) and the $n+1$ numbers are call <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">homogeneous coordinates</code> and is denoted by $[z^0,\cdots,z^n]$. We can make one of them constantly equal to 1, then only the rest are really coordinates, it is called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">inhomogeneous coordinates</code>.</li> </ul> <p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Meromouphic functions</code> are functions holomorphic except at poles.</p> <p>A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">domain</code> in $\mathbb{C}$ is a connected non-empty open subset of $\mathbb{C}$.</p> <hr/> <p><strong>Riemann Sphere</strong></p> <p>There are two ways to think of $\overline{C} \equiv \mathbb{C} \cup {\infty}$, i.e. the complex plane compactified, by adding a point called infinity, $\infty$ is not included in $\mathbb{C}$.</p> <ul> <li>complex projective plane $\mathbb{C}P^1$.</li> <li>a 2D sphere $\mathbb{S}^2$. The coordinates is given by the stereographic projection, except for the north pole $N$, $\pi : \mathbb{S}^2-{N} \to \mathbb{C}$.</li> </ul> <p>The space $\overline{\mathbb{C}}$ has the structure of e Riemann surface and it is called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Riemann sphere</code>. We can introduce two charts on the Riemann sphere, \(\mathfrak{U}_1 = \mathbb{C},\quad \mathfrak{U}_2 = \mathbb{C}^\ast \cup \{\infty\}\) where $\mathbb{C}^\ast$ is the punctured complex plane, $\mathbb{C}^\ast \equiv \mathbb{C} - {0}$.</p> <p><strong>Theorem.</strong> A function is meromorphic on $\mathbb{C}$ iff its restriction on $\mathbb{C}$ is a rational function.</p> <p>By the restriction of a function, we mean that to restrict the domain so that the it is well defined, no singularities. For example, the function $f:x\to 1/x$ has a singularity at $x=0$, then if we want something which is just like $f$ but has no singularity, we can just restrict the domain to $\mathbb{R} - {0}$, which is said to be a restriction of $f$.</p> <p>A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">germ</code> of functions at a point $\mathbb{C}$ is a set of function defined in the neighborhood of $a$ which all have the same Taylor expansion. A more mathematical definition is as following.</p> <p>Use $\mathcal{O}(a)$ to denote the set of functions which are defined in a neighborhood of $a$ and is holomorphic at $a$. Define an equivalence relation $\sim$ so that if $f\sim g$ for $f,g \in \mathcal{O}(a)$, then $f,g$ are identical on some neighborhood of a. The equivalence class is called a germ of holomorphic functions at $a$.</p> <p>Intuitively, the germ of a function tells us how a function behaves locally at point $a$.</p> <hr/> <p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Fundamental Uniqueness Theorem (FUT)</code> for holomorphic functions:</p> <p><strong>Theorem.</strong> If $f,g$ are holomorphic functions on a domain $D\in\mathbb{C}$ and $f \sim g$ for some point $a\in D$, namely f and g are in the same germ at a, then f is identical to g on $D$.</p> <p>The germ of $f$ will be denoted by $\overline{f}$, if there is no ambiguity about around which point it is defined.</p> <hr/> <p><strong>Analytic Continuation, Monodromy</strong></p> <p>First we introduce the analytic continuation in a different way, more formal and more mathematical. We begin by defining <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pairs</code>. The idea is that, a function is not only defined by the values but also the domain on which it is defined.</p> <p>A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pair</code> $(U,f)$ is a non-zero open disk $U\subset \mathbb{C}$ (why does it has to be open? I don’t know.) and a function, holomorphic on $U$, such that the radius of $U$ is the maximum radius of convergence of the series expansion of $f$. The center of the pair is the center of $U$. Usually $U$ will stop at some singular point.</p> <p>Another concept is adjacency, two pairs $(U,f)$ and $(V,g)$ are said to be <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">adjacent</code> if $U\cap V \neq 0$ and $f \equiv g$ on $U\cap V$.</p> <p>If there is a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">finite</code> sequence of pairs $(U_i,f_i),\quad i = 0,1,\cdots, n$ so that for all $i$, $(U_i,f_i)$ is adjacent to $(U_{i\pm 1},f_{i\pm 1})$, then $(U_0,f_0)$ is said to be the analytical continuation of $(U_n,f_n)$.</p> <p>We can define a analytical continuation along a curve $\gamma: [0,1] \to \mathbb{C}$. The definition is kind of intuitive so I will skip it here. Now the question is, is the analytical continued function $(U_n,f_n)$ dependent on the path? The answer is the monodromy theorem:</p> <p><strong>Theorem.</strong> If the two path are homotopic, then the analytical continuation results to the same functions.</p> <p>If in any doubt, just think of the $\ln{z}$ function.</p> <hr/> <p><strong>Linear Differential System</strong></p> <p>A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">linear system</code> is short for a complex linear ordinary differential system. A linear system of order p is a system with p first order ordinary differential equations.</p> <p>\(\frac{dy(x)}{dx} = A(x) y(x),\quad y(x) = \begin{pmatrix} y_1(x)\\ \vdots \\ y_p(x) \end{pmatrix}\) where $y(x)$ is a column vector of functions, and $A$ is the $p\times p$ coefficient matrix. The system is referred to as $(S)$.</p> <p>We used $\mathbb{C}(x)$ to denote the field of complex rational functions, and $\mathscr{M}(D)$ the field of meromorphic functions on domain $D$, and $\mathscr{O}(D)$ the ring of holomorphic functions on domain $D$.</p> <p>A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">fundamental solution</code> of $(S)$ is a $p\times p$ matrix whose columns are $\mathbb{C}$-linear independent solutions to $(S)$.</p> <p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Wronskian</code> for $n$ functions are defined to be \(W(f_1,\cdots, f_n)(x) \equiv \begin{vmatrix} f_1(x) &amp; \cdots &amp; f_n(x)\\ f'_1(x)&amp; \cdots &amp; f'_n(x)\\ \cdots \\ f^{(n-1)}(x) &amp; \cdots &amp; f^{(n-1)}(x) \end{vmatrix}.\)</p> <p>Let $\Sigma= { a_1,\cdots,a_n }\subset \overline{\mathbb{C}}$ be the set of singular points of $(S)$. Let $U_\Sigma \equiv \overline{\mathbb{C}}\backslash \Sigma$.</p> <p>Recall a nice property of Wronskian: Let $\mathscr{D}$ a domain in $U_\Sigma$, $W$ a $p\times p$ solution of $(S)$, the following are equivalent:</p> <ul> <li>W is a fundamental solution of $(S)$</li> <li>$\det{W(x)}\neq 0$ for some $x \in \mathscr{D}$</li> <li>$\det{W(x)}\neq 0$ for all $x \in \mathscr{D}$</li> </ul> <p>In other words, the Wronskian is either nonzero on the entire domain, or identically zero.</p> <hr/> <p><strong>Differential Galois Theory</strong></p> <p>A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">differential field</code> $(k,\partial)$ is a field $k$ with derivation. A \hl{differential homomorphism} $\phi:(k_1,\partial)\to(k_2,\partial)$ from $k_1$ to $k_2$ is a field homomorphism that commutates with $\partial$. A triple $(k_1, \phi, k_2)$ is called a differential extension. $k_2$ is also called a differential extension of $k_1$.</p> <p>A differential system \(\partial y = A y\) where $A$ is a $p \times p$ matrix.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="Math"/><category term="Transseries"/><category term="Notes"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Motivation]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Categorical Equivalence and the Renormalization Group</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Categorical-Equivalence-and-the-Renormalization-Group/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Categorical Equivalence and the Renormalization Group"/><published>2023-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Categorical-Equivalence-and-the-Renormalization-Group</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Categorical-Equivalence-and-the-Renormalization-Group/"><![CDATA[<p><em>Disclaimer: Nothing in this note is original.</em></p> <p>A short introduction about sheaf can be found <a href="https://www.mathlimbo.net/blog/2023/Basic-Algebraic-Geometry-6/">here</a>.</p> <h4 id="gauged-linear-sigma-model">Gauged linear sigma model</h4> <p>A gauged linear sigma model (GLSM) is a type of quantum field theory that incorporates both gauge symmetry and a set of scalar fields which interact with each other through a potential that is usually taken to be a function of the sum of the squares of the scalar fields. These models are a generalization of the linear sigma models that were originally introduced to describe the dynamics of pions in particle physics.</p> <p>The term “linear” in this context refers to the fact that the potential energy function for the scalar fields is quadratic, at least around the vacuum of the theory. This means that the interactions can be written in terms of fields and their derivatives in a polynomial form that does not exceed second degree when expanded about the vacuum expectation value.</p> <p>Often, GLSMs are discussed in the context of supersymmetry. This means that for every boson (like the scalar fields and gauge fields in the model), there is a corresponding fermion. Supersymmetric GLSMs are particularly interesting for string theory and the study of Calabi-Yau manifolds.</p> <p>In essence, the gauged linear sigma model allows for the study of a wide array of phenomena including spontaneous symmetry breaking, phase transitions, and the dynamics of topological defects. By gauging a symmetry, you add a rich structure to the model that includes interactions mediated by gauge bosons and the possibility of incorporating richer topological properties.</p> <p>A key feature of GLSMs is that they can have a “Higgs phase,” where the gauge symmetry is spontaneously broken and the gauge bosons acquire mass via the Higgs mechanism, and a “Coulomb phase,” where the gauge symmetry is unbroken and the gauge bosons remain massless. Transitions between these phases can often be studied using GLSMs, providing insights into non-perturbative aspects of quantum field theories.</p> <h4 id="toric-variety">Toric variety</h4> <p>We all know what a variety is. So what is a toric variety?</p> <p>A toric variety is a type of variety that is built from combinatorial objects known as fans, which are collections of cones. Toric varieties are particularly nice because they provide a bridge between algebraic geometry and combinatorics, and they are also rich in geometric properties.</p> <p><strong>Algebraic Torus.</strong></p> <p>Start with an algebraic torus $( \mathbb{C}^* )^n$, which is the product of $n$ copies of the multiplicative group $\mathbb{C}^* = \mathbb{C} \setminus {0}$. This group acts on itself by multiplication, and this action can be extended to act on other algebraic varieties.</p> <p><strong>Fans and Cones.</strong></p> <p>A fan is a set of cones (not in the usual sense of solid geometry, but in the sense of vector spaces). These cones are generated by a set of vectors in $\mathbb{R}^n$ that satisfy certain combinatorial conditions – they must be strongly convex (no line can be contained in a cone), and the intersection of any two cones in the fan must be a face of each. The dimension of the toric variety is equal to the dimension of the space where the fan lives.</p> <p><strong>Construction of Toric Varieties.</strong></p> <p>Each cone in the fan corresponds to an affine variety that is invariant under the action of a subtorus of $( \mathbb{C}^* )^n$. The toric variety is constructed by “gluing” these affine varieties together in a way that corresponds to how their cones intersect.</p> <p><strong>Divisors and Line Bundles.</strong> Toric varieties are also interesting because there is a correspondence between the combinatorial data of the fan and the divisor class group of the variety. This makes the calculation of certain cohomological and geometric properties much simpler than in general varieties.</p> <p>A key feature of toric varieties is that they come with a lot of symmetry – namely, the action of the torus. This symmetry makes them easier to study and gives them a rich structure. Toric varieties have applications in many areas of mathematics, including combinatorics, symplectic geometry, and mirror symmetry in string theory. They serve as local models in the Minimal Model Program and are also used in the study of singularities.</p> <p>For a concrete example, consider the complex projective space $\mathbb{CP}^n$, which is a toric variety. The fan for $\mathbb{CP}^n$ consists of cones that correspond to the origin and the standard basis vectors in $\mathbb{R}^n$, as well as all their faces. The rich interplay between the algebraic and combinatorial structures of toric varieties makes them a fascinating subject of study in modern algebraic geometry.</p> <h4 id="stacks">Stacks</h4> <p>Let $\mathcal{T}$ be the category of topological spaces, where the objects are topological spaces and the morphisms are continuous maps.</p> <p>A <strong>groupoid fibration,</strong> or a category fibered <em>in</em> groupoids, over $\mathcal{T}$ is another category (which is a groupoid) $\mathcal{X}$, together with a functor \(F: \mathcal{X} \to \mathcal{T}\) such that there exists a pullback and the pull back is unique. First, some terminologies. If the functor maps $X \in \mathcal{X}$ to $T \in \mathcal{T}$ then we say that $X$ lies over $T$, or that $X$ is a $\mathcal{X}$-family parametrized by $T$, and we write $X / T$. If the morphism $\eta: X \to Y$ is mapped by $F$ to $f: T\to S$ then we say that $\eta$ lies over $f$, or $\eta$ <em>covers</em> $f$. The requirement of pullback essentially says that for every $\mathcal{X}$-family $X / T$ and a morphism $T’ \to T$ there exists another $\mathcal{X}$-family $X’ / T’$ such and such. And this pullback is essentially unique. $X’ / T’$ is said to be the pullback of $X / T$ via the continuous map $f$. We use notations \(X' = f^{\ast } X \text{ or } X' = X \mid _ {T'}.\)</p> <p>Groupoid fibration captures two notions at once:</p> <ul> <li>isomorphism of families. By the arrows in $\mathcal{X}$ (Since $\mathcal{X}$ is a groupoid).</li> <li>pullback.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="Geometry"/><category term="Frankel"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Disclaimer: Nothing in this note is original.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Homotopy, Extension, and some topology of SU(N)</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Homotopy-Extension-SU(N)/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Homotopy, Extension, and some topology of SU(N)"/><published>2023-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Homotopy-Extension-SU(N)</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Homotopy-Extension-SU(N)/"><![CDATA[<p><em>Disclaimer: Nothing in this note is original.</em></p> <h2 id="homotopies-and-extensions">Homotopies and Extensions</h2> <p>The problem of extension in homotopy typically deals with the following question: given a continuous map defined on a subspace of a topological space, can it be extended to a continuous map on the entire space? Take the extension of a function on a sphere for example. Let $\mathbb{S}^{1}$ be the equator of a $\mathbb{S}^{2}$, and a continuous map $f$ define on $\mathbb{S}^{1}$: \(f: \mathbb{S}^{1} \to \mathbb{R}.\) The extension problem would be, can you find a function \(F: \mathbb{S}^{2} \to \mathbb{R}\) such that the restriction of $F$ on $\mathbb{S}^{1}$ gives $f$? The ability to extend $f$ depends on its homotopy properties. For instance, if $f$ represents a simple loop around the equator, it may or may not be extendable based on how it “wraps around” the sphere. Certain topological features of the function $f$, such as its winding number or degrees, can serve as <strong>obstructions</strong> to extending it over the entire sphere. In this particular example, $f$ is extendable to the whole sphere if it has zero winding, otherwise the non-zero winding will cause some singularity when extending it to the whole $\mathbb{S}^{2}$.</p> <hr/> <p>Now, consider a sphere of arbitrary dimension $n$, and consider it as the boundary of some $n+1$ dimensional disk $\mathbb{D}^{n+1}$ (a ball if $n&gt;0$). Let $M$ be a $n$ dimensional manifold. We have the following simple observation.</p> <p><strong>Extension Theorem.</strong> The function \(f:\mathbb{S}^{k} \to M^{n}\) is homotopic to a constant map iff $f$ can be extended to a map of the ball \(F: \mathbb{D}^{k+1} \to M.\) The proof is rather intuitive, just think of the homotopy as shrinking $\mathbb{S}^{k}$ all the way to the center of the circle.</p> <p>The extension theorem is important when discussing <strong>defects</strong>.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="covering-homotopy">Covering homotopy</h2> <p>Let $\pi: E \to M$ be a vector bundle and $f: W \to E$ be a map of a space $W$ into the bundle space $E$. Then the composition \(W \xrightarrow{f}E \xrightarrow{\pi} M\) defines a map $\overline{f}$ from $W$ to $M$, \(\overline{f} := \pi \,\circ\, f.\)</p> <p>Now, let $\overline{F}: \overline{f}\to \overline{f_ {1}}$ be a homotopy (a series of continuous functions parametrized by $t$ from $\overline{f}$ to $\overline{f_ {1}}$), we claim that we can <strong>cover the homotopy</strong> $\overline{F}$ by a homotopy of the original map $F: f\to f_ {1}$. That is, there is a map \(F: W\times [0,1] \to E\) such that for $w \in W$, \(F(w,0)=f(w),\quad F(w,1)=f_ {1}(w).\) The trick to prove the existence of covering of a homotopy is to find a way to lift the homotopy from $M$ to $E$. To be specific, consider a fixed point $w \in W$ and look at the curve \(\overline{C}:t \in [0,1] \to \overline{F}(w,t)\) in $M$. We need to find a unique lifting of $\overline{C}$ to a curve $C$ in $E$. The way to achieve that is to endow the bundle a connection $\omega$, then require $C$ to be the <strong>horizontal lift</strong>.</p> <p><em>Note that if $\overline{f}$ is homotopic to a constant map $p_ {0}$, it need not be that $f$ will be homotopic to a constant map</em>.</p> <p>What we have said for a vector bundle can also be shown to hold for a principal fiber bundle.</p> <p>It turns out that one can cover homotopies in <strong>any</strong> fiber bundle, without any use of a connection. In fact, one generalizes the notion of a fiber bundle to that of a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">fiber space</code>. This is a space $P$ equipped with a map $\pi: P\to M$ such that <strong>homotopies can always be covered</strong>. Such spaces need not be local products.</p> <h2 id="some-topology-of-sun">Some Topology of $SU(n)$</h2> <p>$SU(n)$ is represented by $N \times N$ complex matrices acting on $\mathbb{C}^{n}$. Since each $g \in SU(N)$ is unitary, $SU(N)$ sends the unit sphere $\mathbb{S}^{2N-1} \subset \mathbb{C}^{n}$ \(\mathbb{S}^{2N-1} = \left\lbrace z \in \mathbb{C}^{N} \,\middle\vert\, \left\lvert z_ {1} \right\rvert^{2} + \dots + \left\lvert z_ {N} \right\rvert^{2}=1 \right\rbrace\) into itself. The action is also transitive (meaning any two points on $\mathbb{S}^{2N-1}$ can be connected by some group action). The isometry group for the point $(1,0,\dots,0)$ is clearly \(\begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; SU(N-1) \end{bmatrix}\) which we shall briefly denote simply by $SU(N-1)$.</p> <p>We have \(\mathbb{S}^{2N-1} \cong \frac{SU(N)}{SU(2N-1)}.\)</p> <p>and in fact $SU(N)$ is a principal $SU(N − 1)$ bundle over $\mathbb{S}^{2N-1}$, with fiber at each point $p\in M$ being the little group of $p$. Thus we write \(SU(N-1)\to SU(N) \to \mathbb{S}^{2N-1}\) <strong>Theorem.</strong> If $F\to P \to M$ is a fiber bundle with connected $M$ and connected $F$, then $P$ is also connected.</p> <p>As a corollary, $SU(N)$ is connected. To see that, note $SU(1)$ is a single point, $SU(2)$ is a $3$-sphere and is connected, as are all $k$-spheres for $k\geq 3$. From \(SU(2) \to SU(3) \to \mathbb{S}^{5}\) we see that $SU(3)$ is connected. The connectness of higher $SU$ groups follow from induction.</p> <p>Another example of the above theorem is the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Hopf fibration</code>. The Hopf fibration is a fiber bundle where the total space $P$ is $\mathbb{S}^{3}$, the base space $M$ is $\mathbb{S}^{2}$ and the fiber $F$ is $\mathbb{S}^{1}$.</p> <hr/> <p>Recall that we say that $M$ is simply connected provided every map of a circle into $M$ is homotopic to a constant map. During the homotopy, the closed curve gets “contracted” or “deformed” to the point.</p> <p><strong>Theorem.</strong> Let $F\to P \to M$ be a fiber bundle whose fiber and base space are both simply connected. Then $P$ is simply connected.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="Geometry"/><category term="Frankel"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Disclaimer: Nothing in this note is original.]]></summary></entry></feed>