<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-10-21T06:36:50+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Baiyang Zhang</title><subtitle>A place dedicated to sharing insights and reflections on mathematics, physics, and social sciences. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Discussion with Hui</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/HuiDiscussion1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Discussion with Hui"/><published>2023-04-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/HuiDiscussion1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/HuiDiscussion1/"><![CDATA[<p>The equation (2.26) reads \(\pi_ {0}\left\lvert{\psi}\right\rangle _ {i+1}=- \frac{1}{\sqrt{ Q_ {0} }}P \left\lvert{\psi}\right\rangle _ {i},\) to inverse it, we need to inverse \(\boxed { \pi_ {0}=-i \frac{ \partial }{ \partial \phi_ {0} } . }\)</p> <p>\(\frac{ \partial }{ \partial \phi_ {0} } \left\lvert{\psi}\right\rangle _ {i+1}= \frac{i}{\sqrt{ Q_ {0} }}P \left\lvert{\psi}\right\rangle _ {i}\tag{1}\) thus up to a constant of integral we have \(\boxed { \left\lvert{\psi}\right\rangle _ {i+1}=\int d\phi_ {0} \, \frac{i}{\sqrt{ Q_ {0} }}P \left\lvert{\psi}\right\rangle _ {i} + \text{const} } \tag{2}\) Using some equations, the</p> <hr/> <p>If you have $\phi_ {0}^{n}$ acting on $\left\lvert{0}\right\rangle_ {0}$ you have $-i \phi_ {0}^{n+1} / (n+1)\left\lvert{0}\right\rangle_ {0}$.</p> <p>\(\int_ {?}^{\overline{\phi}_ {0}} d\phi_ {0} \, \phi^{n}_ {0}\left\lvert{0}\right\rangle_ {0} =\frac{1}{n+1}\overline{\phi}_ {0}^{n+1}\left\lvert{0}\right\rangle _ {0}\) if you have $\phi_ {0}^{n}$ acting on $\left\lvert{\psi}\right\rangle_ {0}$ in $P\left\lvert{\psi}\right\rangle_ {i}$, you have $\phi_ {0}^{n+1} / (n+1)\left\lvert{\psi}\right\rangle_ {0}$ in $\left\lvert{\psi}\right\rangle_ {i+1}$</p> <hr/> <p>\(\left\lvert{0}\right\rangle _ {1}=\int d\phi_ {0} \, \frac{i}{\sqrt{ Q_ {0} }}P \left\lvert{0}\right\rangle _ {0} + \text{const}\tag{3}\) where \(P \left\lvert{0}\right\rangle _ {0} = -i\phi_ {0}\sum\!\!\!\!\!\!\!\!\int \; \frac{d k}{2\pi} \, \Delta_ {kB}\omega_ {k}\left\lvert{k}\right\rangle _ {0} + \frac{i}{2} \sum\!\!\!\!\!\!\!\!\int \;\frac{d^{2}k}{(2\pi)^{2}} \, \Delta_ {k_ {1}k_ {2}} (\omega_ {k_ {2}}-\omega_ {k_ {1}})\left\lvert{k_ {1}k_ {2}}\right\rangle _ {0}\) substitute into Eq.(3) we have (<strong>up to the integral constant</strong>) \(\left\lvert{0}\right\rangle _ {1}=\frac{i}{\sqrt{ Q_ {0} }}\int d\phi_ {0} \, \left( -i\phi_ {0}\sum\!\!\!\!\!\!\!\!\int \; \frac{d k}{2\pi} \, \Delta_ {kB}\omega_ {k}\left\lvert{k}\right\rangle _ {0} + \frac{i}{2} \sum\!\!\!\!\!\!\!\!\int \;\frac{d^{2}k}{(2\pi)^{2}} \, \Delta_ {k_ {1}k_ {2}} (\omega_ {k_ {2}}-\omega_ {k_ {1}})\left\lvert{k_ {1}k_ {2}}\right\rangle _ {0} \right)\) which seems to be (<strong>up to the integral constant</strong>) \(\left\lvert{0}\right\rangle _ {1}= \left( \frac{1}{2\sqrt{ Q_ {0} }}\phi^{2}_ {0}\sum\!\!\!\!\!\!\!\!\int \; \frac{d k}{2\pi} \, \Delta_ {kB}\omega_ {k}\left\lvert{k}\right\rangle _ {0} + \frac{-\phi_ {0}}{2\sqrt{ Q_ {0} }} \sum\!\!\!\!\!\!\!\!\int \;\frac{d^{2}k}{(2\pi)^{2}} \, \Delta_ {k_ {1}k_ {2}} (\omega_ {k_ {2}}-\omega_ {k_ {1}})\left\lvert{k_ {1}k_ {2}}\right\rangle _ {0} \right)\)</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="Discussion"/><category term="Hui"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The equation (2.26) reads \(\pi_ {0}\left\lvert{\psi}\right\rangle _ {i+1}=- \frac{1}{\sqrt{ Q_ {0} }}P \left\lvert{\psi}\right\rangle _ {i},\) to inverse it, we need to inverse \(\boxed { \pi_ {0}=-i \frac{ \partial }{ \partial \phi_ {0} } . }\)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Basic Algebraic Geometry Class 10</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Basic-Algebraic-Geometry-Class-10/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Basic Algebraic Geometry Class 10"/><published>2023-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Basic-Algebraic-Geometry-Class-10</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Basic-Algebraic-Geometry-Class-10/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="algebraic-varieties">Algebraic Varieties</h3> <p>Let’s take a look back at what we have talked about so far. Algebraic geometry is the study of various things defined by polynomial functions. To start with, we introduced algebraic varieties as a subspace of affine spaces. But this definition is external, since in order to talk about the variety we first need to know what it is imbedded in. We would like to study varieties intrinsically, without mentioning the embedding space, by studying the functions that could be defined on it, namely the coordinate rings.</p> <p>But the problem of affine varieties is that they don’t capture the whole picture. For example, for complex numbers, one can show that bounded sets are not affine variety, so how do you study Riemann sphere? So we want to come up with an idea that generalized affine varieties, and that is exactly what <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">algebraic varieties</code> are. They are the main actors in algebraic geometry.</p> <p>A topological/differential manifold is a reasonable topological space cover by open balls, or things similar to open balls, similar in the sense of homeomorphism. Manifolds are also equipped with their structure sheaves.</p> <p>Something similar goes with varieties. Recall that open subsets of affine varieties are unions of principal open sets, which are themselves affine varieties (in a higher dimensional space). Also affine varieties comes with structure sheaves, since they are ringed spaces.</p> <p>Thus, one would guess that algebraic varieties should be nice ringed spaces covered by open sets, which are isomorphic to affine varieties.</p> <p><strong>Definition.</strong> An (algebraic) <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">prevariety</code> is a ringed space $X$ which can be covered by finitely many affine varieties, \(X = U_{1}\cup U_{2}\cup\dots \cup U_ {n}.\)</p> <p>Note that the <strong>cover by affine open subsets</strong> is not part of the definition.</p> <p>For example, the open subset $\mathbb{A}^{2}-0$ where $0$ is the origin, is a prevariety that is not affine.</p> <p>In general, any open subsets of an affine variety is a prevariety.</p> <p>More generally, affine varieties and other prevarieties can be glued (patched) together to form new prevarieties.</p> <h3 id="gluing">Gluing</h3> <p>Given finitely many prevarieties \(\left\{ X_ {i} \,\middle\vert\, i\in I, I \text{ an index set} \right\}\) with open subsets \(U_ {i,j}\subset X_ {i},\quad U_ {j,i}\in X_ {j}\)</p> <p>and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">isomorphism</code> \(f_ {i,j}: U_ {i,i}\to U_ {i,j} \;\forall\; \, i,j\in I.\) In other words, we can glue different prevarieties together along $U_ {i,j}$. The gluing isomorphism should satisfy \(f_ {i,j}^{-1}=f_ {j,i},\quad f_ {k,j} \;\circ\; f_ {j,i}=f_ {k,i},\) where the last condition means the compatibility of gluing when more than two prevarieties are to be glued together at some point.</p> <p>For any ringed spaces, there must be a topological space and a structure sheaf, the same is true for the glued bigger prevarieties, let’s get started to define them.</p> <p>Consider the set glued together by different prevarieties, let \(X = \bigsqcup_ {i} X_ {i} / \sim , \sim \text{ the equivalence equation defined by } f_ {i,j}.\) This also gives us the natural map from the original prevarieties to the glued together prevariety, \(\iota_ {i}: X_ {i} \to X, \quad x\mapsto [x]\) where $[x]$ is the equivalence class of an element in $X_ {i}$.</p> <p>Then we topologize $X$ by indulging it the quotient topology, namely we declare a set $U\subset X$ open if $\iota_ {i}^{-1}(U)$ is open in $X_ {i}$ for all $i$.</p> <p>Finally we want to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ring</code> $X$ by introducing a structure sheaf $\mathcal{O}_ {X}$ on $X$. To do it, given some open set $U\subset X$, we need to specify what the regular functions are on $U$. To start with, U must be make of a bunch of $X_ {i}$ glued together, and we already know what regular functions are on $X_ {i}$s since they are well-defined prevarieties with structure sheaf. We also know how to turn a function on $X$ to a function on $X_ {i}$: by pull-back $\iota^{\ast}$. Thus, we can define a function of $U$ to be regular, if the pull back of the function to $X_ {i}$ that makes up $U$ are regular on every and each $X_ {i}$. Hence the following definition: \(\mathcal{O}_ {X}(U) := \left\{ \phi:: U\to k \,\middle\vert\, \;\forall\; i: \iota_ {i}^{\ast }\phi \in \mathcal{O}_ {X_ {i}}(\iota^{-1}(U)) \right\}.\) The definition looks pretty messy but the key idea is quite direct.</p> <p>$X$ is then the prevariety obtained by gluing $X_ {i}$s along $f_ {i,j}$.</p> <p>Let’s look at an example, a generalized version of Riemann sphere. Let $X_ {1,2}$ be two affine lines $\mathbb{A}^{1}$ and $U_ {1,2}$ be two open subsets defined by $\mathbb{A}^{1} - 0$ on $X_ {1,2}$ respectively, namely $X_ {1,2}$ themselves but with the origin removed. We can glue them together along the gluing function \(f_ {1,2}: x\mapsto \frac{1}{x}.\) It is hard to see the final result without drawing the picture, but I am too lazy to do it here, interested readers should try by themselves. Convince yourself that the resulting prevariety is a circle. The ideal is similar to adding a point at infinity to an affine line, and compactify it into a circle.</p> <p>The prevariety we got has a name, called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">projective line</code> $\mathbb{P}^{1}$.</p> <h3 id="morphisms">Morphisms</h3> <p>As morphisms of prevarieties one takes all of them to be the morphisms of ringed spaces. In other words, prevarieties form a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">full subcategory</code> of the category of ringed spaces. Recall that a subcategory is said to be full if the arrows (morphisms) are fully passed on to the objects in the subcategory.</p> <p>So let’s review the gluing properties of morphisms for ringed spaces. Given two ringed spaces $X$ and $Y$ and a continuous map $f: X\to Y$. Say $X$ is glued together by an open cover $U_ {i}\subset X$. Then $f$ is a global morphism from $X$ to $Y$ if $f$ restricts to local morphisms on each and every open patch of $X$, namely \(f \mid_ {U_ {1}} : U_ {1}\to Y\) is a morphism of ringed spaces.</p> <hr/> <p>The gluing of prevarieties is of key importance in the study of global properties. However, there are good gluing and bad gluing. Consider the gluing of two $\mathbb{A}^{1}$ to the projective line $\mathbb{P}^{1}$ again, which is an example of good gluing. One can construct easily a bad gluing by identity gluing function, \(X_ {1} \to X_ {2}, \quad x \mapsto x \text{ instead of } x\mapsto \frac{1}{x}.\) The final result is an affine line but with <strong>two origins</strong>! One from $X_{1}$ and one from $X_ {2}$. This is bad since the solution of some polynomial functions may not be closed anymore, such as the identity function \(X_ {1} \to X_{2}, X_ {2} \to X_ {1}\) glued to \(g: X \to X\) has fixed point sets \(\left\{ x \in X \,\middle\vert\, g(x)=x \right\} = X - \left\{ 0,0 \right\}\) which is not closed.</p> <h3 id="subprevarieties">Subprevarieties</h3> <p>Recall that a prevariety is roughly speaking a ringed space cover by affine varieties. Just like groups, rings and manifolds, there exist subprevarieties. Different from groups, rings and manifolds, there are two types of subprevarieties, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">open</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">closed</code>.</p> <p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">open subvarieties</code> are easier to define since any open cover of the whole prevariety $X$ also openly covers the sub manifold, and the structure sheaf can be inherited automatically. In mathematical language, let $X = (X,\mathcal{O}_ {X})$ be a prevariety, any open set $U\subset X$ is a prevariety with structure sheaf \(\mathcal{O}_ {U} = \mathcal{O}_ {X} \mid_ {U},\) this works since sets that are open in $U$ are also open in $X$.</p> <p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">closed subvarieties</code>, on the other hand, are harder to construct, since the open sets in the whole space and in the subspace might be different. We go on to define it anyway.</p> <p>Let $Z\subset X$ be a closed subset of $X$, we can endow the structure sheaf \(\mathcal{O}_ {Z}(U) = \left\{ \phi: U\to k \,\middle\vert\, \phi \text{ is locally regular at each }x \in U \right\}.\)</p> <p>Here $\phi$ is locally regular at each $x \in U$ is there exists some open neighborhood of $x$ on which $\phi$ is regular.</p> <hr/> <p>Let $f: X\to Y$ be a prevariety morphism.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Inverse images.</strong> If $U$ is an open subvariety of $Y$ then $f^{-1}(U)$ is an open subvariety of $X$, the same goes for closed subvarieties.</li> <li><strong>Direct images.</strong> If $W$ is an open subvariety of $X$, or a closed subvariety of $X$, then the direct image $f(W)$ is in general neither.</li> </ul> <p>There is no general notion of subvarieties that are not open (or closed), for example, the union of one open subvariety and one closed subvariety.</p> <h3 id="products-affine-varieties">Products: affine varieties</h3> <p>First recall the products of algebraic sets. If $X\subset\mathbb{A}^{m}$ and $Y \subset\mathbb{A}^{n}$ are algebraic sets, then their product $X \times Y\subset \mathbb{A}^{m+n}$ is an algebraic set. It is an affine variety under the Zariski topology. The projection map $\pi_ {X}: X\times Y\to Y$ and $\pi_ {Y}: X\times Y\to Y$ are morphisms.</p> <p>We can generalize it to affine varieties. Let $X$ and $Y$ now be affine varieties. Then the claim is that $X\times Y$ is truly a product in the categorical sense. Recall that in category theory, product is define by a universal properties. Let $A ,B\in \mathcal{A}$ be objects in category $A$ and assume there exits an arrow $A\to B$, then we call the image of the arrow an <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">element of shape</code> $A$ in $B$. The universal property for product says that $X\times Y$ (now regarding $X,Y$ as objects in some category) is the unique object (up to isomorphism) in the category that there exists map $X\times Y\to X$ and $X\times Y \to Y$ which holds for elements of all possible shapes. For a more conventional definition, refer to textbooks on category theory. In our case, it can be shown that in the category of affine varieties, for any affine variety $Z$ and morphism $Z \to X$ and $Z\to Y$ there is a unique morphism \(f_ {X}: Z\to X\) and \(f_ {Y}: Z\to Y\) such that \(f_ {X} = f \;\circ\;\pi_ {X},\quad f_ {Y} = f\;\circ\;\pi_ {Y}.\)</p> <p>We can further generalize products to prevarieties.</p> <p><strong>Proposition.</strong> Let $X,Y$ be prevarieties, Then there is a product prevariety $X\times Y$ with morphism $\pi_ {X}: X\times Y\to X$ and $\pi_ {Y}: X\times Y\to Y$ satisfying the universal property of products. It is unique up to a isomorphism.</p> <p>The construction works in a more or less intuitive way hence we will omit it.</p> <hr/> <p>Finally let us return to the “bad gluing” of two varieties $\mathbb{A}^{1}$, resulting in a line with two origins. We want to exclude them from the construction, is there a way?</p> <p>In topology, the manifold is supposed to be Hausdorff. This excludes the line with two origins, since these two origins can not be separated by two open neighborhoods.</p> <p>Unfortunately we don’t have usual topology in prevarieties, what we have is Zariski topology, so the original definition of Hausdorff space is not applicable. However, there is a variant of Hausdorff criterion. The original definition for spaces being Hausdorff is equivalent to say that the diagonal \(\Delta_ {X} := \left\{ (x,x) \,\middle\vert\, {x \in X} \right\}\) is closed under the product topology. We can adopt the same definition but substitute Zariski topology for product topology.</p> <p><strong>Definition.</strong> A prevariety $X$ is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">separated</code> if the diagonal \(\Delta_ {X} = \left\{ (x,x) \,\middle\vert\, x \in X \right\}\) is closed in $X\times X$. A separated prevariety is called an <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">(algebraic) variety</code>. Varieties are also called curves, surfaces or hypersurfaces according to its dimension.</p> <p><strong>Proposition.</strong> $X$ is separated if for every topological space $Y$ and a pair of morphisms \(p,q: Y\to X\) the set \(\left\{ y \in Y \,\middle\vert\, p(y)=q(y) \right\} \subset Y\) is closed. It is each pair of morphism $p,q$ lifts to \((p,q): Y \to X \times X,\quad y \mapsto(p(y),q(y)) \in X\times X.\) thus \(\left\{ y \in Y \,\middle\vert\, p(y)=q(y) \right\} = (p,q)^{-1} (\Delta_ {X})\) where $(p,q)^{-1}$ should be regarded as a map inverse, which is continuous. Since $\Delta_ {X}$ is closed, the above set should also be closed.</p> <p>In the following are some examples.</p> <ul> <li>Any affine variety is a variety.</li> <li>Any open or closed sub prevariety of a variety is a variety.</li> <li>The line with two origins (doubled origin line) is not a variety, since it is not <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">separated</code>. This can be proved by the proposition we mentioned before. Or notice that the image of $\Delta_ {X}$ only contains two out of the four origins in $X \times X$, thus is not closed.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="Math"/><category term="Commutative Algebra"/><category term="Notes"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Algebraic Varieties]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Basic Algebraic Geometry Class 8</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Basic-Algebraic-Geometry-Class-8/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Basic Algebraic Geometry Class 8"/><published>2023-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Basic-Algebraic-Geometry-Class-8</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Basic-Algebraic-Geometry-Class-8/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="ring-extension">Ring extension</h3> <p>First let’s review <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">field extension</code> as a motivating example. Let $k$ be any field. A field extension $k\subset k’$ is said to be <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">algebraic</code> if each $a\in k’$ is algebraic over the original field $k$, i.e. $P(a)=0$ for some polynomial function $P$. We may assume that $P$ is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">monic</code>, meaning it is univariate and the leading coefficient is $1$. A natural consequence is that $k’$ is finite dimensional field extension, just take the field extension $\mathbb{R}\subset \mathbb{C}$ for example.</p> <p>What about ring extensions? The definition is rather trivial, a ring inclusion $R\subset R’$ is called a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ring extension</code>, and $R’$ an <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">extension ring</code> or $R$.</p> <p>Our goal here is to define an study an analogy of algebraicity for ring extensions.</p> <h3 id="integral-ring-extensions">Integral ring extensions</h3> <p>Let $R\subset R’$ be a ring extension. An element $a\in R’$ is said to be <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">integral</code> over $R$ if $P(a)=0$ where $P\in R[T]$ is a monic polynomial with coefficients in $R$.</p> <p>If each of $a\in R’$ is integral, we say $R’$ is integral over $R$.</p> <p>The following example helps to explain the terminology.</p> <p>Consider the ring extension $\mathbb{Z}\subset\mathbb{Q}$, where $\mathbb{Q}$ is the set of rational numbers. What are the integral elements in $\mathbb{Q}$? As the name suggests, the integral elements in $\mathbb{Q}$ should be integers, Right? It indeed is true! Assume where $s,t$ are <strong>coprime</strong> integers and $s / t \in\mathbb{Q}$ is the solution of some monic polynomial equation, \(\left( \frac{s}{t} \right)^{n}+c_ {n-1}\left( \frac{s}{t} \right)^{n-1}+\dots=0\) then \(s^{n}=t\times (\text{some integer})\implies t\mid s^{n}\) but $s,t$ are coprime, so we must have $t=1$ and $s / t$ is an integer.</p> <p>The key important thing is that the polynomial has to be <strong>monic</strong>.</p> <h3 id="finiteness-and-integrality">Finiteness and integrality</h3> <p><strong>Proposition.</strong> The ring $R’$ over $R$ is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">finite</code> if and only if $R’=R[x_{1},\dots,x_{n}]$ where $x_{1},\dots,x_{n}$ are integral over $R$.</p> <p>Take $\mathbb{Z}\subset\mathbb{Z}[i]$ where $i^{2}=-1$ for example, $\mathbb{C}=\mathbb{Z}[i]$ where $i$ is integral over $\mathbb{R}$ since $i^{2}+1=0$ is monic.</p> <p>Another way to say it is that $R’$ is finite over $R$ if $R’$ is a finitely generated $R-$module. Keep in mind the difference between finitely generated $R$-algebra and $R$-module. For example, $R[x]$ is a finitely generated $R$-algebra whit a single generator $x$, but it is <strong>not</strong> finitely generated as a $R$-module since the basis of the module would be $x,x^{2},x^{3},\dots$</p> <p>Lets look at one example of integral and non-integral ring extension. Consider $R=\mathbb{C}[T]$, and extend it by introducing another variable $S$, namely $R[S]$, and quotient some vanishing ideal $I[\text{sth}]$. Even after the quotient the resulting ring is still a ring extension. However, depending on the ideal, the ring extension may be integral or non-integral.</p> <ul> <li>Let $R’= R / (S^{2}-T^{2})$, then $R’$ is integral since $R’=R[S]$ and $S$ is integral over $R$.</li> <li>Let $R’=R / (ST-\lambda)$ with $\lambda \in\mathbb{C}$, then $R’$ is not integral since $T$ is in general not invertible.</li> </ul> <p>Some basic properties of ring extension.</p> <ul> <li>if $R\subset R’$ and $R’\subset R’’$ are both integral then so is $R\subset R’’$.</li> <li>if $R\subset R’$ and $R’\subset R’’$ are both finite then so is $R\subset R’’$.</li> </ul> <h3 id="integral-closure-and-normality">Integral closure and normality</h3> <p>Let $R\subset R’$ be a ring extension. The set $\overline{R}$ of all the integral elements over $R$ in $R’$ is a ring, called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">integral closure</code> of $R$ in $R’$.</p> <p>$\overline{R}$ is a ring because if $a,b\in R’$ are integral over $R$ then $R[a,b]$ is also integral over $R$, then $a\cdot b$ and $a+b$ are integral, hence they form a ring.</p> <p>We say that $R$ is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">integrally closed</code> in $R’$ if $R=\overline{R}$.</p> <p>If $R$ is an integral domain, then we say that $R$ is integrally closed or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">normal</code> if $R$ is integrally closed in its <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">field of fractions</code>.</p> <p>As a trivial example, an integral closure of $R$ is integrally closed in some bigger ring $R’$.</p> <p>Unique factorization domains (UFDs) are normal.</p> <h3 id="prime-ideals-in-ring-extension">Prime ideals in ring extension</h3> <p>Let $R\subset R’$ be a ring extension. The question we want to ask is, what are the relations between the prime ideals in $R$ and $R’$? Geometrically, prime ideals corresponds to irreducible varieties, so the question become, what are the properties between the irreducible varieties in $V(R)$ and $V(R’)$?</p> <p>More precisely, we know that</p> <ul> <li>If $J\subset R$ is an ideal, then $JR’$ is an ideal in $R’$,</li> <li>If $J\subset R’$ is an ideal in $R’$, then $J\cap R$ is an ideal in $R$. If $J$ is prime in $R’$ then so is $J\cap R$ in $R$.</li> </ul> <p>The question is, given any ideal in $R$, is there always a bigger ideal in $R’$ such that its intersection with $R$ is the original ideal? Is there only one or multiple such ideals in $R’$?</p> <hr/> <p>We state without proof the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">lying over</code> property.</p> <p>Let $R\subset R’$ be an <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">integral</code> ring extension. If $P\subset R$ is a prime ideal, then there exists a prime ideal $P’$ in $R’$ such that $P’\cap R=P$. We say that $P’$ <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">lies over</code> $P$.</p> <p>The uniqueness of lying over ideals, or at least a weak version of it, is given by the non-containment condition.</p> <p><strong>Proposition.</strong> If $P$ is a prime ideal in $R$ and $P’,Q’$ two prime ideals in $R’$ lying over $P$, then neither $P’$ is contained in $Q’$ nor $Q’$ is contained in $P’$.</p> <p>Consequently,</p> <ul> <li>A prime ideal $P’\subset R’$ is maximal if and only if $P’\cap R$ is maximal in $R$.</li> <li>If $R$ and $R’$ are integral domains, then either both or none are fields. It means that you can’t take a integral domain and find an integral extension of it which is also a field.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="Math"/><category term="Commutative Algebra"/><category term="Notes"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ring extension]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Basic Algebraic Geometry Class 9</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Basic-Algebraic-Geometry-Class-9/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Basic Algebraic Geometry Class 9"/><published>2023-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Basic-Algebraic-Geometry-Class-9</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Basic-Algebraic-Geometry-Class-9/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="dimension">Dimension</h3> <p>Our goal here is to extend the notion of dimension from vector spaces, to affine varieties that fits into our intuition. We will also study dimension globally and locally, and try to express dimension algebraically.</p> <p>One way to think about dimension in vector space is to study the inclusion relation. For example, given $\mathbb{R}^{3}$, the smallest “subspace” is a point, the next smallest subspace containing a point is a line, then a plane, then $\mathbb{R}^{3}$ itself. This is an approach we can adopt for varieties.</p> <p><strong>Definition.</strong> The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">dimension</code> $\text{dim }X$ of a Noetherian topological space $X$ is the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">supremum</code> of all $n$ having a chain \(X_{0}\subsetneq X_{1}\subsetneq\dots\subsetneq X_{n}\subsetneq X\) of non-empty <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">irreducible</code> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">closed</code> subspaces of $X$.</p> <p>Note that we are talking about Zariski topology here.</p> <p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">codimension</code> $\text{codim }_ {X}Y$ of a non-empty irreducible subspace $Y$ in $X$ is the supremum of all $n$ with a chain \(Y\subset X_{0}\subsetneq\dots\subsetneq X_{n} \subsetneq X\) of irreducible closed subsets of $X$.</p> <p>For example, a point is closed in Zariski topology. Let $X$ be a point, then the dimension of $X$ is zero since you can’t find another closed space containing it. The dimension of a line is one since \(\text{point} \subsetneq \text{line}\) and terminates at the line.</p> <p>As an interesting exercise, reader can think about the dimension of a plane pierced by a ling. In $\mathbb{A}^{3}$ the variety $V(X_{1},X_{2})$ is the $X_{3}$ axis, namely a straight line, and the variety $V(T_{3})$ is the $X_{1}\times X_{2}$ plane, think about the dimension of the union of these two varieties and the codimension of some points on it.</p> <p><strong>Definition.</strong> A noetherian topological space is said to have <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pure dimension n</code> if each irreducible component has dimension $n$.</p> <p>An affine variety is said to be a curve if it has pure dimension $1$, a plane if pure dimension is $2$, a hypersurface if it is of pure codimension $1$.</p> <p>Note that there exists infinite-dimensional noetherian topological spaces (but not varieties).</p> <hr/> <p>We have talked about dimension of noetherian topological spaces, the approach is rather geometric. Next we would like to study dimension algebraically. Recall that an irreducible variety is given by a prime ideal, or put it in other words, the coordinate ring of an irreducible variety is a prime ideal. This motivates the following definition.</p> <p><strong>Definition.</strong> The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Krull dimension</code>, $\text{dim }R$ of a ring $R$ is the supremum of all $n$ with a chain \(P_{0}\subsetneq P_{1}\subsetneq\dots \subsetneq P_ {n}\) of prime ideals in $R$.</p> <p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">codimension</code> of a prime ideal $P$ in $R$, sometimes called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">height</code> of $P$, denoted $\text{codim}_ {R}P$, is the supremum of all $n$ with a chain \(P_{0}\subsetneq P_{1}\subsetneq\dots \subsetneq P_ {n}\subset P\) of prime ideals contained in $P$.</p> <p>For example, fields all have dimension $0$ since the only prime ideal fields have is the trivial ideal $0$. Principal ideal domains (PIDs) have dimension $1$.</p> <hr/> <p>Now, having introduced the dimension from both geometric and algebraic side, it would be sad if they don’t agree with each other. Thankfully they do, thanks to the $1:1$ correspondence between irreducible varieties and prime ideals.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="Math"/><category term="Commutative Algebra"/><category term="Notes"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Dimension]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Basic Algebraic Geometry Class 6</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Basic-Algebraic-Geometry-6/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Basic Algebraic Geometry Class 6"/><published>2023-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Basic-Algebraic-Geometry-6</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Basic-Algebraic-Geometry-6/"><![CDATA[<p>The goal here is to obtain an <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">intrinsic</code> description of <strong>algebra and geometry</strong> of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">algebraic sets</code>, or varieties, or zero loci of polynomials.</p> <p>Given a variety $X\subset \mathbb{A}^{n}$ with $k$ being the base (closed) field, we can introduce certain geometric structure on $X$, namely the Zariski topology. Then $X$ is made into a Noetherian topological space. This is the geometric side of the story. On each open subset of $X$ we can define a ring (which is also an $k$-algebra), namely the ring of regular functions, which are rational functions of polynomial functions ${f(x)} / {g(x)}$ where $f(x),g(x)$ are elements of $\mathcal{O}(X)$. This is the algebraic side of the story.</p> <p>To summarize, our data is a pair \((X,\mathcal{O}_ {X})\) Note that it is $O_ {X}$ not $\mathcal{O}(X)$. $O_ {X}$ is a “gadget” that assigns a ring $O_ {X}(U)$ to each open subset $U\subset X$ in a coherent way.</p> <p>Here we have slightly an abuse of notation. $\mathcal{O}(\text{closed sets})$ are coordinate rings, $\mathcal{O}(\text{open sets})$ are the rings of regular functions. Different things depending on where the argument is closed or open. Well I didn’t invent the notation.</p> <p>What we will do next is to extract the important properties of $\mathcal{O}_X$ into a general definition, which we can work with to define affine varieties.</p> <p>Let’s look at some properties of $\mathcal{O}_ {X}$.</p> <h3 id="properties-of-regular-function-rings">Properties of Regular Function Rings</h3> <p>The first thing to notice is that $\mathcal{O} _ {X}$ is not itself a ring, but a “gadget” that, when fed by an open set $U$, spits out a ring $O_ {X}(U)$, or $\mathcal{O}(U)$ for short.</p> <p>Let $X\subset\mathbb{A}^{n}_ {k}$ be an algebraic set, a subset of n-dimensional affine space of field $k$. Let $U\subsetneq X$ be an <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">open</code> subset of $X$. We consider the assignment<br/> \(\begin{align} U &amp;\mapsto \mathcal{O} _ X(U)=: \mathcal{O}(U), \\ \mathcal{O}(U)&amp;=\left\{ \phi: U\to k \,\middle\vert \, \phi =\frac{f}{g},f\in \mathcal{O}(X),g\in \mathcal{O}(X) \text{ and } g\neq 0\text{ on }U\right\} \end{align}\) where $=:$ means the right hand side is defined by the left hand side. $\mathcal{O}(U)$ is also a $k$-algebra. In the following we list some properties of the ring of regular functions on open sets.</p> <ul> <li> <p>Any inclusion $U\subset V$ of open sets in $X$ gives a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">restriction</code> homomorphism \(\rho_{U,V}: \mathcal{O}(V) \to \mathcal{O}(U), \quad \phi\mapsto \phi \mid_{U}.\) The restriction of regular functions on $U$ to its subset $V$ is obvious a ring homomorphism.</p> </li> <li> <p>The ring of regular functions on empty set, $\mathcal{O}(\emptyset)$, is trivial.</p> </li> <li> <p>If you look at the restriction of regular functions on $U$ to $U$ itself, then you are not changing anything, thus for any $U$, \(\rho_{U,U} = \text{Id}_{\mathcal{O}(U)}\)</p> </li> <li> <p>Restriction respects composition. The restriction of $W$ to $V$ then to $U$ is the restriction of $W$ to $U$. If $U\subset V\subset W$, then $\rho_{U,V}\circ \rho_{V,W}=\rho_{U,W}$ .</p> </li> </ul> <p>The above properties are kind of “out there in the open”, the next one is less so.</p> <ul> <li>Functions that are defined locally on an open cover, and agree on intersection, have a unique lift.</li> </ul> <p>Let $U =U_{1}\cup U_{2}$ be the union of two open sets, $V:=U_{1}\cap U_{2}\neq \emptyset$. Let $\phi_{1}$ be a regular function on $U_{1}$ and $\phi_{2}$ on $U_{2}$. If $\phi_{1}$ and $\phi_{2}$ agree on the intersection, that is, the restriction of $\phi_{1}$ on $V$ is equal to the restriction of $\phi_{2}$ on $V$, then there exists a unique regular function defined on the whole of $U$, call it $\phi$, such that $\phi \mid_{U_{1}}=\phi_{1}$ and $\phi \mid_ {U_{2}}=\phi_{2}$.</p> <p>Now let’s generalize these properties to a definition.</p> <h3 id="presheaves-and-sheaves">Presheaves and sheaves</h3> <p>Let $X$ be an arbitrary topological space.</p> <p><strong>Definition.</strong> A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">presheaf</code> $\mathcal{F}$ of rings on $X$ consists of the following data:</p> <ul> <li>For each open set $U\subset X$, is assigned a ring $\mathcal{F}(U)$. Think of the ring of regular functions for example, but $\mathcal{F}(U)$ need be nothing like it, it could be any ring ;</li> <li>For each inclusion $U\subset V$ of open sets in $X$, there is a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ring homomorphism</code> \(\rho_{U,V}: \mathcal{F}(V)\to \mathcal{F}(U),\) subject to the following conditions:</li> <li>$\mathcal{F}(\emptyset)$ is the trivial ring,</li> <li>For any open subset $U$, \(\rho_{U,U}=\text{Id}_{\mathcal{F}(U)},\)</li> <li>If $U\subset V\subset W$, \(\rho_{U,V}\circ \rho_{V,W}=\rho_{U,W}.\) Elements of $\mathcal{F}(U)$ are called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sections</code> of $\mathcal{F}$ over $U$. Notice the similar usage of terminology from fiber bundle.</li> </ul> <p>The homomorphism $\rho_{U,V}$ is called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">restriction map</code> from $V$ to $U$, and denoted $\phi\mapsto \phi \mid_{U}$.</p> <p>The name <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sheaf</code> is rather pictorial. A sheaf in farming is a bundle of grain stalks tied up and laid on the ground, you could say that it is an assignment of bundle of stalks to areas of lands. Here in mathematics a presheaf is an assignment of ring structure to open subsets.</p> <p>We want a sheave to represent the nice properties we have for ring of regular functions, thus we need the above given conditions for restriction maps.</p> <p>Notice that in the definition of presheaf, everything is local. Given a open set $U$, a presheaf only tells you that you can go further into $U$ (restriction), it does not say anything globally. For example ,it does not say if you are given an open cover of some whole space $X$, how can you glue these open charts together to have something defined on the whole atlas. That is why it is called a <strong>pre</strong>sheaf.</p> <p><strong>Definition.</strong> A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">presheaf</code> $\mathcal{F}$ is upgraded to a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sheaf</code> is the following <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">gluing properties</code> holds for any open set $U\subset X$:</p> <p>If \(\{ U_{i} \mid ,i\in I \}\) is an open cover of $U$, and if $\phi_{i}$ are sections satisfying \(\phi_{i} \mid_{U_{i}\cap U_{j}} = \phi_{j} \mid_{U_{i}\cap U_{j}}\) <strong>for all</strong> $i,j\in I$, then there exists a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">unique</code> $\phi \in\mathcal{F}(U)$ such that \(\phi \mid_{U_{i}} = \phi_{i}, \text{ or equivalently } \phi_{i} = \rho_{U_{i},U}\phi.\)</p> <p>It is interesting to compare this compatibility condition with that of fiber bundles, where we use transition functions to glue different bundles.</p> <p>Think: what if two open subsets are disjoint, namely $U_{i}\cap U_{j}=\emptyset$? Given two sections separately, $\phi_{i}$ and $\phi_{j}$, what are the restrictions of them on the empty set? Should there be a bigger section $\phi$ defined on $U_{i} \cup U_{j}$ such that the restriction of $\phi$ on $U_{i}$ is $\phi_{i}$ (similarly for $U_{j}$)? I’ll leave this small problem to interested readers.( When in doubts, mathoverflow!) For less interested readers, when the overlap is empty, then the overlap condition is vacuous and automatically true.</p> <p>Some examples are in order. The most familiar example of a sheaf would be</p> <ul> <li> <p>The sheaf $\mathcal{O}_ {X}$ of rings (regular functions) on an algebraic space $X$, to refresh your memory, \(\mathcal{O}_ {X}(U) = \{ \text{regular functions on }U \}\) and the restriction is given by the usual restriction of functions.</p> </li> <li> <p>The sheaf of real-valued continuous function on a topological space $X$, denoted by $\mathcal{C}(X)$ sometimes. $\mathcal{C}(U)$ where $U$ is some open subset of $\mathbb{R}^{n}$ would be the ring of continuous functions.</p> </li> </ul> <p>The next example is more interesting.</p> <ul> <li>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">presheaf</code> of constant functions. Consider the (real-valued) real functions on a topological space $X$. Let $U=U_{1}\sqcup U_{2}$, namely the union of two disjoint (non-empty) open sets. choose two sections $\phi_{1}=0$ everywhere on $U_{1}$ and $\phi_{2}=1$ everywhere on $U_{2}$, then the overlap condition is satisfied trivially but the gluing condition is not, since you can not find a constant function on the whole of $U$ whose restrictions are blah and blah. This is an example of a presheaf which is not a sheaf. One way out of this problem is to loosen up the continuous condition a little, instead of globally constant functions we consider the locally constant functions, then we may make it into a sheaf, this process is called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sheafification</code>.</li> </ul> <p>Roughly speaking, whenever you are dealing with a ring of functions on open sets, you can expect them to be presheaves. But for them to be sheaves, you want them to satisfy <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">local</code> conditions. The constant functions, for example, from last example, are not local, since you can’t decide if a function is constant or not locally, and that’s a hint that it is not a sheave. On the other hand, when we defined regular functions, we didn’t say that a regular function must be given by the same quotient expression everywhere (globally), but rather on some (principal) open set (locally).</p> <h3 id="ringed-spaces">Ringed Spaces</h3> <p>Topological spaces with a sheave structure has its own name.</p> <p><strong>Definition.</strong> A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ringed space</code> is a topological space $X$ together with a sheaf $\mathcal{O}_ {X}$ of rings on $X$, called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">structure sheaf</code>.</p> <p>For example, let $U\subset X$ be an open subset of $X$, if $X$ is a ringed space then there exists a ring $\mathcal{O}_ {X}(U)$, also the overlapping condition, restriction condition and gluing condition are all satisfied.</p> <p>The ringed space $(X,\mathcal{O}_ {X})$ is referred to as $X$ if the structure sheaf is clear from context.</p> <p>For example, an algebraic set is a ringed space, the structure sheaf is by default taken to be the ring of regular functions.</p> <p>It is kink of obvious that if $X$ is a ringed space, then an open subset $U\subset X$ is also a ringed space, whose structure sheaf is that of $X$ restricted to $U$.</p> <p>In general, given a presheaf $\mathcal{F}$ on $X$ and an open subset $U\subset X$, The restriction of $\mathcal{F}$ to $U$ is given by \(\mathcal{F} \mid _{U}(V) = \mathcal{F}(V)\) for all open $V\subset U\subset X$. The restriction of a presheaf is a presheaf and the restriction of a sheaf is a sheaf.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="sheaves-of-functions">Sheaves of Functions</h3> <p>Our goal is to define affine varieties as ringed spaces <strong>isomorphic to the ringed spaces of algebraic sets</strong>. To have a reasonable definition of isomorphism, we will restrict the notion of sheaves.</p> <p>From now on, the sheaf $\mathcal{F}$ on a topological space $X$ is assumed to be a sheaf of $k$-valued functions. For all open subsets $U\subset X$, $\mathcal{F}(U)$ is supposed to be a sub ring of the ring of all $k$-valued functions $U\to k$, with pointwise addition and multiplication.</p> <h3 id="morphisms-of-ringed-spaces">Morphisms of Ringed Spaces</h3> <p>Let $(X,\mathcal{O} _ {X})$ and $(Y,\mathcal{O} _ {Y})$ be two ringed spaces, where $O_ {X}$ is the sheaf of regular functions on $X$, etc. Let $f: X\to Y$ be a <strong>continuous</strong> map. Let $U\subset Y$ be an open subset of $Y$, and $\phi: U\to k$ a function defined on $U$. Then we can use $f$ to pull back $\phi$, the pull-back $f^{\ast}\phi$ is the function \(\phi\circ f: f^{-1} (U)\to k.\)</p> <p>Recall that $\phi$ is an element of a ring, namely the ring of regular functions defined on $U$, $\mathcal{O}_{Y}(U)$. Thus the pull-back defines a ring homomorphism \(\boxed{f^{\ast }: \phi\mapsto \psi}, \quad \phi: U\to k,\quad\phi: f^{-1}(U)\to k.\)</p> <p>If we want to define the morphism between ringed spaces, the morphism map must respect both the topology of the spaces, and the structure ring on those spaces. To be specific,</p> <p><strong>Definition.</strong> A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">morphism of ringed spaces</code> is a continuous map \(f: X\to Y\) such that for each open $U\subset Y$, the pull-back of any $\phi \in\mathcal{O} _ {Y}(U)$ belongs to $\mathcal{O} _ {X}(f^{-1}U)$. This is possible since $f$ is continuous, meaning that $f^{-1}(U)$ is an open set on $X$, hence there exists a ring of functions $\mathcal{O}_ {X}(f^{-1}(U))$. This defines a ring homomorphism \(f^{\ast }: \mathcal{O}_{Y}(U) \to \mathcal{O}_ {X}(U'), \quad U':=f^{-1}(U).\)</p> <p>Note the inverse direction between $f$ and $f^{\ast}$, $f$ points from $X$ to $Y$ and $f^{\ast}$ points from $\mathcal{O}<em>{Y}$ to $\mathcal{O}</em> {X}$. In terms of category theory, the morphism is a contravariant functor.</p> <p>Now we have the definition of morphism, we can go on and define isomorphism. A morphism $f$ of ringed spaces is an <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">isomorphism</code> if it is bijective and there exists the inverse $f^{-1}$, which is another morphism of ringed spaces.</p> <h3 id="affine-varieties">Affine Varieties</h3> <p>Finally we can define what affine varieties are, in an intrinsic manner, without mentioning the embbedding space or anything like that.</p> <p><strong>Definition.</strong> An <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">affine variety</code> is a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ringed space</code> that is isomorphic to $(X,\mathcal{O}_ {X})$ of an algebraic space $X$, with the sheaf of functions $\mathcal{O} _ {X}$.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="Math"/><category term="Commutative Algebra"/><category term="Notes"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The goal here is to obtain an intrinsic description of algebra and geometry of algebraic sets, or varieties, or zero loci of polynomials.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Basic Algebraic Geometry Class 7</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Basic-Algebraic-Geometry-Class-7/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Basic Algebraic Geometry Class 7"/><published>2023-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Basic-Algebraic-Geometry-Class-7</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Basic-Algebraic-Geometry-Class-7/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="localization">Localization</h3> <p>Localization is a technique used in commutative algebra in both algebra and geometry. In geometry it is used when we want to look at points in varieties locally, hence the name.</p> <p>Let $R$ be a ring (commutative, unital). The general idea is that, given a certain subset $S\subset R$, we want to introduce the inverse of $S$, namely the inverse of all the elements $s\in S$, into $R$. In other words, we want the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">division</code> by $S$.</p> <p>As a motivative example, look at the ring of integers $\mathbb{Z}$. Let $S$ be the non-zero integers, $S = \mathbb{Z}-0$. Inverting all elements of $S$ one obtains the ring of rational numbers $\mathbb{Q}$, or the field of rational numbers since all the elements are invertible. Formally, a rational number can be considered as a pair of integers $(a,s)$ where $a\in\mathbb{Z}$ and $s\in S$, plus the equivalence relation \((a,s) \sim (a',s') \iff as'=a's,\) then the equivalent class $(a,s)$ is denoted $a / s$, and addition and multiplication is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">defined</code> by \((a,s)+(a',s') = (as'+a's,ss'),\quad (a,s)\cdot (a',s')=(aa',ss').\)</p> <p>Now we want to generalize this procedure to arbitrary rings. The first observation is that one can not introduce the inverse of just about any arbitrary subsets, but just <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">multiplicatively closed</code> sets, namely sets that is closed under multiplication. To be accurate, A subset $S\subset R$ is said to be multiplicatively closed if \(1\in S \text{ and } s,s'\in S\implies ss'\in S.\)</p> <p>In spirits of construction of rational numbers from integers, we define the equivalence class $(a,s),a\in R,s\in S$ under the equivalence relation \((a,s)\sim (a',s') \iff \exists u\in S \text{ such that } u(as'-a's)=0.\) The set of equivalence classes is denoted by $S^{-1}R$, with addition and multiplication defined as before.</p> <p>Readers can check that $R^{-1}S$ indeed form a ring, called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">localization</code> of $R$ at $S$.</p> <p>Note that the condition \(\exists u\in S \text{ such that } u(as'-a's)=0\) means that if $R$ is a integral domain, then $as’-a’s$ itself must be zero since there are no zero devisors. $u$ should not be $0$ or we will get a trivial localization.</p> <p>There is a natural isomorphic map from $R$ to $S^{-1}R$ defined by $\iota : a\mapsto a / 1$. Surprisingly the map is not always injective, it is only so when $S$ does not contain zero divisors. To see it, take a look at the kernel of $\iota$, \(\text{ker }(\iota) = \left\{ a\in R \,\middle\vert\, \frac{a}{1}=\frac{0}{1} \right\},\) the equivalence relations says that the equal sign holds if there exists non-zero $u\in S$ such that \(u(a\cdot 1-1\cdot 0)=ua=0,\) namely if $u$ is a zero divisor.</p> <p>By the way, $S$ contains zero divisors does <strong>not</strong> necessarily means that $S$ contains zero itself, think about it.</p> <p>Given a ring it is always important to first identify its <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">zero</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">unity</code>. The zero element of $S^{-1}R$ is the equivalence class $[0 / 1]$ and unity $[1 / 1]$. Here the bracket denotes the equivalence class.</p> <p>If $S$ has only one element $1$, in terminology if you localize $R$ with respect to $1$, then you are adding nothing new to the ring, thus $S^{-1}R=R$. If $S=0$, then the kernel of $\iota$ is the whole ring $R$ thus $\iota$ would map everything to $0$, namely $0^{-1}R$ is the trivial ring.</p> <p>In the following we list some important examples of localization.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Fields of fractions.</strong> If $R$ is an integral domain and $S=R-0$, then $S^{-1}R$ is the field of fractions of $R$.</li> <li><strong>Localization at an element.</strong> If we want to localize $R$ at an element $a$, it is not enough to just write $a^{-1}R$ since the thing we localized at must be multiplicatively closed. Thus we have to make $a$ into a multiplicative set, by defining \(S= \text{ all the powers of }a, S = \left\{ a^{n} \,\middle\vert\, n\in \mathbb{N} \right\}\) then we can localized $R$ at $S$, the resulting ring $S^{-1}R$ is denoted $R_{a}$, called the localization of $R$ at the element $a$.</li> <li> <p><strong>Localization at a prime ideal.</strong> If ${\frak p}\in R$ is a prime ideal, we can construct a multiplicative set $R-{\frak p}$, it is closed under multiplication since, by the definition of prime ideals, \(a \notin {\frak p} \text{ and } b\notin {\frak p} \implies a\cdot p\notin {\frak p}.\) We can go on and localize $R$ at $S$, the resulting ring is denoted $R_{\frak p}$, called the localization of $R$ at the prime ideal ${\frak p}$.</p> <p>Note the potential confusion between two similar but opposite concepts, the localization at an element and at a prime ideal. The localization of an element $R_{a}$ means $a$ is made inversible in $R_{a}$, however the localization of a prime ideal means that everything <strong>but</strong> the prime ideal ${\frak p}$ is made inversible in $R_{\frak p}$.</p> </li> </ul> <hr/> <p>When we localize rings, we would like to know what is the relation between the prime ideals in the original ring and the prime ideals in the localized ring.</p> <p>Let $S$ be a multiplicatively closed subset of $R$, and denote \(\sigma: R\to S^{-1}R\) the canonical map (I used $\iota$ before, sorry for the arbitrary use of notations).</p> <p>Since $\sigma$ is a ring homomorphism, we know that if $J$ is an ideal in $R^{-1}R$, then the pre-image of $J$ is also an ideal in $R$. It has nothing to do with special properties of the canonical map, it is general for all ring homomorphisms.</p> <p>Without prove, we introduce the following proposition.</p> <p><strong>Proposition.</strong> The association \(J\mapsto \sigma^{-1}(J)\) defines a bijection between the set of prime rings in $S^{-1}R$ and the set of prime rings in $R$ that do not intersect $S$.</p> <p>This bijections contains two sides of information. On the one hand, if $J$ is a prime ideal in $S^{-1}R$, then $\sigma^{-1}(J)$ is a prime ideal in $R$ that does not intersect $S$. On the other hand, for all prime ideals in $I\subset R$, if $I\cap S=\emptyset$, then $\sigma(I)$ is a prime ideal in the localized ring. $I$ must not intersect $S$ since if it does, then $I$ contains elements in $S$, whose image under $\sigma$ are units, and when units appear in an ideal the ideal is bounded to be the whole ring.</p> <p><strong>Corollary.</strong> Let ${\frak p}\subset R$ be a prime ideal in $R$, and $S=R-{\frak p}$. The association \(J \to \sigma^{-1}(J)\) is a bijection between the prime ideals in $R_{\frak p}$, or $S^{-1}R$, and the prime ideals contained in ${\frak p}$.</p> <p>Note that an ideal contained in ${\frak p}$ just means the ideal does not intersect $R-{\frak p}=S$.</p> <h3 id="local-rings">Local Rings</h3> <p>A ring is called a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">local ring</code> if it has exactly one maximal ideal.</p> <p>Local rings has a close relation between the localization of a ring at the prime ideals. Let ${\frak p}\subset R$ be a prime ideal, the localization of $R$ at ${\frak p}$, or $R_{\frak p}$ is a local ring, with maximal ideal \(\frac{\frak p}{R-{\frak p}}:=\left\{ \frac{p}{r} \,\middle\vert\, p\in {\frak p},\,r\in R-{\frak p} \right\} .\)</p> <p>To have a feeling about this, consider a maximal ideal $M$ in $R_{\frak p}$. Since maximal ideals are automatically prime ideals, we knwo that $\sigma^{-1}(M)$ is a prime ideal in $R$ that is contained in ${\frak p}$, furthermore, since $\sigma$ and its inverse respects inclusion, namely respects the order between sets, $M$ being the maximal ideal means that $\sigma^{-1}(M)$ must be the biggest ring contained in ${\frak p}$, namely ${\frak p}$ itself, ${\frak p}=\sigma^{-1}(M)$. This means that $M=\sigma({\frak p})$, which is nothing but ${\frak p} / (R-{\frak p})$.</p> <p>Returning to the case of an affine variety $X,\mathcal{O}(X)$ and a point $a\in X$. We will use this to shed light on the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">stalk</code> denoted $\mathcal{O}_{X,a}$.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="local-study">Local Study</h3> <p>Sometimes in an affine variety we want to study the regular functions that are defined “at a point $a$”, namely locally at point $a$, or in an arbitrarily small open neighborhood of $a$. We want to study how regular functions are seen by a point $a$. For a near-sighted point $a$, it can only see what happens in its neighborhood, if there is another point $b$ distant from $a$, then $a$ doesn’t really care what $b$ has to say about a regular function. As far as $a$ is concerned, two functions are the same if they agree with each other at some neighborhood of $a$, no matter how small the neighborhood is. This motivates the following definition.</p> <p><strong>Stalks and germs.</strong> Let $\mathcal{F}$ be a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">presheaf</code>on a topological space $X$. Let $a\in X$ be a point in $X$. The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">stalk</code> of $\mathcal{F}$ at $a$ is defined as \(\mathcal{F}_{a} := \left\{ (U,\phi) \,\middle\vert\, U\subset X \text{ containing } a,\,\phi \in \mathcal{F}(U) \right\} / \sim\) with the equivalence relation \((U,\phi)\sim (U',\phi') \text{ if } \phi\mid_{V} =\phi'\mid _{V}\) for some \(V\subset U\cap U' \text{ containing } a.\)</p> <p>Elements of $\mathcal{F}_{a}$ are called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">germs</code> of $\mathcal{F}$ at $a$. The terminology is because in complex plane holomorphic functions can be “grown” out of a locally defined function, I guess.</p> <p>Morally, germs are functions defined locally at $a$, namely at an arbitrarily small neighborhood of $a$: their properties depend on no other points.</p> <p>For example, consider the stalk of $\mathcal{F}$ on $\mathbb{A}^{1}$, namely the real line, at the origin $0$. Regular functions are the ratio of two polynomial functions $f(x) / g(x)$, for it to be well defined at $0$ we just need \(g(0) \neq 0 .\) It does not matter if $g(x)$ vanishes at some other points.</p> <p>To better understand these local objects, we need the notion of localization. Returning to the case of an affine variety $(X,\mathcal{O}_ {X})$, given a point $a\in X$, the machinery of localization sheds light on the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">stalk</code> of $\mathcal{O}_ {X}$ at $a$, denoted $\mathcal{O}_ {X,a}$.</p> <p>But before that, let’s look at an easier version of localization, namely not the localization of prime ideals, but at an element of the ring.</p> <h3 id="first-geometric-application">First Geometric Application</h3> <p>Now we have two concepts, one geometrical, one algebraic.</p> <ul> <li>The open set given by a polynomial function, and the regular functions that could be defined on it.</li> <li>The localization of a ring at some multiplicative closed set.</li> </ul> <p>It is far from obvious, but there indeed exists a deep relation between them, which we will talk about.</p> <p>Let $X$ be an algebraic set, and $f\in\mathcal{O}(X)$ some polynomial functions (quotient $I(X)$, of course) defined on $X$. Recall that $f$ also defines an open set denoted \(U_ {f} = \left\{ x\in X \,\middle\vert\, f(x)\neq 0 \right\} .\)</p> <p><strong>Proposition.</strong> The ring of regular functions on $U_ {f}$ is the ring localization of $\mathcal{O}(X)$ at $f$, i.e. \(\mathcal{O}_ {X}(U_ {f}) = \text{ localization of } \mathcal{O} (X) \text{ at } f .\)</p> <p>Recall that the sheaf on $U_ {f}$ is \(\mathcal{O}_ {X}(U_ {f}) = \left\{ \frac{g(x)}{f^{n}(x)} \,\middle\vert\, g(x)\in \mathcal{O}(X) \right\} \tag{1}\)</p> <p>and the localization of $\mathcal{O}(X)$ at $f$ is \(\mathcal{O}(X)_ {f}:= \left\{ (g,f^{n}) \,\middle\vert\, g\in \mathcal{O}(X) \right\} \text{ with equivalence relation},\) sometimes denoted \(\mathcal{O}(X)_ {f}:= \left\{ \frac{g}{f^{n}} \,\middle\vert\, g\in \mathcal{O}(X) \right\} \text{ with equivalence relation}, \tag{2}\)</p> <p>comparing Eq. (1) with Eq.(2) we find they formally look the same, which is actually kind of misleading since the quotient has different meanings in different context. However, thanks to the equivalence equation defined in ring localization, one can show that there indeed exists a bijection between $\mathcal{O}_ {X}(U_ {f})$ and the localization of $\mathcal{O}(X)$ at $f$.</p> <h3 id="stalks-are-localizations">Stalks are Localizations</h3> <p>Let $X$ be an affine variety with structure sheaf $\mathcal{O}_ {X}$, and $a\in X$ a point in $X$. Recall that $I(a)$ is a maximal ideal in $\mathcal{O}(X)$, thus a prime ideal.</p> <p><strong>Proposition.</strong> The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">stalk</code> $\mathcal{O}_ {X}(a)$ is the isomorphic to the localization $\mathcal{O}(X)_ {I(a)}$ of the coordinate ring $\mathcal{O}(X)$ at the prime ideal $I(a)$.</p> <p>We will omit the proof here.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="local-and-global-properties-of-morphisms">Local and Global Properties of Morphisms</h3> <p>Recall that, roughly speaking, a morphism for ringed space is a continuous map where the pull-back of the structure sheaf is well-defined.</p> <p>Let $(X,\mathcal{O}_ {X})$ and $(Y,\mathcal{O}_ {Y})$ be two ringed spaces. We have the following properties.</p> <p><strong>Restriction.</strong> If \(f: X\to Y\) is a morphism, let $U\subset X$ and $V \subset Y$ be two open subsets and $f(U)\subset V$, then the restriction of $f$ on $U$ is morphism of ringed spaces.</p> <p><strong>Gluing.</strong> If $f: X\to Y$ is a map between two topological spaces, $f$ need not be continuous. If there exists an open cover of $X$ denoted $U_ {i}$ and $f\mid_ {U_ {i}}: U_ {i}\to Y$ are all morphisms, then we can glue them all together and $f$ is itself a morphism.</p> <p><strong>Categorical properties.</strong> A composition of morphism is a morphism. An identity is a morphism. Thus ringed space form a category, where the arrows are morphisms. We will focus on the <em>full subcategory of affine varieties</em>.</p> <hr/> <p>Roughly speaking, affine varieties are varieties embedded in affine space with structure sheaves. Let $X=(X,\mathcal{O}_ {X})$ and $Y=(Y,\mathcal{O}_ {Y})$ be two affine varieties, and $Y\subset\mathbb{A}^{n}$. Let $U\in X$ be an open set.</p> <p>Since $Y$ is embedded in $n$-dimensional affine space, $Y$ has $n$ coordinates in $\mathbb{A}^{n}$, for example a circle in $\mathbb{R}^{2}$ has two coordinates $(x,y)$. If there exists a morphism from $X$ to $Y$, then $f$ can pull-back there coordinate functions, for coordinates are nothing but regular functions $Y\to k$. This motivates the following proposition.</p> <p>Given a map \(f: U\to Y,\) it is a morphism if and only if there exists $n$ regular functions \(f_ {i} \in \mathcal{O}_ {X}(U)\) such that \(f=(f_{1},\dots,f_ {n}) : x\mapsto(f_{1}(x),\dots,f_ {n}(x))\) where $(f_{1}(x),\dots,f_ {n}(x))$ denotes a point in $Y$ with coordinates given by these $f$s.</p> <p>The prove can be found elsewhere.</p> <p>As a corollary, a morphism to $\mathbb{A}^{1}$ is just a regular function.</p> <h3 id="principal-open-subsets-are-affine-varieties">Principal Open Subsets are Affine Varieties</h3> <p>The title is rather confusing, since by definition varieties are closed sets, and principal open subsets $U_ {f}$ are, as the name suggests, open. How can they be the same thing? The answer is that, to make a principal open set into a closed affine variety, we need to increase the dimension of the embedding affine space by $1$.</p> <p>Let $X=(X,\mathcal{O}_ {X}$ be an affine space and $f\in\mathcal{O}(X)$ some function of $X$. The principal open subset \(U_ {f} = X - V(f)\) is an affine variety with coordinate algebra $\mathcal{O}(X)_ {f}$.</p> <p>To see this, let’s introduce a new dimension of affine space and let the coordinate be $t$. Define \(Y = \left\{ (x,t)\in X\times \mathbb{A}^{1} \,\middle\vert\, tf(x)=1 \right\}\) which is closed in the higher-dimensional affine space since it is the vanishing set of $t f(x)-1$. This is a well-defined map $U_ {f}\to X\times\mathbb{A}^{1}$ since $f(x)\neq 0$ on $U_ {f}$ by construction.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="Math"/><category term="Commutative Algebra"/><category term="Notes"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Localization]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Basic Algebraic Geometry Class 5</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Basic-Algebraic-Geometry-5/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Basic Algebraic Geometry Class 5"/><published>2023-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Basic-Algebraic-Geometry-5</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Basic-Algebraic-Geometry-5/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="zariski-topology">Zariski Topology</h3> <p>Rings are purely algebraic structures, it was to my surprise that, in a very direct manner, we can endow it with topological structures, called Zariski topology. This has a feeling of unity of algebra and geometry, with topology represents the geometry side. It makes people wonder why is it possible to define a topology on rings so naturally… The answer I do not know, let me know if you have any ideas.</p> <p>First, an overview of the ideal of topological space. Given a set $X$, we want to introduce a geometric structure on $X$ by defining what the it means for a subset to be <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">closed</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">open</code>. Namely we classify all the subsets of $X$ into two categories, open and closed. They don’t have to me mutual exclusive, a subset can be both open and closed, contrary to people’s common sense, such sets are sometimes called clopen but I seldom see living human being ever utter that word. No need to make the terminology more complicated than it already is.</p> <p>A topology on $X$ is a collection $\mathcal{T}$ of the subsets of $X$ called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">closed</code> subsets, such that the following holds:</p> <ol> <li>The empty set $\emptyset$ and whole set $X$ are closed,</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">finite</code> unions of closed sets are closed,</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">arbitrary</code> (meaning finite and infinite) intersections of closed sets are closed.</li> </ol> <p>The reason why we require <strong>finite</strong> unions of closed sets to be closed, rather than arbitrary unions, is that infinite unions of closed sets may be open. Take $\mathbb{R}$ for example, Let the topology on $\mathbb{R}$ be the usual topology, for example $(1,2)$ is a open set and $[1,2]$ is closed. However, the infinite union of closed sets \(\bigcap_{n\to \infty}\left[ 1+\frac{1}{n},2-\frac{1}{n} \right],\quad n\in \mathbb{N}\) is nothing but the open set $(1,2)$.</p> <p>The set $X$ with topology $\mathcal{T}$ is called a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">topological space</code>. It is a quite weak (or should I say abstract) sense of “space”, since there is not necessarily the concept of distance, or metric. If the topology is clear from the contest you just say that $X$ is a topological space, without mentioning $\mathcal{T}$ explicitly.</p> <p>A set $U$ is called an open set if its complement, denoted by $X-U$ (or $X \backslash U$ ) is closed.</p> <p>This is how you define topology in terms of closed sets. More often the topology is defined by specifying which sets are open. Then the condition also changes from “finite union, arbitrary intersection” for closed sets to “finite intersection, arbitrary union” for open sets.</p> <p>Once we have defined which sets are open, we can define which maps are <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">continuous.</code> A continuous map is a map between two topological spaces such that the pre-image of any closed sets is closed, equivalently (convince yourself of it) the pre-image of any open sets is open.</p> <p>Then we can further define <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">homeomorphism</code> (note the spelling is different from homomorphism in, for example, group theory). A homeomorphism is a continuous map with continuous inverse. By the way, there is a nice article online discussing the difference and connection between homeomorphism and homomorphism, sadly I am too lazy to put the link here, interested readers can google it.</p> <p>Whenever you need examples for these definitions, just think of $\mathbb{R}$ with usual topology.</p> <hr/> <p>Now let’s come back to algebraic sets and try to endow it with a topological structure. There are two ways to define the topology, one geometric and one algebraic. We will start with the geometric one.</p> <p><strong>Proposition.</strong> Let $X\subset \mathbb{A}^{n}$ ($\mathbb{A}$ for affine) be an <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">algebraic set</code> and $\mathcal{T}$ to be the collection of all <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">algebraic subsets</code> of $X$, then $\mathcal{T}$ is a topology of $X$ and $\mathcal{T}$ is the set of closed sets.</p> <p>In other words, a subset $U\subseteq X$ is closed if $U$ itself is algebraic, that is if $U$ is the variety of some ideals of $I(X)$, where $I(X)$ is the coordinate ring of $X$, namely the ring of non-zero polynomial functions on $X$.</p> <p>The empty set $\emptyset$ is algebraic since it is the variety of $I(X)$ itself, the entire set $X$ is also algebraic since it is the variety of the zero element of $I(X)$. The union of algebraic sets are algebraic since \(\bigcup_{i}V(I_{i}) = V\left( \prod_{i} I_{i} \right)\) and the intersection of algebraic sets are algebraic since \(\bigcap_{i} V(I_{i}) = V\left( \sum_{i}I_{i} \right).\)</p> <p>I’ll leave the distinction between “arbitrary” and “finite” to readers.</p> <p>This topology is called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Zariski topology</code>.</p> <p>From now on, when we talk about topology of an algebraic set, we would always assume Zariski topology, unless stated otherwise.</p> <p>Note that Zariski Topology is very different from the usual topology of $\mathbb{R}^{n}$ or $\mathbb{C}^{n}$, where open sets are open balls. For example, consider the complex plane $\mathbb{C}$ with usual metric topology where open sets are open balls \(\{ z\in \mathbb{C} \mid \left\lVert z \right\rVert &lt;1 \}\)</p> <p>However, this open ball is <strong>not Zariski open</strong> for if it were, its complement must be closed, namely its complement must be the variety of some ideal of $\mathbb{C}[z]$, which is not true. Hence the open ball is not Zariski open. In this sense, the usual topology on $\mathbb{C}$ is <strong>finer</strong> than Zariski topology, meaning roughly with more open sets.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="connectedness-and-irreducibility">Connectedness and Irreducibility</h3> <p>The definition of connectedness is quite intuitive: if a set can be written as the disjoint union of two proper subsets, then it is said to be disconnected, otherwise it is said to be connected. To be more specific,</p> <p><strong>Definition.</strong> Let $X$ be a topological space. If $X=X_{1} \sqcup X_{2}$ , where $\sqcup$ is the disjoint union and both $X_{1}$ and $X_{2}$ are closed (=algebraic) proper subsets of $X$, then $X$ is said to be <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">disconnected</code>, otherwise $X$ is said to be <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">connected</code>.</p> <p>For example, if you put two entirely irrelevant varieties together, let there be no intersection or superposition, and consider then as one big variety, then it is clearly less interesting than to study the individual varieties separately. Thus connected varieties are more interesting to us, since otherwise we can separate the variety into connected parts and study them separately.</p> <p>Another related yet different concept is reducibility.</p> <p><strong>Definition.</strong> Let $X$ be a topological space and $X_{1},X_{2}$ be two <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">closed</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">proper</code> subsets, not necessarily disjoint. If $X=X_{1}\cup X_{2}$ then $X$ is said to be <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">reducible</code>. Otherwise it is said to be <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">irreducible</code>.</p> <p>Think about the difference between connectedness and irreducibility.</p> <p>Obviously, irreducibility implies connected but the converse is not true. As an example, consider Zariski topology and $V(xy)$. It is connected but reducible.</p> <p>Zariski topology is a weird topology, with some uncommon properties. To start with, Zariski topology is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">coarse</code>, meaning it has very few open or closed sets. Consider Zariski topology on the real affine line $\mathbb{A}^{1}$, the closed sets are the zero loci of polynomials in one variable. But every polynomial has but finite zeros, thus the closed sets comprises of finite point, it is a finite set. Then the open sets are the whole affine line with finite points removed. Similarly for a complex line $\mathbb{C}$.</p> <p>The problem is that, the definition of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">neighborhood</code> of a point depends on the open sets. So, when taking the neighborhood of a point on $\mathbb{C}$, keep in mind that the open sets are the entire complex plane with finite points removed. Thus given two points on $\mathbb{C}$, you can’t find two disjoint neighborhoods of these two points. Then, by definition, $\mathbb{C}$ with Zariski topology is not s Hausdorff space. Recall that in a Hausdorff space, two points, no matter how close they are to each other, can be separated by two <strong>disjoint</strong> open sets.</p> <p>Another consequence of Zariski topology is that, the affine line $\mathbb{A}$ (or $\mathbb{C}$ in that matter) is not reducible, since a line is not the union of finite points.</p> <p>Yet another consequence of Zariski topology is that, in any irreducible space $X$, every proper open subset of $X$ is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">dense</code>. Recall that a proper subset $Y\subset X$ is dense in $X$ means the close of $Y$ is $X$.</p> <hr/> <p>We have told the geometric side of the story. On the algebraic side, we talk about the ideals. Let’s start with the algebraic view on connectedness.</p> <p><strong>Proposition.</strong> If $X$ is a disconnected algebraic set with $X=X_{1}\sqcup X_{2}$, where $X_{1,2}$ are <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">closed proper</code> subsets, then the coordinate rings on them obey \(\mathcal{O}(X) = \mathcal{O}(X_{1}) \times \mathcal{O}(X_{2}).\)</p> <p>Intuitively speaking, if $X$ is make of two separated parts $X_{1}$ and $X_{2}$, then the non-vanishing polynomial functions on $X$ is made up by the product of non-vanishing polynomial functions on $X_{1}$ and $X_{2}$.</p> <p>The proof uses the Chinese Remainder theorem, which claims that if two ideals $J_{1},J_{2}$ satisfies $J_{1}+J_{2}=R$ and $J_{1}\cap J_{2}=(0)$, then \(R\cong R / J_{1} \times R / J_{2}.\) In our case, let \(R=\mathcal{O}(X)\) be the coordinate ring of $X$, and \(J_{1}= I(X_{1}),\quad J_{2}=I(X_{2}).\)</p> <p>Then we have \(I(X_{1})\cap I(X_{2}) = I(X_{1}\cup X_{2}) = I(X),\) where the last equal sign is by assumption. An easy way to memorize the first equality is to keep mind that the smaller the ideal, the larger the corresponding variety.</p> <p>However, we know that $I(X)$ is zero since that’s the only polynomial function that vanishes everywhere on $X$. Thus we have shown that \(I(X_{1})\cap I(X_{2})=(0).\)</p> <p>On the other hand, we have \(I(X_{1}\cap X_{2})=\sqrt{ I(X_{1})+I(X_{2}) }= I(\emptyset)\) since $X_{1}\cap X_{2}$ is empty. But $I(\emptyset)$ is nothing but the coordinate ring of $X$! namely \(\sqrt{ I(X_{1})+I(X_{2}) }=\mathcal{O}(X) = R.\) Any ideal whose radical is the entire ring $R$ is itself $R$, thus \(I(X_{1})+I(X_{2})=\mathcal{O}(X).\) Then we can apply the Chinese remainder theorem to prove the proposition.</p> <p>Next let’s turn to the algebraic view of irreducible varieties.</p> <p><strong>Proposition.</strong> A non-empty algebraic set $X$ is irreducible iff $\mathcal{O}(X)$ is an <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">integral domain</code>.</p> <p>First let’s prove the “only if”, then “if”.</p> <p>If $\mathcal{O}(X)$ is not an integral domain, then there exists two zero-divisors $f_{1},f_{2}\in \mathcal{O}(X)$ such that non of them are zero but they multiply to zero, $f_{1}\times f_{2}=0$. The corresponding varieties $X_{1}:=V(f_{1})$ and $X_{2}:=V(f_{2})$ are proper subsets of $X$, and \(V(f_{1}\times f_{2}) = V(f_{1})\cup V(f_{2}) =X_{1}\cup X_{2},\) on the other hand, \(V(f_{1}\times f_{2}) = V(0) = X,\) thus \(X = X_{1}\cup X_{2}.\)</p> <p>Now we prove that $\mathcal{O}(X)$ being an integral domain implies irreducibility. If $X$ is reducible, it can be written as $X_{1}\cup X_{2}$, where \(X_{I}, \quad I = \left\{ 1,2 \right\}\) are the proper, closed subsets of $X$. Then we can choose two non-zero elements $f_{1}\in I(X_{1})$ and $f_{2}\in I(X_{2})$, it is possible because $X_{I}$ are not equal to $X$. Apparently $f_{1}\times f_{2}$ is zero on $X_{1}\cup X_{2}$, which is $X$. But only $(0)$ can be zero on $X$, thus \(f_{1}\times f_{2}=0\) and $f_{1},f_{2}$ are zero divisors, implying that $\mathcal{O}(X)$ is not an integral domain.</p> <p>By definition, the coordinate ring $\mathcal{O}(X)$ is $R / I(X)$ where $R$ is the polynomial ring. Recall that $R / I$ is an integral domain if $I$ is prime (similarly if $I$ is maximal then $R / I$ is a field), $\mathcal{O}(X)$ being an integral domain implies that $I(X)$ is a prime ideal, and note that prime ideals are automatically radical. Thus under the bijection between algebraic sets and radical ideals, irreducible algebraic sets (non-zero, of course) correspond to prime ideals in $k[X_{M}]$, where $M$ is an index set.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="noetherian-topological-space">Noetherian Topological Space</h3> <p>Recall that a ring is called Noetherian if the ideals satisfy the ascending chain condition (ACC). We can interpret it geometrically in the context of Zariski topology.</p> <p><strong>Definition.</strong> A topological space is called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Noetherian</code> if every descending chain of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">closed</code> proper subsets terminates. Namely, the descending chain \(V(J_{1})\supsetneq V(J_{2})\supsetneq\dots\) always terminates.</p> <p>This implies that, in terms of the ideals $J$s, the ascending chain \(J_{1}\subsetneq J_{2} \dots\) terminates, hence the name Noetherian.</p> <p>Apparently, any subsets of a Noetherian topological space is also Noetherian. We also mention that algebraic sets (with Zariski topology) is Noetherian, since there exists a smallest closed algebraic set, namely the set of points.</p> <p>The good thing about Noetherian topological spaces is that, they can be reduced to irreducible subsets. Let $X$ be a Noetherian topological space, then there exists non-empty irreducible subsets $X_{1},\dots,X_{n}$ such that \(X = X_{1}\cup \dots \cup X_{n},\) this decomposition is unique up to permutation.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="zariski-open-sets">Zariski Open Sets</h3> <p>We want to understand the open sets of a algebraic variety in Zariski topology in detail. First, we define a fundamental concept.</p> <p><strong>Definition.</strong> Given $f\in \mathcal{O}(X)$, the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">principla</code> or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">distinguished open subset</code> $U_{f}$ if given by \(U_{f} := \{ x\in X \mid f(x)\neq 0 \},\text{ or equivalently } U_{f}=X-V(f).\) Since $V(f)$ is closed by definition, $U_{f}$ is obvious open.</p> <p>The reason why principal open sets are so useful is that if $U\subset X$ is open, then $U$ is finite union of principal open sets, \(U = \bigcup_{i}U_{i}\) where $U_{i}$ are principal.</p> <p>To prove it, notice that if $U$ is open then we have \(U = X - V(J)\) for some $J\in\mathcal{O}(X)$. Suppose $J$ is finitely generated by $f_{M}\in\mathcal{O}(X),M=1,2,\dots,m$, then \(U = X - V(f_{1},\dots,f_{m})= X- \bigcap_{m}V(f_{m}) = \bigcup_{m}X-V(f_{m})=\bigcup_{m}U_{f_{m}}.\)</p> <p>Thus, principal open subsets form a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">base</code> for the Zariski topology on $X$.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="regular-functions-on-open-sets">Regular Functions on Open Sets</h3> <p>The closed sets and opens sets are very different in Zariski topology, much more so than in usual topology. To see that, consider the definition of coordinate ring of a algebraic subset $Z\subset X$, \(\mathcal{O}(Z) = \mathcal{O}(X) / I_{X}(Z)\) where $I_{X}(Z)$ is the vanishing ideal in $\mathcal{O}(X)$ on $Z$. Such a definition would <strong>not</strong> work for open sets: If $X$ is irreducible and $U\subset X$ is open, then no polynomial function $f\in\mathcal{O}(X)$ vanishes on $U$, since $U$ would be the entire affine space minus finite points. So $I_{X}(U)=(0)$ and $\mathcal{O}(U)=\mathcal{O}(X)$, which creates all kinds of problems.</p> <p>The solution is not to see open subsets as obstructions but opportunities. We should allow quotients whenever the denominator is non-zero. And we should aim locally. This leads us to the following definition.</p> <p><strong>Definition.</strong> Let $X$ be an algebraic set and $U\subset X$ an open subset. A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">regular function</code> $\phi$ on $U$ is a map \(\phi: U\to k\) where $k$ is the base field (real, complex, whatever), such that for each point $a\in U$, there exists a subset $U_{a}\subset U$ and $f,g\in\mathcal{O}(X)$ satisfying \(\forall\, x\in U_{a}: f(x)\neq 0 \text{ and } \phi(x) = \frac{g(x)}{f(x)}.\) It is nothing but quotient of polynomial functions on some “neighborhood” of $a$.</p> <p>Note that the specific $f(x)$ and $g(x)$ would depend on the choice of $a$. This definition is local in nature.</p> <p>The set of all regular functions on $U$ is denoted $\mathcal{O}(U)$. It is a $k$-algebra under pointwise operations.</p> <p>On principal open sets, the denominator can be fixed globally. Given any $f\in\mathcal{O}(X)$, the corresponding principal open set is $U_{f}=X-V(f)$, $f$ is non-zero on $U_{f}$ by construction, thus we can define \(\mathcal{O}(U_{f}) = \left\{ \frac{g(x)}{f^{n}(x)} \mid g(x)\in \mathcal{O}(X) \text{ and } n\in \mathbb{N} \right\}.\)</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="Math"/><category term="Commutative Algebra"/><category term="Notes"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Zariski Topology]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Minkowski Space</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Minkowski-Space/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Minkowski Space"/><published>2023-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Minkowski%20Space</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Minkowski-Space/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="curvature-and-special-relativity">Curvature and Special Relativity</h3> <p>Given a curve $C:= \mathbf{x}=\mathbf{x}(t)$ in $\mathbb{R}^{3}$, its tangent vector is a column vector, denoted by $\dot{\mathbf{x}}(t)=(\dot{x},\dot{y},\dot{z})^{T}$. $t$ can be considered as time in physics problems and $\dot{\mathbf{x}}(t)$ would be the velocity. Introduce the arc length $s$ by means of \(\left( \frac{ds}{dt} \right)^{2} = \left\lvert \dot{\mathbf{x}} \right\rvert^{2} = v^{2}, \quad s(t) = \int_{0}^{t} du \, \left\lvert \dot{\mathbf{x}}(t) \right\rvert.\)</p> <p>We then have the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">unit tangent vector</code> $T:= d\mathbf{x} / ds=\dot{\mathbf{x}}dt / ds = \mathbf{v} / v$, that is $\mathbf{v}= v\mathbf{T}$. Then the acceleration is given by \(\mathbf{a} = {\dot{v}}\mathbf{T} + v\mathbf{\dot{T}} = \dot{v}\mathbf{T} + v^{2} \frac{d\mathbf{T}}{ds}.\) Since $\mathbf{T}$ has constant length, ${d \mathbf{T}} / {ds}$ must be orthogonal to $\mathbf{T}$. The direction of ${d \mathbf{T}} / {ds}$ defines a unique unit vector normal to the curve called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">principal normal</code> $\mathbf{n}$, \(\frac{d\mathbf{T}}{ds} = \kappa(s) \mathbf{n}(s)\) where $\kappa(s)$ is the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">curvature</code> of curve $C$ at $s$. Then the acceleration is \(\mathbf{a} = \dot{v}\mathbf{T} + v^{2}\kappa(s)\mathbf{n}.\) The plane spanned by $\mathbf{T}$ and $\mathbf{n}$ is called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">osculating plane</code>. There is an easy way to compute $\kappa$ in terms of the original parameter $t$ rather than $s$, note that \(\mathbf{v}\times \mathbf{a} = v^{3}\kappa \mathbf{T}\times \mathbf{n},\) so \(\kappa = \frac{\left\lvert \mathbf{v}\times \mathbf{a} \right\rvert }{v^{3}}.\)</p> <p>We define the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">curvature vector</code> by \(\boxed{ \kappa=\frac{d\mathbf{T}}{ds}=\kappa \mathbf{n}, }\) note that it is $d\mathbf{T} / ds$ rather than $d\mathbf{T} / dt$.</p> <p>The curvature $\kappa$ has an intuitive geometric interpretation. Consider three nearby points $\mathbf{x}(s-\epsilon),\mathbf{x}(s),\mathbf{x}(s+\epsilon)$ on a curve $C$. There three points are generically not colinear, and determine a circle. Intuitively speaking, the larger the curvature, the smaller the determined circle. Under mild conditions, it is shown that at $\epsilon\to {0}$ limit, the determined circle lies on the osculating plane and the radius of the circle $\rho(x)=1 / \kappa(s)$ is called the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">radius of the curvature</code> of $C$ at $s$. The accelerator is \(\mathbf{a} = \dot{v}\mathbf{T} + \left( \frac{v^{2}}{\rho} \right)\mathbf{n}.\)</p> <h3 id="completion-and-promotion">Completion and Promotion</h3> <p>The laws of physics are Lorentz invariant, it means that physics quantities should transform “nicely” under Lorentz group. Given a 3-dimensional spatial infinitesimal displacement $d\mathbf{x}$, it needs to be <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">unified</code> with a fourth component $dt$ to form a Lorentz 4-vector $dx^{\mu}$. We say that $d\mathbf{x}$ is not relativistically <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">complete</code>. In Minkowski’s words,</p> <blockquote> <p>space by itself and time by itself have now faded away into mere shadows.</p> </blockquote> <p>The problem is that, all the quantities we are familiar with from Newtonian physics are not Lorentz invariant. For example, take a look at the definition of velocity, \(\mathbf{v}= \frac{d\mathbf{x}}{dt}\) where both $\mathbf{x}$ and $t$ changes under Lorentz transform, they are actually different components of a single Lorentz 4-vector, by no reason should $\mathbf{v}$ behave nicely under Lorentz transform. However, if we change $dt$ to $d\tau$, since $\tau$ is a Lorentz scalar and $\mathbf{x}$ is a 3-vector, the new definition will have better Lorentz transform property, it at least transforms as a 3-vector. Thus we define \(v_{r} = \frac{d\mathbf{x}}{d\tau}\) where the subscript $r$ is for relativistic. Now $v_{r}$ is the 3-dimensional, spatial component of some 4-vector velocity. Obviously this 4-vector velocity is \(u^{\mu}= \frac{dx^{\mu}}{d\tau}.\) This is what we should study in relativistic theory.</p> <p>We can further write everything in terms of non-relativistic quantities, escaping the use of $\tau$, as some authors like to do. For example, we can write \(\frac{dt}{d\tau}=\frac{1}{\sqrt{ 1-\left( \frac{d\mathbf{v}}{dt} \right)^{2} }}=:\gamma\) and the four velocity would become \(u^{\mu}= \gamma(1,\mathbf{v}).\)</p> <h3 id="electromagnetism-in-minkowski-space">Electromagnetism in Minkowski Space</h3> <p>Electromagnetic field is best described in the language of differential forms. However, electric field and magnetic field are given by forms of different ranks. When it comes to counting the rank of forms, there are usually two ways to do it,</p> <ol> <li>differential forms are what we integrate on a manifold, the dimension of the form must be the same as the dimension of the manifold on which it is integrated. For example, a form which we integrate on $\mathbb{R}^{3}$ is a 3-form.</li> <li>Forms also are maps that turns vectors into numbers. We can count the rank of a form by counting how may vectors does it acts on. For example, if a form maps $V\otimes V$ to real numbers, then it must be a 2-form.</li> </ol> <p>In our case, it is easiest to adopt the first method. Given a test charge of charge $q$, if it moves along a curve $C$ in electric field $E$, the work done to the charge is given by \(W = q \int_{C} E,\) thus $E$ must be a 1-form. Similarly, the magnetic flux is given by the integral of magnetic field on some surface $S$ \(\Phi=\int_{S} \, B\) thus $B$ must be a 2-form.</p> <p>However, that is what we have in 3-D space. In 3D space the basis of forms are $dx,dy$ and $dz$, turning to relativistic 4-D spacetime, we have an extra basis, namely $dt$. The expressions for electromagnetic field also needs some modification.</p> <p>Let’s start with the Lorentz force law. In non-relativistic case, the 3-dimensional Lorentz force is given by \(\mathbf{f}=q(\mathbf{E}+\mathbf{v}\times \mathbf{B})\) where the speed of light is set to $1$. We need to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">complete</code> this spatial force vector to Minkowski 4-vector force. Lucky for us there is a trick to do that. The 3-force can be written as \(\mathbf{f} = \frac{d\mathbf{p}}{dt} = \frac{d m_{0}\mathbf{u}}{dt}\) where $\mathbf{u}$ is the three component of the four velocity $u$, $\mathbf{p}$ is the three momentum. As discussed before, a natural completion of the three momentum is the four momentum so in order to complete $\mathbf{f}$ we should replace $\mathbf{p}$ by the four momentum $P$, and we need to substitute $t$ for the Lorentz scalar $\tau$. Thus the four-force become \(f^{\mu} = \frac{d}{d\tau}(m,\mathbf{p})=\left( \frac{dm}{dt},\gamma \frac{d\mathbf{p}}{dt} \right) = (f^{0},\gamma \mathbf{f}).\) To obtain $f^{0}$, notice that the inner product of $P$ and itself is a constant, \(P^{2} = \left\langle P,P \right\rangle =\text{const}\) and as a consequence, the four momentum $P$ is perpendicular to $dP / d\tau$. Since $P=m_{0} u$ and $m_{0}$ is a Lorentz scalar, we have \(\left\langle f,u \right\rangle =0= -\gamma f^{0} +\gamma^{2} \mathbf{f}\cdot \mathbf{v},\) from where we can work out $f^{0}$, \(f^{0} = \gamma \mathbf{f} \cdot \mathbf{v}.\)</p> <p>Putting everything together, we have complete the three-force to the Lorentz contravariant four-force, \(\boxed{ f = \gamma (\mathbf{f}\cdot \mathbf{v}, \mathbf{f}). }\) Substitute the expression for $\mathbf{f}$ as the Lorentz force, in terms of classical vector form of electro-magnetic field, we have \(f = \gamma q (\mathbf{E}\cdot \mathbf{v}, \mathbf{E}+\mathbf{v}\times \mathbf{B}).\) On the other hand, the force itself is a 1-form since we can integrate it along some path $C$ to evaluate the work done, \(W = \int_{C} \, f.\)</p> <p>Coming back to the case of Lorentz force, to simplify the notations we write $E = E_{i}dx^{i}$ and $B= B_{i&lt;j}\,dx^{i}dx^{j}$. The 1-form expression of the Lorentz force \(f = -\gamma q\, i_{\mathbf{v}}E dt + \gamma q \, (E_{i}dx^{i}-i_{\mathbf{v}}B)\) where $i_{\mathbf{v}}$ is the inner product with vector $\mathbf{v}$.</p> <p>The Lorentz 1-form $f$ can be written as \(f = -q i_{\mathbf{v}} F\) where \(F=E \wedge dt+B\) is the electromagnetic field strength 2-form. It was first introduced by Minkowski in 1907.</p> <h3 id="maxwells-equations">Maxwell’s Equations</h3> <p>In Minkowski space we have \(d = \mathbf{d}+dt\wedge \partial _{t}\) then half of the Maxwell equations are given by \(dF = 0\) Following the Poincare’s lemma, if the spacetime manifold is simply connected, \(F = dA\) for some 1-form $A$. Then we can further express $E,B$ in terms of $A$, we would recover the familiar expressions.</p> <p>To account for the other half of the Maxwell equation, we need to introduce the charged flux. Consider a charged fluid with local velocity $\mathbf{v}$, the current vector then is $\mathbf{j}=\rho \mathbf{v}$, $\rho$ is the density <strong>measured in the inertial system $x$</strong>. Let $\rho_{0}$ be the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">rest charge density</code>, that is, the density measured by someone moving instantaneously with the fluid, then \(\rho=\rho_{0} \gamma,\) this is due to the contraction of the space. Thus \(\mathbf{j} = \rho_{0}\gamma \mathbf{v}.\)</p> <p>Since $\rho_{0}$ is independent of the observer by definition, we can construct the so-called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">current 4-vector</code> \(J:= \rho_{0} u = (\rho,\rho \mathbf{v}) := (\rho,\mathbf{J}).\) We may then construct the associated <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">current 3-form</code> \(\mathcal{J}=i_{\mathbf{J}}\text{vol}^{4}\) where $\text{vol}^{r}$ is the 4-volume form. Then the other half of the Maxwell’s equations can be written as \(d\star F = 4\pi \mathcal{J}.\)</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="Geometry"/><category term="Minkowski"/><category term="Frankel"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Curvature and Special Relativity]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes on Coleman-Weinberg Potential</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Colemen-Weinberg-Potential/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes on Coleman-Weinberg Potential"/><published>2023-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Colemen-Weinberg-Potential</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Colemen-Weinberg-Potential/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="quantum-effective-action">Quantum Effective Action</h3> <p>The goal of this chapter is to introduce the quantum action and quantum potential. There are usually two kinds of quantum actions, one is the Wilsonian quantum action, where the higher momentum modes are integrated out to obtain an effective theory at a lower energy. For example, if we want to integrate a field out at the tree-level, we set $\hbar\to 0$ and in the path integral, only the classical solution contributes. We can replace the field by its classical solution to equation of motion in the Lagrangian. The other is the quantum effective actions which is a Legendre transformation of the generating functional of connected diagrams, we will talk more about it in the next section. When replacing the original action, the tree-level diagrams generated by the effective quantum action contains all the quantum corrections of the full theory (i.e. the original theory). The quantum effective action has a useful property that it can give us the vacuum expectation value (VEV) of the field operator with quantum correction. As we will see, Coleman-Weinberg potential is a special case of the effective action.</p> <p>There are in general three ways to calculate the effective action, namely</p> <ul> <li>by matching, that is to require \(\int \mathcal{D}\{\text{original dof}\} e^{iS} = \int \mathcal{D}\{\text{effective dof}\} e^{i\Gamma}\) where dof stands for the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">degree of freedom</code>, the LHS is the original theory, while the RHS is the effective theory, with different degree of freedom.</li> <li>by Legendre transformation, as will be shown in the next section, and</li> <li>by background field method, that is to separate the field into a static non-propagating background field $\phi_b$ and a dynamic propagating field $\tilde{\phi}$, the dynamic fields are the fluctuations around the background field. Integrate the fluctuations out will we have an effective potential $\Gamma[\phi_b]$, \(\int \mathcal{D} \phi e^{i S[\phi_b + \tilde{\phi}]} = e^{i\Gamma[\phi_b]}.\)</li> </ul> <p>Actually there is another way by guessing. Since the effective action must obey the same symmetries as the original action, people can try to write down all the local terms meet that criterion, leaving the coefficients to be determined by experiments.</p> <p>For the sake of simplicity we will constrain our discussion to $\phi^4$ model with real scalar fields.</p> <h3 id="quantum-action">Quantum Action</h3> <p>The partition function is \(Z[J] = \int \mathcal{D} \phi e^{iS[\phi] + i\int \phi J}\) where $S$ is the action, $J$ is the source, $\int \phi J$ is short for $\int dx^4 \phi(x) J(x)$. $\phi$ field is integrated out hence $Z$ is a functional of $J$ only.</p> <p>From it we can define $W[J]$ by \(Z[J] = e^{iW[J]} \implies W[J] = -i \ln Z[J],\) $W[J]$ is the summation of connected diagrams with source, refer to Mark Srednicki’s text book on quantum field theory. It is the generating functional of connected diagrams.</p> <p>The expectation value of $\phi$ in the presence of a source $J$ is given by \(\left\langle {\phi}_J \right\rangle=\frac{1}{Z} \int \mathcal{D} \phi e^{iS[\phi] + i\int \phi J} \phi = \frac{\delta W[J]}{\delta J(x)}\equiv \varphi,\) Note the difference between $\phi$ and $\varphi$, one is a operator while the other is a classical field. When compared to the classical dynamics, $W$ is similar to the Lagrangian $L$, $J$ is similar to $\dot{q}$, $\delta W / \delta J$ is similar to $\partial L / \partial \dot{q}$ which define a new variable. Perform the Legendre transformation we define a new functional, the quantum action, \(\boxed{ \Gamma[\varphi] = W[J] - \int J\varphi }\) note that $\Gamma$ is a functional of $\varphi$. We have \(\frac{\delta\Gamma}{\delta\varphi} = -J.\)</p> <ul> <li>$\Gamma[\varphi]$ generates the 1-particle irreducible (1PI) diagrams</li> <li>$W[J]$ generates connected diagrams</li> <li>$Z[J]$ generates all kinds of diagrams</li> </ul> <p><strong>Remark.</strong> There are also two definitions for the quantum effective action, one by requiring that the tree diagrams of the effective action includes all the quantum effects of the original action, and the other by the Legendre transformation. It is not obvious but they are equivalent to each other. To see this, we can first DEFINE $\Gamma[\phi]$ to be whose tree diagrams gives us all the quantum effects, then since $iW[J]$ also gives all the quantum effects with loops, we have \(e^{iW[J]} = \lim_{\hbar\to 0} \int \mathcal{D}\phi e^{i\Gamma[\phi]/\hbar}\) where the limiting isolates out the tree contribution, then use the fastest descent approximation we find $\Gamma$ can be written as the Legendre transformation of $W[J]$.</p> <p>To see that $\Gamma$ generates only the 1PI diagrams, recall that quantum effective action has the property that the tree-level graphs generated by it gives the complete scattering amplitude. Think of $\Gamma[\varphi]$ as in the place of action $S$, we will have a new path integral \(Z_\Gamma[J] = \int \mathcal{D}\phi e^{i\Gamma +i\int \phi J}.\) It will generate Feynman diagrams with sources, just like the original action $S$ does, only this time the tree diagrams alone is enough to give the complete information of the original theory. Thus $\Gamma$ must gives us exact propagators and exact n-point vertices, while the original action $S$ gives us the ordinary propagator and ordinary vertex. Also in order to calculate the exact n-point vertex, we need not consider the 1-particle reducible diagrams since any contribution from connected diagram can be written as a tree diagram comprised of two or more sub 1 particle IRREDUCIBLE diagrams.</p> <p><strong>Remark.</strong> The generating functionals such as $W[J]$ and $\Gamma[\varphi]$ are classical. In fact the language of path integral is highly classical, in the sense that each path, namely each field configuration is a c-field of space of time, instead of q-field.</p> <h4 id="tree-level-example">Tree-level Example</h4> <p>In the classical limit, taking the limit $\hbar \to 0$, the partition function become \(Z = \int \mathcal{D}\phi e^{iS + i\int \phi J}\) which receives dominant contribution from the stationary configuration, given by \(\frac{\delta}{\delta\phi}\left( S + \int \phi J \right) = 0 \implies \frac{\delta S}{\delta\phi} = - J\) which has a solution $\varphi$. Thus the partition function is \(Z = e^{iS+i\int \varphi J}\) up to a normalization factor. Since \(W[J] = -i \ln Z = S + \int \varphi J,\) we have \(\varphi = \frac{\delta W}{\delta J} = \left\langle {\phi}_J \right\rangle\) thus \(\Gamma[\varphi] = W - \int \varphi J = S[\varphi].\) At the tree-level, the quantum effective action and the original action are the same.</p> <h3 id="effective-potential">Effective Potential</h3> <p>In the classical dynamics, the vacuum (lowest energy state) configuration of the system is given by the minimum of the potential. In the quantum theory, we are sometimes interested in the vacuum expectation value (VEV) of the field operator $\phi$. In a quantum field theory, there is also have a potential term whose minimum gives the classical vacuum field configuration, however that’s not the full story, since in a quantum theory the field always fluctuates around the vacuum, giving rise to a correction to $\left\langle \phi \right\rangle$.</p> <p>We want a quantum effective potential which works like the classical potential, in the sense that its minimum corresponds to the field configuration of the vacuum, quantum corrections included. Luckily we already have something like that, i.e. the quantum effective action.</p> <p>Recall that the quantum effective action</p> <ul> <li>is a functional of $\varphi$, and $\varphi = \left\langle {\phi}_J \right\rangle$, meaning $\varphi$ is the expectation value of $\phi$ in the presence of a source term $J$</li> <li>satisfies ${\delta \Gamma}/{\delta \varphi} = J$ thus</li> <li>when $J=0$, the solution to ${\delta \Gamma}/{\delta \varphi} = J$ is the vev of $\phi$.</li> </ul> <p>Furthermore, assume that the vacuum has translation symmetry, meaning $\left\langle \phi \right\rangle$ is a constant in space and time, then we just need one number to denote the field configuration, we can define a function $\mathcal{V} _ {\text{eff}}$ whose minimum is the vev of $\phi$, \(\Gamma[\varphi]|_{\varphi = \text{const}} = -VT \mathcal{V}_{\text{eff}}(\varphi)\) where $V$ is the volume of the space and $T$ the extension of time, $\mathcal{V} _ {\text{eff}}(\varphi)$ is the quantum effective potential. We can see that $\mathcal{V} _ {\text{eff}}$ is a intensive quantity while $\Gamma$ is a extensive quantity, and ${\partial\mathcal{V}}/{\partial\phi} = 0$ reproduces ${\delta \Gamma}/{\delta \varphi} = 0$.</p> <h2 id="coleman-weinberg-potential">Coleman-Weinberg Potential</h2> <h3 id="background-fields">Background Fields</h3> <p>The method of background method is very useful for calculating beta functions and effective action. For a real scalar field $\phi$, the general idea is as following</p> <ul> <li>separate the field into the static background field $\phi_b$ and dynamic field $\phi$, $\phi \to \phi_b + \phi$. By static we mean it is not path-integrated, thus don’t propagate. It will simplify the calculation a lot.</li> <li>Define the corresponding action with background field $S_b[\phi_b;\phi]$, and resulting generating functional $W_b[\phi_b;\phi]$, and the effective action $\Gamma_b[\phi_b;\varphi]$, where $\varphi$ is defined to be the vev of $\phi$ in the presence of the background field $\phi_b$.</li> <li>$\Gamma_b[\phi_b;\varphi]$ has the useful property that \(\Gamma_b[\phi_b=\phi;0] = \Gamma_b[\phi_b=0;\varphi] = \Gamma[\varphi].\) The first term means that the effective action with background field $\phi_b = \phi$ and zero dynamic field $\varphi = 0$. Since the dynamic field will be set to zero at last, if a diagram has dynamic field external legs, it is also zero. It is similar to the Feynman diagrams with sources, when we set $J=0$ in the end then all the diagrams with a un-canceled source vanish.</li> </ul> <p>The reason why $\phi_b$ does not propagate can be seen in two ways, namely in the context of canonical quantization and path integral.</p> <p><strong>Canonical:</strong> the background field $\phi_b$ is regarded as a classical field, it is not quantized thus there is no such thing as $\phi_b$ propagator, <strong>Path integral:</strong> $\phi_b$ don’t fluctuate, means it is left out of the path integral, recall how we came to the propagator in the first place, it means $\phi_b$ don’t propagate.</p> <p>The action with a background field is defined as \(S_b[\phi_b;\phi] = \int d^4x\mathcal{L}(\phi_b+\phi),\) the partition function with source is \(\mathcal{Z}[\phi_b;J] = \int \mathcal{D}\phi \exp\{ i S_b[\phi_b;\phi]+i\int J\phi \} = \mathcal{Z}[J] e^{-i\int J\phi_b},\) note that the source only couples to the dynamic field. Since $\phi$ is integrated over, $\mathcal{Z}$ can only be a functional of $\phi_b, J$. Define the generating function as \(W_b[\phi_b;J] \equiv -i \ln \mathcal{Z}_b[\phi_b;J] \implies W_b[\phi_b;J] = W[J] - \int J\phi.\) Define \(\varphi_b(x) = \frac{\delta W_b[J]}{\delta J(x)}\) we have \(\varphi_b = \varphi - \phi_b\) which means that in the presence of a background field, $\left\langle \phi \right\rangle$ will be shifted by $\phi_b$, which is kind of natural.</p> <p>Now we need to define the effective action in the presence of a background field, by the means of Legendre transformation again. \(\Gamma_b [\phi_b;\varphi_b] = W_b - \int \frac{\delta W_b[J]}{\delta J}J = W_b - \int \varphi_b J\) you can check that \(\frac{\delta \Gamma_b[\phi_b;\varphi_b]}{\delta\varphi_b}= J .\) Replace $W_b[J]$ with its expression in terms of $W[J]$, we can check that \(\Gamma_b[\phi_b;\varphi_b] = W[J] - \int J (\varphi_b+\phi_b) = \Gamma[\phi_b + \varphi_b]\) so for example if we want to calculate $\Gamma[\eta(x)]$, we can set $\phi_b = \eta,\,\varphi = 0$ and use that to simplify calculations.</p> <h3 id="coleman-weinberg-potential-1">Coleman-Weinberg Potential</h3> <p>Consider the real scalar Lagrangian \(\mathcal{L} = -\frac{1}{2} \phi \partial^2\phi - \frac{1}{2} m^2\phi^2-\frac{1}{4!}\phi^4\) the question is, when $m = 0$, will the quantum effects modify the shape of the potential?</p> <p>Introduce a background field $\phi \to \phi_b +\phi$, take it into the action and expand, keep in mind that the path integral is over field $\phi$, we have \(\begin{align} e^{i\Gamma[\phi_b]} &amp;= e^{i\int d^4 x (-\frac{1}{2} \phi_b \partial^2 \phi_b-V(\phi_b))} \\ \\ &amp;\times\int \mathcal{D}\phi e^{i \int d^4 x (-\frac{1}{2} \phi \partial^2 \phi -V(\phi_b) - \phi V'(\phi_b)-\frac{1}{2}V''[\phi_b]\phi^2-\frac{1}{3!}V'''[\phi_b]\phi^3-\cdots)}. \end{align}\) In the path integral, one of the terms in the Lagrangian, i.e. $\int \mathcal{D} \phi e^{i\phi V’}$ can be thrown away because we only need to consider 1PI diagrams in the calculation of $\Gamma$, while the Feynman diagram given by $\phi V’(\phi_b)$ will never contribute to the 1PI diagrams. For the same reason we can also discard $\phi^3$ term in the Lagrangian. At one loop, there will be no contributions from $\phi^4$ and higher terms either. Hence we are left with \(e^{i\Gamma[\phi_b]} = e^{i\int d^4 x (-\frac{1}{2} \phi_b \partial^2 \phi_b-V(\phi_b))} \int \mathcal{D} e^{i \int d^4 x (-\frac{1}{2} \phi \partial^2 \phi -\frac{1}{2}V''[\phi_b]\phi^2)}.\) use the master formulae in QFT \(\int\mathcal{D}\phi\exp\left\{ i \int d^4x (\phi M \phi) \right\} = \mathcal{N}\frac{1}{\text{det}^{M}}\) we have \(e^{i\Gamma[\phi_b]} = \mathcal{N}e^{i\int d^4 x (-\frac{1}{2} \phi_b \partial^2 \phi_b-V(\phi_b))} \text{det}^{-1/2}(\partial^2 + V''(\phi_b))\) In order to calculate the functional determinant, we need to put it in a specific representation, such as the position representation or the momentum representation, to turn $\partial^2 + V’’(\phi_b)$ into a matrix, then calculate the determinant of that infinite dimensional matrix. Writing \(\Gamma[\phi_b] = \int d^4 x (-\frac{1}{2} \phi_b \partial^2 \phi_b-V(\phi_b)) + \Delta \Gamma[\phi_b],\) where \(i\Delta \Gamma[\phi_b] = -\frac{1}{2}\ln \det (\partial^2 +V''(\phi_b)) + \text{const}.\) With the help of identity \(\ln \det M = \ln \prod_i \lambda_i = \sum_i \ln \lambda_i = \text{tr } {\ln M}\) where $\lambda_i$ are the eigenvalues of $M$, we have \(i\Delta \Gamma[\phi_b] = -\frac{1}{2} \text{tr } {\ln (\partial^2 +V''(\phi_b))} + \text{const}.\) Next we assume that $\phi_b$ is a const in space-time, and define \(m_{\text{eff}}^2(\phi_b) \equiv V''(\phi_b),\) calculate the functional determinant in the representation of $x$, with the help of \(\mathbb{1}= \int \frac{dp^4}{(2\pi)^4} \left\lvert k \right\rangle \left\langle{k}\right\rvert\) we have \(\begin{align} i\Delta \Gamma[\phi_b] &amp;= -\frac{1}{2}\int d^4 x \left\langle{x}\right\rvert \ln\left( 1+\frac{V''}{\partial^2} \right) \left\lvert{x}\right\rangle +\text{const}\\ &amp;= -\frac{1}{2}\int d^4 x \int\frac{d^4 k}{(2\pi)^4}\ln\left( 1-\frac{m_{\text{eff}}^2}{k^2} \right)+\text{const} \end{align}\) where $\int d^4 x = VT$ is the space-time volume of the system.</p> <p>The integral over momentum is divergent, we will render it finite by a hard cut-off, that is to Wick rotate the system into Euclidean space and insert the momentum cut-off $\Lambda$, yielding \(\begin{align} \Delta\Gamma[\phi_b] &amp;= -VT \frac{2\pi^2}{2(2\pi)^4} \int_0^\Lambda dk_E k_E^3 \ln(1+\frac{m_{\text{eff}}^2}{k_E3^2}) +\text{const}\\ &amp;= - \frac{VT}{128\pi^2} \left( 2 m_{\text{eff}}^2 \Lambda^2 + 2m_{\text{eff}}^4 \ln\frac{m_{\text{eff}}^2}{\Lambda^2}+\text{const}\right) \end{align}\) where $k_E$ is the Wick-rotated momentum and we have used the relation $\Lambda \gg m_{\text{eff}}$. The effective potential accordingly is \(V_{\text{eff}} = V(\phi_b) + c_1 + c_2 m_{\text{eff}}^2 + \frac{1}{64\pi^2} m_{\text{eff}}^4 \ln\frac{m_{\text{eff}}^2}{c_3}\) where $c_1,c_2,c_3$ are some $\Lambda$-dependent constants. They are independent of $\phi_b$ thus in general are not of interests to us. For example, $c_2 = \Lambda^2 / 64\pi^2$.</p> <p>Next we need to add the counter terms to the potential \(V(\phi) = \frac{1}{2}m_R^2(1+\delta_m)\phi^2 +\frac{\lambda_R}{4!}(1+\delta_\lambda)\phi^4 +\Lambda_R (1+\delta_\Lambda),\) with all the counter terms starting at 1-loop level, that is of $\mathcal{O}(\lambda_R)$. $m_{\text{eff}}^2$ is still defined as $V’’$.</p> <p>What about the renormalization conditions?</p> <ul> <li>The question we want to ask is how the quantum corrections change the shape of the potential, when the mass term is zero, thus we require $\lambda_R^2 = 0$</li> <li>$V(0) = 0 \implies \Lambda_R = 0$</li> <li>$\lambda_R = V’’’’(\phi_R)$ for some arbitrary fixed scale $\phi_R$</li> </ul> <p>They will fix the counter terms, plugging them in gives \(\boxed{ V_{\text{eff}}(\phi) = \frac{1}{4!}\phi^4\left\{ \lambda_R + \frac{3 \lambda_R^2}{32\pi^2}\left[ \ln \left( \frac{\phi^2}{\phi_R^2}-\frac{25}{6} \right) \right] \right\} }\) which is known as Coleman-Weinberg potential.</p> <p>Now having the effective potential at hand, we can answer the question: does the quantum correction change the vacuum expectation value of $\phi$? Originally, without the quantum correction, the minimum of the potential is at $\phi = 0$ since there is no quadratic term and only a quartic term. With quantum correction, the vev of $\phi$ is given by the minimum of the effective potential, which is the Coleman-Weinberg potential, which is minimized when \(\lambda_R \ln \frac{\left\langle \phi^{2} \right\rangle}{\phi_R^2} = \frac{11}{3} \lambda_R - \frac{32}{3}\pi^2.\) which gives a nonzero $\left\langle \phi \right\rangle$. It means now we have a double-well potential, instead of the original single-well potential, due to the quantum correction.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="ColemanWeinbergPotential"/><category term="EffectiveTheory"/><category term="Coleman"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Quantum Effective Action]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Caratheodory’s approach to Thermodynamics</title><link href="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Thermodynamics-in-Terms-of-Foliations/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Caratheodory’s approach to Thermodynamics"/><published>2023-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Thermodynamics-in-Terms-of-Foliations</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://baiyangzhang.github.io/blog/2023/Thermodynamics-in-Terms-of-Foliations/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>Disclaimer: Nothing in this note is original. Including the figures.</p> </blockquote> <p>Around 1909, Caratheodory was urged by Max Born to come up with an axiomatic treatment of thermodynamics. As a result, Caratheodory made use of Frobenius’s theorem and constructed a rather mathematical treatment of thermodynamics. In this note we will only superficially look at the theory.</p> <p>Consider a system of fluids separated into $n$ chambers by “diathermous” membranes, namely membranes that allow only the passage of heat, not fluids, as shown in the figure below. Each chamber has its own pressure and volume, denoted by $p_{i}$ and $v_{i}$.</p> <p><img src="/img/chamber.png" alt="fluid"/></p> <p>We assume that each state of the system is a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">thermal equilibrium</code> state. We assume that the membranes are stretchy enough so that in the equilibrium state the pressure is uniform between different chambers, $p_{1}=p_{2}-\dots=p_{n}$. The equations of state (for instance, $p_{i}v_{i}=n_{i}RT$) will allow us to eliminate all but one pressure, say $p_{1}$. Then the state is described by $n+1$ parameters, $p_{1},v_{1},\dots,v_{n}$. The uniform temperature is given by the n-tuple from the equation of state. It is important to assume that there is a global <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">internal energy</code> function $U$ of the system that can be used instead $p_{1}$. The equilibrium state is then described by $n+1$ parameters, \(v_{0}:= U,v_{1},\dots,v_{n}.\) Each $v_{0}$ will fix a point in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">state space</code>, namely the space of all the possible states. The state space then would be a $n+1$ dimensional manifold.</p> <p>Next consider a sequence of states, forming a continuous change of the states, the change is slow enough that each state during the change is itself an equilibrium state. Such a slow change of states traces a curve in the state space. Such transition is sometimes called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">quasi-static</code>.</p> <p>We shall also consider non-quasi-static transitions, such as “stirring”. In the space of states, such a transition starts at some point $x$ and ends at some other points $y$, but since there is no sequence of equilibrium states intermediating the initial and final states, there is no path in the state space joining $x$ to $y$ (since each point in the state space represents a equilibrium state by construction). These corresponds to irreversible processes. Schematically, we shall draw such transitions by a <em>dash line</em> joining $x$ to $y$.</p> <p>On the state manifold (the manifold of state space), we assume the existence of a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">work 1-form</code> $W$, describing the work done <em>by</em> the system due to a change of volume. \(W := \sum_{i=1}^{n} p_{i} \,dv_{i} = \sum_{i=1}^{n} p_{i}(U,v_{1},\dots,v_{n})\, dv_{i}.\) Recall that when a form is closed, the integral of it along some boundary is always zero, thanks to the Stokes theorem. It is important to note that here the work 1-form $W$ is not supposed to be closed, thus if the system undergoes a loop of state transition, the total energy done by the system may not be zero. The line integral of $W$ is in general dependent upon the path joining the endpoint states.</p> <p>We also assume the existence of a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">heat 1-form</code> \(Q:= \sum_{i=1}^{n} Q_{i}(U,v_{1},\dots,v_{n})\,dv_{i}\) representing the heat added or removed from the system. At first glance it seems strange that $Q$ should depend on $dv_{i}$, we will say more about it later. Again, $Q$ is not supposed to be closed, and we shall always assume that $Q$ never vanishes. Note that in some other texts $Q$ is derived, rather than postulated as here.</p> <p><strong>Remark.</strong> In some textbooks the 1-form $W$ and $Q$ are denoted by $d$ with a bar crossing the upper part, to show that they are different from usual $dQ$ and $dW$. It is very misleading, since that in the language of differential forms, $dW$ would be an exact form, but the work 1-form is in no means exact. The same goes for the heat 1-form.</p> <p><strong>The first law of thermodynamics</strong> says that \(dU = Q-W.\) <strong>This is the conservation of energy</strong>.</p> <hr/> <p>Next we show some elementary changes of states, and how the look like in the state space.</p> <ol> <li>Heating at constant volume. It is shown as $\gamma_{I}$ in the figure below. The work 1-form vanishes when evaluated on the tangent $\dot{\gamma}_{I}$. The conservation of energy says that $dU = Q$.</li> <li>Quasi-static adiabatic process. There is no heat added to the system, thus $Q=0$ along the path. It is shown by $\gamma_{I I}$.</li> <li>Stirring at constant volume. Since it is not quasi-static we cannot represent it by a curve in the state space. We can only schematically represent it by connecting $x$ and $y’$ with a dashed curve. $Q,W$ make no sense for this process.</li> </ol> <p><img src="/img/transition.jpg" alt="transition"/></p> <p><strong>Definition.</strong> A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">submersion</code> is a smooth mapping $f:M\to N$ from an $m$-dimensional manifold $M$ to an $n$-dimensional manifold $N$, $m&gt;n$, under which for any point $p\in M$, the map $f_{\ast}:T_{p}M\to T_{f(p)}N$ is onto.</p> <p>A basic example of submersion is the so-called canonical submersion from $\mathbb{R}^{m}$ to $\mathbb{R}^{n}$ with $m&gt;n$, given coordinate system $(x)$ on both the manifolds, the smooth mapping is defined by \(f:(x^{1},\dots,x^{n},\dots,x^{m})\to (x^{1},\dots,x^{n}).\)</p> <p>The above figure suggests us to treat $U$ as a distinct dimension, separate it from the rest $v$ coordinates. We shall <strong>assume</strong> that there is a connected $n$-manifold (one dimension less than $M$, the state space), the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mechanical manifold</code> $V$. We assume there is a smooth map $\pi:M\to V$, which is a submersion. By the main theorem on submanifold, if $v\in V$ then $\pi^{-1}(v)$ is a 1-dimensional embedded submanifold of $M$. The manifold $V^{n}$ will be covered by a collection of <em>local</em> coordinates $v^{1},\dots,v^{n}$. <strong>$V$ takes the place of the volume coordinates used before.</strong> The curves $\pi^{-1}(v)$ corresponds to the heating and cooling at constant volume. Obviously on $\pi^{-1}(p)$ we have $W=0$. The $n+1$ tuple $U,v^{1},\dots,v^{n}$ forms a local coordinates system for $M$.</p> <hr/> <p>A <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cyclic</code> process is one that starts and ends at the same state. The <em>second law of thermodynamics</em>, according to Lord Kelvin, can be stated as:</p> <blockquote> <p>In no quasi-static cyclic process, can a quantity of heat be converted <strong>entirely</strong> into its mechanical equivalent of work.</p> </blockquote> <p>The same law, according to Caratheodory(1909), says that</p> <blockquote> <p>In every neighborhood of every state $x$ there are states $y$ that are not accessible from $x$ via quasi-static <strong>adiabatic</strong> paths, that is, paths along which $Q=0$.</p> </blockquote> <p>It is not meant to be obvious, but Caratheodory’s assumption is weaker than Kelvin’s,</p> \[\boxed{ \text{Kelvin's assumption} \implies \text{Caratheodory's assumption.} }\] <p>Take the path $\gamma_{I}$ in the previous figure for example, assume $\gamma_{I}$ goes form $x$ to $y$. If there were <em>quasi-static</em> and <em>adiabatic</em> process going from $x$ to $y$, call it path $\gamma_{I’}$, then along $\gamma_{I’}$ we would have \(\int_{\gamma_{I'}} \, W = \int_{\gamma_{I'}} \,Q-dU = \int_{\gamma_{I'}} \,-dU=-\int_{\gamma_{I}} \,dU=-\int_{\gamma_{I}} \,Q\) where in the second-to-last step we changed from path to $\gamma_{I}$, which is allow since $dU$ is closed. But this would say that the heat energy pumped into the system has been <strong>entirely</strong> converted into mechanical work, which contradicts the Kelvin! Thus there is no such path $\gamma_{I’}$.</p> <p><strong>An adiabatic quasi-static process is a path in the state space such that $Q=0$ along it.</strong> We know that if $Q=0$ were a<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"> holonomic constraint</code>, then there would exist other states $y$ in the neighborhood of $x$, that is not accessible from $x$ along any adiabatic path. All the accessible points would lie on the maximal leaf through $x$. The question is, does having inaccessible points in turn implies that the distribution $Q=0$ is integrable? Caratheodory showed that it is indeed the case. In the following we have a pure mathematical result:</p> <p><strong>Caratheodory’s theorem.</strong> Let $\theta$ be a 1-form which is smooth and non-vanishing on an $n$-dimensional manifold $M$, and suppose that $\theta=0$ is not integrable, thus at some point $x_{0}$ we have \(\theta \wedge d\theta \neq 0.\) Then there is a neighborhood $U$ of $x_{0}$ such that any point $y$ in $U$ can be joined to $x_{0}$ by a piecewise smooth path that is always tangent to the distribution.</p> <p>Roughly speaking, since $\theta=0$ is not holonomic, the distribution given by $\theta=0$ is not integrable, then at $x_{0}$, we can find two vectors $X,Y$ tangent to the distribution but their Lie bracket $[X,Y]$ is not in the distribution. They will allow us to move away from the distribution and reach any point $y$ in the neighborhood. A detailed proof can be found in Frankel.</p> <p>We thus conclude from Caratheodory’s mathematical theorem, together with his version of the second law of thermodynamics, that the <strong>adiabatic distribution $Q=0$ is integrable</strong>.</p> <p>If the reader is interested in the construction of entropy, one of the most important concepts in thermodynamics, from Caratheodory’s mathematical approach, please refer to Frankel and books referred therein.</p>]]></content><author><name>Baiyang Zhang</name></author><category term="Geometry"/><category term="Physics"/><category term="Thermodynamics"/><category term="Notes"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Disclaimer: Nothing in this note is original. Including the figures.]]></summary></entry></feed>